Portland City Council to order on
Tuesday,
April 14th.
Please stand with me if you wish to,
to show our respect to the multicultural republic
that is the United States of America.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of
America, and to the Republic for which it stands,
one nation, under God, indivisible, with
liberty and justice for all.
Thank you. Mr. City Manager, may we have a roll call, please?
Oh, yes.
Councilor Scott?
Here.
Councilor Walker?
Councilor Coleman?
Here.
Mayor Tipton?
I am here.
Councilor Pride?
Here.
Councilor West?
Councilor Matthews?
Yes, sir.
Thank you. We're all here. We're being joined by some more guests.
Maybe that will continue.
So I just wanted to explain how this evening's going to work
so that everybody's clear. And I also want to say that it is
truly my privilege to be with all of you for
this gathering in which we are going to engage in a democratic
process. Aren't we fortunate? So thank you.
Because we didn't get to hear it last week, we're hearing a presentation from the
schools on what is now the school board's budget.
Then the councilors will likely have some questions.
It could be that the city manager be asked to make clarifications, but
mostly we will stick to councilor questions.
Then we're moving to public comment, and I'll tell you about that in
one moment.
And then the council will have a discussion.
It's a workshop, so the council doesn't do any voting tonight,
but we'll have a discussion, and from the discussion, I
think it will become clear how our councilors are feeling about the school
budget, and whether we'd like to offer any additional guidance on
that.
I wanted to read our rules of public comment,
and remind folks that at our workshops, which
tonight is, we don't have an open public comment
period. So your comments need to be confined to
items that are on our agenda for the workshop.
Comment is three minutes. You're going to see the timer
running when you're making comments.
You'll get a reminder at 30 seconds that you might want to
start wrapping up, and also,
if you want to make comments that are less than three minutes long, go for it.
The other thing I would say is we don't have clapping or booing, and we don't do
ceding of time to others. Each person, individual,
gets three minutes.
So those are our rules.
I was just wondering if...
I think there may be some clarification ahead of the
authorities of the school board, and the
authorities of the council, and I think it's
singular authority. But I think at this time,
we don't need to talk about that until we get rolling.
So let's hear the budget presentation from the schools.
All right. Good evening, everyone.
My name is Abigail Ketchen, and I serve as the Director of Finance for the
South Portland School Department.
And tonight I'm going to share with you our FY27 board budget.
I'm going to give an overview,
and then I'll be turning it over to Chair DeAngelis for a board request
of the city.
Excuse me, is Chair DeAngelis with us?
Yes.
She's outside.
She stepped out.
Yeah.
I will go down and see if I can find her.
All right. Well, she's welcome to join at any time, but I
just note her absence.
All right. So I want to take you through a little bit of our before and
after.
You can see our
overall budget. What I first want to direct your attention to is the
initial budget, FY27. That's the column on the
far right-hand.
So as we began our budget process, we began with a
roll-forward budget, just all current costs rolling forward to the
next year. We
then added other costs that we deemed necessary, capital
expenses, other increases,
and the like. And where we found
ourselves
was at $84 million.
And how that would have worked
out had we stayed there would've been an
over 21% tax increase for the school share.
I think as we can all understand, that is a likely
untenable
situation.
And so throughout the past few months,
we have gone through a very difficult process,
a very painful process.
We've had
many conversations
that have been very tough, and
we have years of context that sort of led us here,
and I'm not going to go through all of that tonight.
But nevertheless, we've faced where we are
atAnd through an extraordinarily painful
process, we have made a decision to close
one of our beloved elementary schools.
And as you can imagine, that's extremely painful for many families.
And we've also gone through
whether to redistrict or reconfigure.
And at this point, we are kind of working through what that will
ultimately look like. But we have paused on some of
our
current push towards reconfiguring quickly.
In addition to closing a school, we are
also proposing
reducing our staff overall by about 12%.
So I think it has really taken a lot for us to get to
a point where we can offer the taxpayers a 6%
increase for the school share.
And we certainly hope that our efforts are recognized.
We value all stakeholders, including all of our taxpayers,
and we've really gone through a lot to get here.
And then I just also want to note, one of the reasons why it's sort
of additionally painful to get to that 6% is that
our fund balance has been depleted over the years, and so then
we no longer have that amount to buffer the
taxpayer experience.
To take you through some of the reductions that we faced.
So we are currently, in order to get to that 6% mark,
we are looking at losing 11% of our teachers,
10% of our ed techs and clerks,
one principal, 14% of our service
folks, and 23% of our directors.
And then overall, on the whole, that works out to about 12%
for staff overall.
So the main update is we remain
dedicated to our mission.
As tough as it is, we are still a school district.
We're still here for our students.
We still care about academic excellence and all that students
will have opportunities for in the future. That's still there.
But we are at a point where, indeed, we are closing a school,
and letting go of 12% of our staff.
And with that... Oops, I'm sorry.
I'd like to turn it over to our chair, DeAngelis.
Hello, Madam Chair.
Hi there.
Didn't get to say hello to you earlier.
Thank you, and hello to everybody, and thank you for having us tonight.
The board took two actions last night, passed two
actions, and they are in front of you.
So the first is asking for the council to
approve considering increasing the school board portion of the tax
increase from 6% to 7%,
and the purpose for that would be to add to contingency
towards seeding the school fund balance.
And as
Abigail Ketchen just said, we
have no money in reserve at this point.
So
this goal was in an effort to specifically help
us to begin to build our school fund balance.
So that was the first. And the second action that the board took was
to consider asking the city council
to fund snow plowing and school resource officers, and
that was to the tune...
We specifically passed an amount of $360,000
to ask
for that to be used for
$220 for our school resource officers and
approximately
140,000.
I shouldn't have said $220.
$220,000 to fund our school
resource services and 140,000 for
snow removal
for the
next budget year, the 2026-27.
So that was the purpose, to utilize
that offset to add to the contingency .
The first one was to add to the... Well, let me just
see here. Eventually seeding the school fund.
Okay, that's the
first one, considering the school portion of the tax increase from
6% to 7%, and
that would be for the purpose of adding to our
contingency and eventually seeding the school fund balance.
The second item is for the city
to absorb the cost for the 26-27
budget year for snow plowing at 140,000 and
school resource officers at 220,000,
to the tune of 360,000. So we passed both those
requests last night.
And if anybody has any questions, I'm happy to answer them.
Thank you.
Is that the end of the presentation? Okay.
We're going to move to council questions in a moment.
Remember, I wanted to say, because I saw quite a few folks come in,
that we are going to have a public comment period after the
councilors have a chance to ask questions.
You probably won't be surprised to learn that it is three minutes long.
You'll see timers here that show you how much time you have.
And
yeah, I think that's about it.
The other thing is I said we'd have some opportunities for
clarification.Seeing
what the school board chair just
presented, I saw that you had presented based
on the board moving this yesterday, that the ask
for a 1% increase would be for the contingency.
I just wanted to make something clear, and I'm going to make it clear by reading
aloud from what we have posted. "If the council elects to
increase or decrease the school budget amount, it can only do so
to the bottom line number per state law and city charter.
Council cannot dictate which specific items to add, cut,
increase, decrease, including whether or not a school building
is closed. Should a majority of the council opt to increase or
decrease the bottom line school budget amount, the
school board would then meet to discuss how it would make additional
cuts if decreased, or spend the additional funds if
increased." So,
it is interesting to hear your school board's
intention for using an extra 1%,
but it is not anything that the council dictates, and so I want to
make that clear.
All right, councilors.
Oh, yes.
Again, Rosemary DeAngelis, school board.
I just wanted to say that was specific for the
board, and that was specific because that was the
way to engage in discussion and to get the vote.
So that was how we got to a unanimous vote, was with
the commitment amongst ourselves.
It was not about coming to the council for that approval, but the
commitment amongst ourselves that that's how the money would be used.
So that's why, and we just included that before you
tonight. Thank you.
Thanks very much.
Okay, councilors, a volley of questions, or at least
a few. Anyone want to go first?
Councilor Scott, thank you very much.
Thank you. I'm happy to go first.
I think I'd like to understand between the budget,
which I think is a 6% increase, and the additional request,
what the actual percentage is that the school board
is asking for in terms of a school board budget, and
what that tax impact is. Appreciating that there are sort of a
couple of different requests in there, but I think in the end, it
is sort of
attributable to the school portion of our overall city budget,
and would like to make sure that we, as a council, understand
those numbers, that request, and that we are
approving or reviewing
sort of a single number that is ultimately attributable to the
school portion of our budgets.
Hi. Thank you for the question. So for our bottom
line budget, we would add about 540,000, and that would lead
to a tax increase from 6% to
7% for the school share.
Sorry. That's inclusive of
both the six-
No
... to 7%.
No.
And, I guess-No, that is the... Okay. Yeah. So the two requests, the first one is to increase
from 6% to 7%. For us, the dollar amount to the bottom
line is about 540,000. And then we're additionally asking
for the city to cover two school resource officers and snow
plowing.
For us, that would not impact our bottom line, but obviously it would
impact
the city's bottom line.
Okay, to clarify-
Well, actually-
Yeah, I don't see that as...
If it,
quote-unquote, "Impacts the city's bottom line," I think it
should be attributable to the school board portion, so therefore
I'm trying to make sure that there's transparency between the
school portion and the city portion, and that that
is a clear number that is allocated, even if it's
sort of under the city's work.
So I'm-
Yeah, no, we understand.
Thank you.
We are all one city.
We definitely understand that, and we're making this request within
that understanding.
And so, sorry, do you have those numbers of what the percentage and the amount
would be with-
For 360,000, it would be somewhere
around .75-ish. It would be between a half and 1%,
because a half percent, it works out to about 255.
It'd be between that.
Okay.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Other councilors with questions?
Councilor Walker?
If you don't mind hopping back up. So I have a couple of questions.
So my first question is,
the 540,000, so if we were to grant the
request and go to 7%,
is the 540,000
sufficient to ward off
ending right back up here next year? Because it is only to seed the fund balance.
It's not necessarily to... And the fund balance, part of how we ended
up here is the fund balance had consistently been spent down-
Mm-hmm
... to kind of help balance the budget.
So I'm just curious about kind of long-term plans to
avoid...
Yeah, no, it's a very good question.
I think the 540 towards fund balance,
it's important that we do that, but in terms of not
being here next year,
I think the biggest
reason why we hope to not be here in the same position next year is due to
our massive financial adjustments that we've made this year,
letting go of 12% of staff and closing a school.
It would take an extraordinary set of circumstancesTo
be in this position again in a year.
If that answers that.
It does. Can I ask a couple follow-up questions?
Yeah. Sure.
So I know that this year it looks like there's going to be close to, well,
at least a $2 million deficit. Is that what I'm understanding from the
meetings that I've been following?
No.
Right now for FY26,
I've been presenting a range of possibilities.
There's truly a set of unknowns.
Okay.
Right now the range is anywhere from a very small deficit upwards
to $1 to $1.5 million. I've had conversations
with the city's finance director where I've suggested think about $2 million
just in case.
And I would add that the $2 million that I've thought of as
the
biggest hole we could be in, does include our nutrition deficits
from both the prior fiscal year and this year.
So I feel like the $2 million is probably all-inclusive.
But I understand there's a $3 million figure out there, and I totally
understand
being conservative given our situation as a whole, and some additional
unknowns that we still have ahead of us this fiscal year.
So with that, and this is the second year, I think, in a row that
there's been a deficit coming out of the net.
Third.
Third. Okay. So with the budget work that you all have done, and
first, I want to commend you all. All of you in this room.
I want to commend the staff, I want to commend the board, I want to commend the
parents, the teachers, all of the staff of the schools that have come up and
fought so hard for our children. I have just been a resident watching this play
out, and just you all deserve to be commended.
So well done to all of you.
But...
Not but, and.
With that, the work that you did on the budget this year,
what level of confidence do you have that we're not going to end up in that same
type of situation again next year?
Mm-hmm. Yeah, so one thing that I believe our FY27
budget does is it adjusts for what I feel is prior
years' under-budgeting.
Okay.
Just as we've looked through just all types of costs, there are many
costs that we are just consistently over budget.
And so what
I've done, and then our team, we've really taken a careful view.
We've looked at the increases that have happened from
years ago to now, really analyzed the increase and
how it's changing.
And that's informed the art and the science of budgeting.
But I do feel confident that this is a
more realistic budget than I think we've had in a few years.
Okay.
Barring unknowns, including world events.
Yeah.
I understand that.
Yes.
Good evening. I'm Johanna Prince. I'm the assistant superintendent.
I think another important thing that we have proposed to the
board, and I believe the board is in support of, is that we
need to set some new fiscal policies as a school
board that both look at how we set up
the timeline of a budget development, how we are willing to
think about fund balance moving forward, and those are some
guardrails that I think all of us collectively believe will
help decrease the likelihood that we are here again,
and sort of rebuild the trust with the council and with our
constituents as we move forward. And again, that is
ultimately a board decision, but I think the board has been interested in that
idea, and we'll certainly take it forward in policy.
Okay. Thank you.
Okay.
A lot of other folks have a turn.
Thank you. Counselors, questions? Counselor Matthews.
Madam Mayor, how deep are we going into these questions at this time?
I
left the school board for a reason. You know that.
That's why I'm running for city council.
So but, I just want to know how deep we're going.
Well, let-
Because our job is not to micromanage, but
certainly some serious questions to ask, and if anybody's going to
do it, it's probably going to be me.
Mm-hmm.
So I just want to know, are we going to wait for public comment and then dive deep,
or are we doing it now?
The questions were supposed to be for them, not me.
Well, I understand.
Director. I think we are dealing with some fairly
unusual circumstances that we recognize across the community.
Having said that, you are absolutely right.
You and I both are no longer on school board,
and we've already mentioned the authority of the school board versus the council.
So let us try to keep our questions
focused, and then after we hear from members of the public,
which I assume we will, including potentially school board members,
then I think maybe we do a deeper dive.
And also, I think if we have additional questions, it will still be
appropriate to ask them.
All right. I'll pass it this time.
All right. Any other counselors with focused
questions?
Well...
Yes, Counselor Pride.
Sure.
I also want to applaud the work of the board. I know it's been difficult.
I know how it is to go through very, very difficult budgets and have
people not happy with you, and I want to applaud those people who
also
tried really hard to stay calm and give
constructive criticism. But I have a question.
So
if the council, because I want to be
honest with the people about what is being paid for
the schools and what's being paid for the city.
So if the council, instead of
plowing and paying for the police officers,
were to give you another percent,
what would you do with the excess there? And I guess, yeah.
And it's a two-part question, because the second part is, if the council were
to suggest a 2% increase over the 6%,
I-
And this is going to be difficult not to make a leading question, but
there's this fear that it won't pass, because
I feel Ed Cobb staring at me with daggers right
now.
Go next.
But then I also feel like there are lots of people who are unhappy with other
decisions the school board has made, which will make it difficult.
So
I guess the question is,
what are you going to do to help it pass? I guess.
I mean, it sounds like we have some communication work to do, and I think
we're here for that as much as possible in terms of explaining how we
got here, and how we believe we can improve moving forward, and how we
think that an increase can
be
helpful towards
a list of other actions that we're taking to solve our own problems.
But otherwise, exactly what is done with it, that's a bigger decision
with leadership and in our school board.
Okay. Councilor West, not a question? Not at this time?
All right. Thank you. Councilor Coleman.
Mine was also very similar. I still don't quite understand
what Councilor
Scott was saying.
You're requesting 7% increase going from
6.1 to seven, however, you're asking us to fund,
the city,
$360,000 for snow removal
and the officers, and then you're
asking us for another
$540,000-
No.No.No.
For the seeding? No.
No.
So where is that seed going to be coming from?
You're finding that from your own budget then?
Yeah. So if we move our tax increase from 6% to
7%, we will add another 540-
To seed
... raised from the taxpayers.
Okay. Thank you.
Thank you. I'm glad you clarified that. Thank you.
I have
actually just two questions, but they're two sides of the same coin.
In the budget presentation that we just saw, with the knowledge
that the board has not officially voted for this
but has put out indication that it will
slow down reconfiguration, in this budget, do
we see any of the costs of launching
reconfiguration that would've been in there in the first year?
And conversely, here's the other side, do we see any
first-year savings that we're no longer seeing,
or is everything still as if you were going to reconfigure because it
hasn't been an official vote of the board yet?
Yeah. So our current proposed budget, our board budget,
is financially neutral, whether we reconfigure or redistrict.
In both cases, we're moving,
so in both cases, we have moving charges.
In both cases, we have stipends for the teachers to move classrooms.
So there are a lot of the moving aspects of this that are equally
built in. So for us, it is the same budget either way for
FY27.
Okay.
Okay. Well, that makes it a little easier. Thank you.
All right. We're going to-- Oh, wait.
Sorry.
Councilor Scott.
Can I ask a-
One more question
... follow-up?
Yeah.
I've been trying to follow as many of the
school board meetings as possible, and I wonder if you could
clarify.
My understanding of the reconfiguration process and budgeting
considerations was that I think there was some consideration
that reconfiguration actually might cost more
money going forward than be a savings, as I think was
originally presented in February.
So I wonder if you can clarify the neutrality of that as a
budget configuration aside from the policy
configuration or policy-
Yeah
... consideration of reconfiguration. Thank you.
Yeah. I mean, I think that was one of the criticisms
was that we may not be fully aware of all unknown costs.
That's not lost on me.
And what I can say at this point is that we do have more time.
Thank you.
I appreciate that.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
Everybody's good. We're going to move to public comment.
Again, three minutes.
We don't have booing or clapping. We are all folks
here from the same community who may see one another in the same grocery store,
and we have different opinions, but we can all hear them
politely.
So come on up. Come on. Somebody needs to be
first.
Ah, Mr. Parsons, I presume.
Yes.
Welcome.
I did want to just take some time
to just talk about a little bit of what I brought up.
I know who you are, but you better introduce.
Oh, sure. Carlton Parsons, 358 Clarks Pond Parkway.
Thank you.
So I wanted to give a little bit of an overview of what I talked about last
time.
Mm-hmm.
Basically,
from what I'm hearing from a lot of people from a lot of the city
is that I think one of the
issues I think that's on everyone's mind is not
necessarily the budget, that we're
having a lot of budget cuts because of one
major problem, which is the market rates in this
city are out of control. Those are contributing to
people having high taxes in houses that they
bought that are now worth double, and they're paying taxes for
that house. The other piece of it is that we have not
put in the work to build in housing to spread
that tax base across more people.And I think it's
weird that our solution is to fire our public
employees, and increase the unemployment rate, and lower
the number of taxes to try to do this.
I've heard that our
student council is going to... Or sorry, our school board is trying
to say this isn't going to happen again.
But we don't have a forward-thinking policy.
What's South Portland going to look like in five years?
Where's the economic growth? Where's the radical
revenue generation that we'd like
to make our city prosperous?
I don't hear on any of these city councils
since I heard, is there any organization or business
currently getting less than the residential mill tax rate?
Are there any that are currently getting tax breaks that maybe we can ask
them to contribute to that for one more year?
Lower the average number of taxes here.
I am more than happy as a citizen to contribute more in taxes if
that means that lowers the tax base for those
most vulnerable in our city. Why are we having seniors
that are living in half a million dollar homes?
Because we haven't put the investment into housing.
We haven't asked people to pay their fair share.
This is where we're at now.
30 seconds.
And we're going to be here again next year.
And I appreciate Scott. Scott's presentation last week was
incredible, but it also showed that if we're going to
start raising more revenue, we also have to think
about our mill rate and how much funding we get from the
state. So that's my time. I really want to ask,
what are some of those policies? Can we do a policy of radical
revenue generation? Can we have a progressive property tax rate
so that some people like myself can pay more to save our
other citizens less money? So those are my big
questions, and that's my spiel, but that's what I wanted to ask of the council.
Thank you very much.
Someone else with public comment? Yes.
Hi, my name's Jack Bowler, and I'm a South Portland resident.
This situation has made one thing clear, the school department cannot solve this
alone, and the community should not be expected to carry it without a
clear path forward. What feels especially concerning
is the deep distrust
many in the community are feeling towards the schools right now, and when
trust in our schools starts to erode, trust in our city can erode with it.
These institutions are deeply connected, and confidence in one
inevitably shapes confidence in another.
I'm not sure how involved the city is meant to be in an issue like this,
but I would sincerely hope
this is a moment where city leadership steps up and gets involved.
People are not asking for perfection.
They are asking for a plan, a clear, coordinated
path forward between the city and the school department, that
explains the options, the trade-offs, and where we are actually
going. Right now, it feels like we are reacting instead of
being led. This is a moment for leadership.
Thanks for what you guys all do.
Thank you very much. Next.
I'm sure a lot of you are here to make public comments, so please don't
be shy.
Chelsea Bian. I live on Margaret Street, and I'll just be brief to say
I
generally support the request by the school department.
And I think it is a very prudent
request that this money is not adding
additional spending that will add to the operating budget for next
year, but is really trying to give
the school department a more stable budget
moving forward.
It's been a painful few years, and
I appreciate that this is trying to lessen the pain in the
future.
Thank you very much. Thank you.
Good to hear.
All right.
Come on. There.
Hi. Jenny Lupica. I live on Bower Street.
I just wanted to say really quickly, because it seems like people have a few
questions about what will happen next year and kind
of what the future holds. And I wanted to bring up some of the words that have been
talked about with this particular budget.
Daniel Feller, who I don't know if he's here, but he has talked about this being a
budget crisis. Just tonight, Abigail had said it's really been a
difficult and painful process. I've heard our
previous
school board members calling it a fairly unusual circumstance.
And I think it's just
important that we all remember this isn't going to be a request that the school
board comes to you guys with every single year.
We're asking for the SROs and the snow removal for
$360,000, which wouldn't be... I get you saying
it's like an additional percent, but it'd be coming out of your budget
instead of adding it to ours, so it wouldn't be an additional percentage that
citizens would be paying, which I think is really important to consider. Correct?
Mm-hmm. And I think anything you guys can do to help
make this situation any less painful based on what's already happened would be
so appreciated, because it's not quite over yet, but it's getting there.
Thank you.
Thank you again. Thank you.
Thanks.
Hi, everybody. Eleni Richardson.
I'm a school board member, but I'm speaking
as a very tired mom tonight.
I've emailed this council a couple of times about the
research that I've been doing
with other municipalities, and
local municipalities
about-How does
one deal with this kind of an issue?
I'm a lawyer, I'm a problem solver, and
the math hasn't been mathing for us over with the school budget.
And,
I've been trying to
just explore creative ways to kind of
soften the blow of the intensity of the changes that
the school department is undergoing, or will be undergoing.
So,
and I haven't stress tested this, but as a lawyer, I look for precedent,
and precedent means that it's worked in the past, or
that there's a model that we can follow.
And, I sent you all a joint resolution
between the Portland City Council and the Portland School Board back
in 2008,
kind of addressing a partnership, if you will, for the
creation of a sustainability plan.
I also sent you the sustainability plan that kind of
explained how that partnership worked, and there was sort
of a sharing of resources, if you will.
And the city had an opportunity to
work with the school and kind of stress test some of the issues that the school
department had been having.
I was going to call you Congressman Walker, but that's not right. Councilor.
But it has such a ring.
You've been-
Watch out.
You've had a raise.
Councilor Walker's questions about how is this not going to happen again and
kind of... Those are really valid questions.
So maybe the city can come down the street
and sit with Abigail and her team and
help in some way. I don't know. But I'm
not trying to do your job. I'm not trying to offer anything that is
inappropriate or not transparent to taxpayers.
I'm simply trying to find other ways.
We've already, as a board, asked for your blessing
on an additional tax increase.
Councilor Pride, you're right. This budget
has presented a number of issues for the public.
My hope is last night's decision to potentially pause on
reconfiguration allows taxpayers to
think just about the school budget right now, given that
the decision we made last night does show that we are listening to the community,
and most importantly, our classroom teachers, which I think is what
potentially swayed other people to change their mind.
Time.
But anyway, I just want to implore you to please open your minds
and help. Thank you.
Hold on for just one moment. Just a quick...
Generally, when someone asks a question, the city manager answers it.
And I am intuiting that your
question might have been,
what kind of reaction or what kind of process would there be
to discussing this material you've sent?
Correct.
All right.
Sure. Yeah. Thank you for putting...
All right. Yeah. What a question. Wow.
Thank you.
I should have posited a question. Thank you for-
All right
... doing it for me.
Thanks very much.
Thank you.
More public comment, please.
Hey, everybody. I'm Tyler Smith. I'm also on the school board.
I just wanted to quickly voice my support for the work that
the school administration, Abigail, Joe, and everybody else has done
on this budget. I'm new to the school board and new to the city and
this school.
In particular, I come with a background in schools.
I worked for a grant-making organization that did technical assistance
for schools with their budgets and how to
make things work, especially with declining enrollment.
Some context for the
city council is that when federal COVID funds went
out at this point four or five years ago, one of the main things that
we were talking with school leaders about is not spending our funds
on positions, because that money runs out.
South Portland dealt with a very unique issue, which is that they
also accepted a large number of asylum seekers at the same time,
and so chose to spend almost all of their funds on positions,
which is what got us to this position
where we are right now, primarily.
There's obviously been a lot of turnover in terms of
the director of finance, and that has created its own set of problems, but
I think those two things are working together.
And I think the administration, the work they've done over the last
five, six, eight months to get us back on track
and put a budget together that's realistic and that will set us up for the
future
is commendable.
And I'll also say that we're definitely not out of the woods after this year.
Abigail was discussing the FY28 budget, and our current
roll-forward projections put us at 6%, pretty much on the dot.
And that's with a lot of question marks about
fuel, electricity, the kinds of operational costs that are going to come up in the
next year that are really big question marks.
And so, I implore you guys to take this budget
and accept it, and
2%, I think, would be great for building a contingency.
But we're also not going to be out of the woods with this.
So, to set expectations that next year will
not be this hard, but it may be hard.
And so we have to, I think, look forward to a
larger term after this year, really thinking about the
next five, 10 years, and how this city can make our schools work long term.
So, thank you.
Thank you very much. Other public comment?
Thank you.
Sometimes better than now, I guess.
Ed Cobb, Romano Road. I spoke last night at the school board meeting for the first
time ever. I've also watched the meetings,
and I will say, like what I said last night, it was a lot of contentious
stuff, and I don't envy being on the school board,
and getting phone calls, and threatening
that I don't know what I'm doing, and all kinds of stuff like that.
So I guess thank God I'm not on the school board.
But I will say part of the issue, I think is...
And to me, it's the most ridiculous thing ever.
We vote on a school budget in June.
Roughly speaking, 11% to 12% of the people show up to vote on that school board out
of the whole population.
We don't really know, if I'm understanding what you're saying correctly,
how
much spending we may be looking at coming up.
It's just something you don't know. It's an unknown.
And for the taxpayer, what's an unknown is we don't know what our new assessed
value's going to be. And I reached out to Mr.
Matthews during the last assessed value, and I will say Mr.
Morelli called me and said, "Hey, do you want to sit down?" I go, "I don't want to
have to sit down." But regardless, his assessed value went up
$36,000 last year. My assessed value for the
land that I haven't done anything with went up $3,600 out of nowhere,
really, in my mind.
The cheapest property, stick-built property in this town, as I mentioned last
night, is $399,000. It was listed three days ago.
It's 650 square feet, and the property taxes are
$4,300 or so annually on a 650 square
feet building.
This is unsustainable. And my thought would be, in all
honesty, if possible, would be take last year's budget for the
city and for the school department, carry it over.
Let's know some of those unknowns around September.
Let's have the public vote on it in November when we all sort of know where
we're really going to be at. The public will know where their assessed value will
be. The school probably will have a better idea of where they
will be. And ultimately, I think it's a fairer
system.
I don't think that there's a law that says we have to have the
budget passed by June. I could be wrong.
But I think we could carry over the existing budgets.
Let's
see where we really all are at and have a vote in November,
where I think we get more people from the public coming out to vote for it.
I think people see June elections, and people are off doing stuff with their kids.
I'm going to be off doing stuff with my kid, who's going to get out of college here
pretty soon. So
that's my first thought. I guess the other thing I would mention is
I certainly would like to see-
30 seconds
... the teachers
be more public-facing, meaning I'd like to see more teachers, and I'd like to see
more administration cuts
or salary freezes in the administration level.
Not trying to take money away from teachers, but I think that's who talks to those
students every day, not the administrators in their back offices.
I'm not saying they don't work hard.
I'm just saying they don't face the students on a daily basis. Thanks so much.
Thank you very much.
Additional public comment?
Excuse me.
Lauren Shapiro, Deek Street. I want to acknowledge the school
board and leadership for all of their effort.
It was an impossible budget to work with.
We see you, and we appreciate you and all that you've done throughout this
difficult process.
I'm here to repeat the same message you've all heard before.
I again want to call out very real inequity that exists in our
community.
Industrial concentrations have shaped housing, property values,
and environmental conditions, placing an unequal burden on certain
neighborhoods.
These realities must be acknowledged and addressed in future planning and policy
decisions to protect health, expand opportunities, and help bridge
inequities in the school system.
As we know, inequity starts with housing, and addressing it at the root is
essential to creating lasting fairness and opportunity for all children and
families.
It's critical to note that the tank farms which sprawl across our city and
infiltrate our neighborhoods have been systematically undervalued for
decades.
While residents have faced continual and substantial increases
in property values, the tank farms have never and continue to
avoid their fair share of contribution to the rising costs of our city,
all while their emissions harm the health and wellbeing of our
residents. Based on 2021 assessor's data, even
before the recent revaluation that further widens the gap,
tank values per acre were one-seventh of residential and industrial
warehouse one-fifth of residential.
Why do we continue to subsidize these parcels at the expense of our
community when we are in such dire need for funding our city
and school needs?
It is inequitable and unsustainable.
Fairly assessing these parcels would generate significant revenue for our
schools, supporting staff, programs, and resources that
benefit every child. It's long overdue.
Please make it happen. Thank you.
Thank you very much. Additional public comment?
If there isn't any, I'm going to... Okay.
I'm not threatening anyone with this, but-
Claire Holman. I'm also a member of the school board.
A couple of things. I want to say that
I'm thankful to our budget
director, Abigail Kirchin, for helping to create this budget
and for the rest of our administration. I do support the budget.
It's been a very difficult season, as I know you've all heard.
And
I hope that it would be nice if we can get some help.
I am concerned about burden on taxpayers. It's something we need to think about.
I've heard some interesting ideas right now and some other interesting ideas, and I
want to voice once again that, umFunding our
cities only with property taxes is not a great
path forward for us for several reasons.
One of the reasons is the development pattern that it's going to force upon us.
The second is that it's inequitable.
Property taxes are regressive inherently.
So, Scott Morelli once said something about a possible sales tax.
Well, that's also regressive, but at least some tourists and stuff would be paying
it, unlike property taxes. And there are other types of things we could
consider doing. I really think it's not a healthy path for us to always
depend on property tax. Well, I don't know, why are we doing
that? It's painful, and it's risky for people.
So, and then I want to say that
the idea that we may contribute, what we make, if we go to 2%,
for example, 2% more,
for example, that that could help fund our contingency plan, that's very important.
We have lost some very valuable positions.
And
we're hoping that there are some other funds that seem to be on the horizon, like
for our insurance rate not being as high.
We're hoping there's going to be some relief there.
But it's painful to lose some of the people we have lost.
It's hard enough to close a school.
And
I know some people may feel, well, why do you need such fancy schools?
They're not fancy, but what we do want is really good schools.
And that's something that we all value, and because
our children are going to be running this place in a while, and we want to make
sure they're well-equipped to do so. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Oh, in just over two minutes even.
All right.
One
minute.
Two.
Rosemary DeAngelis, Pleasantdale, member of the school board also.
I just want to reiterate what it is that the
school board voted last night, because that's the only thing
that we all agreed on, was asking for a
1% increase,
which was going from 6% to 7%,
and to ask for the city to fund
our plowing and school resource officers in
fiscal year '26-'27. And
that was an additional $360,000.
I
really appreciate so many school board members showing up tonight, and
as well as parents who are here, and I think everybody has
said this
has been a difficult... It's been the most difficult budget I've
ever seen in my years in any kind of
public service. So,
it's trying to come up with that balance between what we think
that is reasonable to ask and what we think will result
in passing of a budget. So that's really what's key for
us is,
if you listen to Mr. Cobb or you listen to some other people,
I
speak with people who are on fixed incomes.
They're our taxpayers, too. So what can we
ask for that we think
will sustain a yes vote? And
I think what we have heard
consistently from our finance
director is
that if we continue to put money
into the budget that we can't sustain the next year.
So if we go back to just adding in
positions, as much as people really want to do that,
that's going to get us, to use Abigail's expression, kicking the can
down the road. So then we are going to be back
here again in another year. So,
I think
with the request for the snow plowing and the school resource
officers, it would be up to the council if you approve
that, and if you approve that for one year or on an ongoing
basis, we'd be thrilled.
30 seconds.
Yes. Thank you.
And otherwise, looking for what feels
best to this council and
hopefully supporting us on a request for another percent that would
help fund our fund balance. Which we're also doing in some
savings that we received in our health insurance premium that did
not result in being as high as we had expected.
So some of that savings is also going into our contingency.
So we're working on that-
Time
... as much as possible. Thank you.
Thank you very much. I'm just making a quick note.
Do we have more public comment?
All right. We're getting serious about this. All right.
Well, if there isn't additional public comment on this item, public
comment is closed. I think we heard some questions for our
city manager, and I think that the
city manager also has some information to share that might
help council's discussion. So
we're getting into it.
So to answer some of the questions, I'm happy for others to chime
in. I know
Carlton had suggested, always a good idea, what are some other
creative revenue sources to take a look at, because
as we all know, most of our budget, both in the school and the
city
sides, are reliant on the property tax.
We've got other funding sources, but that's a big source of the funding for both of
those budgets. And so, are there ways to look at that?
The
problem in Maine is that the
legislature has preempted municipalities
from doing anything with property taxation.
So we hear people say sometimes, "Hey, why don't you tax someone's extra home?"
Or if they're somewhat using it for
a-Airbnb or something. We are
legally prohibited from charging one tax rate to
a certain group and another to other folks.
Same way we can't institute our own local sales
tax,
especially on the motels, which if you look at the studies, are mostly paid for
by folks that are not from South Portland, either out of state or
out of town, and that would help spread some of the burden that we have for cost.
But we can't even do that without permission from the legislature, and that's
something this council has been trying to work on
for many years, but in particular, especially since two years ago when we had the
big revaluation. And it's something that's gained momentum, but
similar to the question about assessed values, we also can't
tell one group, "Hey, we don't like what you're doing, so we're going to assess
your property more." That would be kind of weaponizing
the assessing process, and we're not allowed by statute to do that.
We have a process that's established effectively by
the state for how we assess different properties.
And just remember, if we increase the value of one property, the city doesn't get
more revenue out of that. What that effectively serves to do is it impacts the mill
rate, because the total amount we need to raise from
taxes,
let's say we need 100 million in taxes.
If we're raising the assessed value of
a group of homes or a group of businesses, that doesn't raise us more money.
What it does is it impacts the formula, and it impacts the mill rate, and it means
the mill rate's lower than it would otherwise be, but we
don't raise more money from that.
I think we'll talk about in a minute this idea of collaborating
or the good idea about what Portland went through back
20-ish years ago.
I'm trying to think here. Oh, there was a question about the law and the school
budget being passed in June. I actually don't know the answer to that.
Do any of the school officials know whether there's a state law?
Jessica, of course. Our city clerk, Jessica Hughes.
Lucky she's here.
I just looked up the statute.
Sorry.
Hi, Jessica Hughes, city clerk. So school budget validation referendum has
to pass before July. So there is a time deadline that we do
have to do that. If it does not pass by the deadline that is in statute,
the FY26 budget would carry through for operational until a
budget is passed. So that's why our budget is in June, because we are having to
have it approved by July.
Great. Thanks, Jessica.
Thank you.
I'm going to share my screen because I had anticipated a few of
these questions here, and I think it's sometimes helpful if people can see them
visually what I'm talking about. So I understood the
idea of collaboration and cost savings would come up, and we'd be very
happy. I don't know if it needs to be because it's a request from the school board
or if staff simply just want to get together,
and start talking about whether there are ways to see if we can
reduce overall cost to taxpayers through
consolidation of services or cooperative purchasing
arrangements or any sort of these different things.
And we're also fortunate, our finance director was literally working as the
finance director in Portland the time that the MOU that was referenced was in
place. So we have someone that has experience with
that, and so, a good thing to build on.
I think one of the things that is important, and we'll be upfront, is I do think it
is important that the costs are accurately accounted for
where they're incurred. And as superintendent knows, we've
worked for a couple of years. We had a consultant come in and help us.
We frankly believe this is going to be turning some of the conversation on its
head. We believe there's a lot of costs the city right now is incurring that are
more appropriately should be shown in the school budget.
For example, as the study showed, the city could fire two parks
workers today because all they do is work on school athletic fields and
things of that nature, but it shows up in our side of the budget.
And there's a lot of examples of that, and so,
I think part of that discussion should be where should these costs lie?
Those things don't really save taxpayers' dollars, right?
Because it's either showing up on our side of the budget or the school, but it does
give a more accurate representation of when we split up that dollar we
receive, every dollar we receive in taxes, what is it really going
towards?
With that, I understand the school folks have had
a... I'll say I've been doing this work for 20 years.
This is one of a handful of incidents where I've seen,
four different communities I've worked in.
This is probably one of the top three or four toughest discussions, so I
really feel for you all. I've been on the other side of it in some of the other
communities.
But it's not tough when you've got teachers that are looking to be
laid off and parents that are upset and
it's not something I know you all envy.
So, I completely understand why there'd want to be discussion about
moving costs under the city's share of the budget.
I guess my message more towards the council would be,
there's two things that would happen if those costs for the SRO and for
snow plowing are absorbed on our side of the budget.
We either need to increase taxes,
again, showing up on our side of the budget to fund that
$360,000, or if
we can't increase that taxes any more than we have, we need to now go
find $360,000 in cuts on our side of the
budget to make up for those shifted costs.
And so if it's the first scenario where we need to increase taxes, again, that
skews where the costs are actually occurring.
There's a possibility, depending on what costs are shift.
I don't know if these ones
would be eligible, but the school gets EPS funding for certain
costs that it has, and if they're shifted to the school, there's a question of, are
those now not reimbursable by the
state?Most importantly, it doesn't save the taxpayers any money because we're still
raising taxes. So that begs the question, why not just allow the
school budget to increase taxes to cover these costs?
If no tax increase is acceptable and we need to cut in our budget,
I guess the question is, is it equitable to make the city cut services or
position to fund school costs? Um, and also bring up the
example a couple of years ago, when we sent out tax bills that were $4 million
less than they should have been,
the proportional, equitable thing to do would've been to say, "All right, school,
2.6 million of that loss in revenue is yours to find."
We didn't do that. It was our error, and we ate it by doing
position freezes, spending freezes, different things of that nature, because
it was our error. And, um,
I just think that's worth mentioning.
I also think it's worth mentioning that the city has been...
And I know especially because of that Mr.
Cobbs and others' points about the assessed property values
going up and that having such an impact on folks, um, and
so you've seen tax increases. On the city side of the budget since
FY22, we've added 15.5 positions, but we've
eliminated 16.25, so we're net loss of
0.75 positions during that time, and we've
got another two and a half additional FTEs proposed to be
eliminated in this budget, so that would bring us down to negative
3.25 positions, um, since FY22. However, the
demand for our services, as I talked about during our budget presentation last
week, whether it's, um,
uh,
a request for service through, um, uh, car
registrations or for, uh, road work and the number
of storms that we've had, or just IT demands, uh, has
actually increased. And so we're cutting positions, but we're seeing increases.
Um, so anyway, I think that's all I wanted to share on that.
And then just finally, fund balance, I think one thing we haven't really talked
about here is, um, whether it's one million or two million or three
million, um, that probably is maybe a conservative number.
Um, what are we going to do about that?
Because whether it's a million or two or three,
that's going to eat into the city's fund balance, and those are dollars that,
um, next year, we would've used to buy capital items like
fire trucks and public works trucks and parks
equipment to maintain our parks. So if we don't have that money and the
school doesn't repay it, there's two options again.
We raise taxes to buy those things, and now
on our side, we have to raise taxes for money that we should have had, so
it skews where they should be shown.
Or we just go without those capital equipment.
And I guess that's a question really for the council is, is that acceptable or does
there need to be, um, a plan there as well for
repayment? Because that's ultimately what we'd look to pursue.
There's no easy answers because where's the school get the money to repay it?
Because right now they don't even have enough in their own fund balance.
So there's no good options here, and I understand that, but I
think it's worth considering before we talk about whether we shift costs or not to
make sure we're factoring in all those different things.
So hopefully that answers questions and clarifies a few things.
Um,
sorry.
Take a question.
Yeah, I had indicated we can't assess...
Um, sorry, just to reiterate. We can't assess,
um, based on whether we think someone's a
bad actor, they're emitting too much.
You can't do property value assessments on those.
Um, and in fact, over the years when we've assessed some of the tags,
some of them have challenged that assessment and been successful in getting it
reduced. So they are being
increased this year, I do know that, but, um, we can't just
arbitrarily, especially this council doesn't control
assessments. It's done through, um, a process defined by the state.
And so, um, right now we don't have evidence that
they're being, um, uh, under-assessed, or at least we can't go in and
say, "Hey, we're going to jack your assessment up because we want you to pay more
in taxes." That's not
how it legally works, um,
right or wrong.
Okay. That's it.
Thank you. Thank you very much, and thank you again to everyone who made public
comment. Thank you to my fellow councilors for
what we are about to discuss, which I believe...
Yeah, can I just say what I
think what we're being asked to give a reaction to is,
um,
any percentage guidance we would give back to
the school department, whether it's 1% or different than 1%.
Um, and also
this guidance I think was going more to the city manager on
just a reaction to how you would feel about the school budget
changing by the amount of the SROs
and snow removal
if the city absorbed that. Ms. Councilor Matthews.
Okay.
I'm going to take a breath because my wife said sometimes I sound very overbearing
when I'm talking. I think it's over passionate.
Um,
so, uh, wow.
How'd we get here?
Five years ago, we weren't here. What a long five years.
Anyway, I got a lot of questions for the, uh, school department.
Um,
there's a lot of people... I had
72 texts today, which was completely ironic that 36 was begging me
not to agree to raise
your percentage, and 36 saying, "Please, please, please, save the
teachers, save positions, everything."
Well,
here's the thing,
is I am 100% pro-school, pro-teacher,
pro-student, everything. Gave 12 years of my life to the
schools.And we're asking
the public to go ahead and
pay higher taxes, and some of those people we're asking to pay
higher taxes, we laid off.
What an abomination.
I'm
going
to ask Abigail to go to the podium, if you would, please, because I got some
questions. So I've watched the school board meetings, followed it
pretty closely. I've talked to several school board members, several parents.
First of all, I don't want to see any schools close.
I don't like the thought of the reconfiguration now.
So when the health savings, it came in at 5%.
All right? What's that give us, about 600,000 savings,
700? More?
Yeah. We budgeted at 12%, and it came in at
5.14%. It yielded about 655 or
so thousand.
Okay. Where did that money go into the new budget?
So in our current budget, 179,000 of that is in
contingency with the idea towards fund balance.
The rest is with adding back positions.
Okay. Now, by adding back those positions that you
guys felt were needed,
okay?
And again, our job is not for the public.
Our job is not to micromanage the school board and
what they've cut and what they've decided, and I'm not trying to do that.
I'm just asking questions.
The positions that you decided to eliminate, I had
grandmothers calling me, it was awful, crying that they were losing their
10-hour job
in the
cafeterias.
I just can't
fathom what lunch aids
could possibly do to a $74 million
budget at $15 an hour or whatever.
And I've listened
to Dr. Prince. Is it Dr. Prince? Dr.
Prince preached that,
in a respectful way,
that we don't get rid of anybody at the top
because it's a domino effect of legality
and protecting the students. But when we have a lot of
top-heavy people,
we could possibly remove some of
those positions. We really could
remove some of those positions and add that to the contingency and
keep it at the 6%.
We have a lot of
social workers. We have a lot of
counselors. We
just have a lot of top brass that are salaried positions that are not face-to-face
with children, and this is what this education system is about.
It's about face-to-face. We try to get
our children away from as much screen time as possible and put them in front of a
teacher, and I think it's the teachers that
make a difference in a child's life.
I know there's a lot of good administrators, don't get me wrong.
They make
differences, too. But
is there any way that we could really take a look at this budget
and possibly
trim the fat in the
higher salaried positions to add to the contingency of the
179 and get it back to the 600,000 or the
700,000? I don't
understand how we took 70 positions, and they were
probably some of the lowest positions on the totem pole. All right?
That's my first question. Second question is, does
consolidating Kayla's school
cost any more bus driving wise, bus aide wise?
Is that going to cause more
congestion places? Have we looked at that?
Why don't you answer those first two, and then we'll go from there.
Okay.
Yeah. I appreciate these questions very much.
The first one about the
lunch aides, if you add them all up together, it's
around 55 or so thousand plus payroll taxes.
Add it all up together, that's almost an ed tech.
That's a decision,
right? It is a decision,
but we get to keep an ed tech for that.
And then we figured, well, we often have vacancies there anyway.
Obviously, we don't want to put anybody out of a
beloved 10-hour-a-week job that they really cherish and that the students enjoy as
well.
That is the calculus,
that it saves an ed tech.
I think the administrative director versus
student facing,
there's a lot of different opinions on that one.
There's a lot of valid opinions on that one.
I think every sector has its kind of
frontline and its inner operational engine.
Think about the Artemis launch
that we've recently watched. I watched that with my children.
I remember watching that, and I saw these four
interplanetary-facing employees
supported by buildings of administrators,
engineers, researchers, HR people that help them with all their
issues.
So there's something to be said for the operational engine
that
enables the teachers to do their best work.
And I'm not denying there's notGood decisions either
way on what you're saying.
It's a tough position to be in.
It's a tough position to say,
"I, as a director,
need to be here right now,"
and think about what that means.
And we've had to think about that about ourselves.
And that doesn't make every decision right,
but
we do have to
accept some trade-offs and understand that there is an inner
engine that supports
the student-facing employees. And I believe every single employee is
important. The custodian, okay, they're not student-facing, but they're
important.
A teacher's important. I think I'm important.
I think every single person here is important, and there's no easy choices.
And I understand the criticism. I think we can take that on the chin.
Thank you for your question. I don't think I can give you all of the answer you
need.
That's fine. Now, as far as the busing?
As far as the busing,
we believe that should be similar, primarily because we're paying for drivers
for all of that time anyway.
So they remain on the road,
whether we have the
Taylor school or not.
Okay. So
as far as
the 179, that's going to go into the general fund?
Yeah. That goes to contingency. The idea and hope is that we don't
spend it, the expectation is that we don't spend it, and then it'll eventually go
into a fund balance.
Okay.
And I just want to add, I don't want to
offend anybody who believes in teachers. My mother was a teacher. I love teachers.
Right. Oh, and I didn't take it that way at all.
It is a hard question.
Do you guys have a plan... Well, first of all, is there any idea what
the shortfall that the city's going to cover that
city manager was talking about, it's possibly up to $3 million.
Mm-hmm.
And do you guys have a plan to pay back that $3 million?
So
what's
going to happen is a lot of the taxpayers don't understand is that if you guys
don't pay that back by next June
or so-
Yeah
... yeah, fiscal year
... we are already going to have to increase taxes already.
So is there a plan to pay back that $3
million in place yet?
Mm-hmm. Yeah, we're hoping for two at the most.
But again, there are unknowns, and we'll see.
I think what I've understood with my conversations with
your finance director is that we may end up needing to come up with a
memorandum of understanding where we may make payments on an annual
basis until we knock that out. I think that could
be a path, but in the meantime, we do need to hold some
savings
in school control for
a sudden mold issue or something like that.
And that savings helps support personnel
long-term.
Okay. I'm good for right now.
Thank you.
Mr. Morelle,
if they do go to a payment plan, let's say-
Mm-hmm
... we still have to keep the tax rate
higher because we have an outstanding loan, correct?
It depends. If
there are certain capital items that we want to purchase that we now don't have the
fund... Because we use excess fund balance, as you know, to make many CIP
purchases, capital purchases. And so if that amount is not sufficient
to fund all the needs that we have, we either don't purchase those
or we raise taxes in order to purchase those. So that's kind of the two options.
And yeah, it would be unrealistic to expect that's all repaid in
one year, frankly. It's a big amount given the situation.
So it would be over probably a multi-year period, which
still may have that same impact. We can't fund certain things.
But it
also does have some money coming back where it's not quite as dire
situation.
All right. Thanks. I'm good.
Thank you. Thank you, Councilor West.
Can we put the slide up that shows the budget, the original budget, the
budget they come before us with,
and the whatever the other, I forget the third column.
Is that on a website somewhere I can...
No.
Councilor West-
Sorry.
... do you have anything else you want to say while they're setting up or not so
much?
Well, I think it's-
Okay
... really important to get in public exactly what we're
talking about with this
vague description of the $2 million or $3 million
deficit.
And so I want to start by asking
that question, because I think the school board came before
us having said last night that they...
Oh, and by the way, I just want to tell you, I got to start.
This I can do without seeing the slide.
Thank you all, the school board, the members of the community, the staff,
clearly tremendously difficult year, and people have been working
very hard to do our best for the schools.
One bit of trivia when I was looking up if the elections have to take place in
June, which is state law requires the school elections in June.
Maine is one of only three states in the nation that requires a vote
of the people on the school budget.
And it would seem to me that's something to take a look at in the long term.
But can we just quickly...
So
this board voted last night to come in and ask us for
7% when we had given guidance at 6%.
I have no trouble with that. I think we should just say yes, go to the voters with
7%. Second, the board asked us to consider funding
snow plowing and the school resource officers for a
total of about 360,000. I have no
problem with doing that this year, funding it out of the city
budgetBut I am concerned about
what's going on, that we're still, even if we do that,
there's going to be some kind of a $2 million or $3 million deficit, and I
would like to hear a better, more complete description
of that.
You've got
on that side at least, the-
It's on that one.
So where
does it show in the budget
where that deficit is coming from?
Why are we going to have a $2 or $3 million deficit next year?
Oh, why are we going to have a-
Yes.
Many reasons. I think primarily we're fundamentally
under-budgeted this fiscal year.
I don't know that we could've helped that at this point.
So I think that is a big piece of it.
I'm sorry, say that again.
I think
the primary reason is that we're fundamentally under-budgeted this
fiscal year. That's my take on it.
Is the deficit being incurred this fiscal year?
That's what I'd-
Yes... like to make clear for the public.
Yeah.
So you are going to end this fiscal year $2 million in the red.
Is that clear? Is that what the story is?
Yes. But I'm including the nutrition deficit from
the prior fiscal year and what I'm projecting to be their deficit this
fiscal year, and then also our school
natural deficit this fiscal year.
So add it all up, I'm
leaning towards $2 million at the most.
I agree with $3 million as a nice conservative figure, just in case.
I understand that.
Yes.
I don't think we'll really be there.
Okay, so just make sure that people in the community understand this, because
I'm hearing different things. This fiscal year for our schools,
they are operating in the red to the tune of at least 2 and maybe
as much as $3 million.
Right?
Mm-hmm.
Right. So then the city is
prepared to make up that deficit.
Mm-hmm.
My question to throw to my colleagues is,
they've come in for 7%. Why don't we go to
8% so that we can reduce the amount of
the deficit
in a year? Ordinarily, I would never
do this, but it's because I don't think that it's our job to
micromanage the school board's budget.
But we're put in a tremendously difficult situation
because of things that we didn't do, and really, this actual
staff that's working on it now, they didn't do.
But why don't we say we're going to go
with 8%?
If 7% is going to give them 540,000,
then 8% would give them another
540,000, and that's a
more fair thing to do than us giving them some kind of a loan and then
putting them on a repayment schedule.
So I throw that out to my other counselors for discussion.
I think that's really the most key thing.
And as far as the SRO and the snow plowing,
see, if we were coming in with a zero budget, a balanced
budget, I'd say, "Yeah, let's give them that for one year.
Just for one year, we'll pay those costs.
And then after this, because
they've gone through a really difficult time, and et cetera.
And then after this, they can have it be part of their budget."
But this year is such a big mess, I would just say
let's just try to go to the voters with eight and
just explain to the voters what the problem is.
That's where I'm finished. Thank you for listening.
Councilor Pride. Thank you very much, Councilor West.
Yeah.
And I'm amenable to the 2%. I think I sort of
indicated that with my question earlier,
that I was willing to go that extra percent.
I'm not sure about the plowing and the SROs, and I know that cuts
into the extra percent because you're going to have to find a way to pay for it.
But I think
one thing, and this is what I think we're talking about when it comes to
transparency, is that if the
school has a lot to pay for, they have to put that
all in front of the voter, right? And if things shift and the city
starts taking care of school responsibilities, then the voter sees that the
school isn't asking for as much of an increase.
But the city is asking for more of an increase because we're covering more of those
costs. And I don't mean this in
a glib way, but my job gets on the line.
Because at re-election, the people will see, "Oh, gosh, Councilor
Pride and the City Council just voted for all this extra spending,"
when all that extra spending was really for the school.
It's not our budget that we increased.
So I think, just in a really basic
democracy-driven
thought process here, if people are going to support the school
budget, they need to know, this is what the school budget is.
This is what it costs to run our schools.
We shouldn't be watering that down by having the school take on a
portion that now the people don't vote on directly.
They vote for city councilors instead.
And are they going to vote for those city councilors if they see those city
councilors continually adding onto their budget to take care of school
needs? Well, they don't necessarily see that part of it.
Someone who's really paying attention might see that part of it.
But
that's the way that they're going to potentially take that problem,
is to decide not to elect any one of us.
And I say that being term limited. I'm not running for re-election.
But
what I'm getting at is I think it's really
part and parcel to the democratic process is having the
school budget be the honest school budget.
What are we paying for?And I'm willing to pay the extra
2%. My value has also gone way up, Ed,
as everybody's has, because I believe in schools. I really do.
And in some ways, I know I recommended what, three to five, I think, when we
first started, but I also asked some questions that I was hoping I'd get a
presentation that would convince me to go higher about the fact that
special ed has gone up. We see this
graph, if you have a graph in your head about enrollment, you see enrollment
going down, but at the same time, special needs enrollment going way
up. And the cost of educating a special needs
student is way higher than educating
a normal student. And we are mandated.
And it's funny because
we recently went to a conference in Washington, and we talked to legislators, and
we were talking about
what do we get for mandates from
the
federal legislators that aren't funded, and one of them is schools.
They mandate a certain amount of special education,
but they only funded that mandate 13%.
Yep.
13%.
If they fully funded that, we wouldn't be in as much of a
crisis.
And so, the state is doing sort of the same thing.
They
were going to rebalance the funding for schools to give
more money to our schools, and then they saw that brought their budget too high,
so they couldn't stomach that, and they reduced it.
And it just keeps getting passed down to the cities who
don't have a choice about what kind of tax then they can do, can't target people,
can't target businesses with taxes because we're not allowed to have a separate
rate for businesses that we do for residents.
That's constitutional. Maine constitution dictates, according to the Supreme
Court, that everybody has to have the same mill rate, which isn't true in
Massachusetts, by the way. In Massachusetts, commercial mill rate is
different than
residential mill rate. So write your legislators.
Start collecting signatures now to send to the state and to
amend our constitution so we can do it differently.
Because if we could have a separate commercial mill rate, we could take a lot of
these costs off the residents. Because what's happened is
COVID. COVID made the value of
commercial buildings go down.
No one's buying office space anymore. Everybody's working from home.
So
those sales of commercial
real estate are what dictate the assessment,
right? And so people are paying less for commercial real estate
across the board, so those values go
down.
But I digress.
Noticed.
I know. I could feel you staring at me.
Hoping that I stop talking soon.
No, it's interesting. It is very interesting.
But when commercial values go down, that puts more
taxes on the residents, and that's why we're seeing our residential
values go up, because we got so many more residential sales than we did commercial
sales. And when there's more residential sales, it means there's more demand.
And when there's more demand, the values go up.
So you all are paying more,
but we need to be honest about what we're funding with our dollars.
And so if it's going to
the schools, it needs to be part of the school budget to go before the
taxpayer. And I
really do applaud Councilor Matthews' questions.
I think
he, as every parent or everybody in this community, should be
curious about what the process is with the school making those
decisions. But in the end, if this council says, "Look,
we'll go ahead and pass
a budget that is 8% increase and allow that to go to the
voters,"
we don't get to decide what that 2% is. That's the school board.
So keep attending those meetings. Keep talking to them.
And honestly,
they're listening. They really are.
We don't always seem like we're listening, but we always are.
I can't tell you how many times I second-guess decisions I made up here
based on feedback I'm getting from the public.
So they're listening,
and I hope that that process continues in a
way that
we can all support our schools
through the ballot initiative. So that's my input.
Thank you. Thank you very much.
Others?
And again, we are ultimately looking to
give guidance and a response to the snow
removal and SRO request.
I realize that this is not our final decision, so I'm going to
provide this with some guidance and appreciate the rest of my fellow
councilors'
positions and
consider that. I first want to say, I really
hope that this community and the councilors engage in this
process with a certain amount of kindness and compassion, and I've
been discouraged by the lack thereof.
And so I
want you to know that I come with this, and I teach my children as a parent
to try to act with kindness and compassion.
I have been
frustrated by these discussions and sort of watching the
school board process over the last several years, and this is very personal
to me. I have a child in the current school system.
I have two children who've gone through the school system.
I
came to the first council
school board meeting, I think, asking for a sort of right sizing
of the school board budgetIn
those presentations or the presentation that was provided,
the enrollment numbers have, I think,
drastically decreased. And our budget,
as I recall, has gone from below $60
million to above $75 million over the last
five years.
I know that it is challenging to make
cuts. I know that it's challenging to lose positions.
It has impacted my family specifically, and
I feel that.
I also don't feel that it's appropriate when our enrollment is going
down and our school system is shrinking, to increase
our school budget year after year.
And I think we have to right-size our budget, and we
have to rip off the Band-Aid.
I
was trying to get behind reconfiguration when I thought it was a budget-saving
measure. I don't believe it is anymore, and I am again not
behind that. I think we have to close a school.
That is very challenging. We have to cut staff because we have lower
students, and the ratio of staff to students
have to reflect what our taxpayers can
absorb and what we need to adequately
and well serve our students, maybe not best serve our
students. That is not, I think, our job.
We are trying to fund a public school system.
It may not be the best, but I think it is adequate, and I think our students
are incredibly well-served. The staff, the
teachers are just...
I can't speak enough to how much they give.
So as much as I wish we could fund
our school and our program to
the best of our abilities and have an unending budget,
I am actually not in favor of increasing the budget.
I'm not in favor of moving funds from the school
budget to the city budget. I think we need to have that accurately
reflected between
the two.
And
again, I know this is a workshop. I know that it's not the final decision, but I
just wanted to voice that our enrollment has been
dropping. I think we need to build more housing.
I hope that people realize that our comprehensive plan and development in the
city and not opposing every single building project is a really
important way for our city to move forward, and I hope that you think about that in
the future. This is comprehensive. This is what the council is looking at.
It is every aspect of our city and how we move the city forward.
And this is a very challenging time for our schools, but it is
all connected to many different aspects of our city.
And I know it's challenging, but we sort of have to
go forward with what we can. And we can't renovate our house to the way that
we want. We may not be able to afford to send our children to the best schools.
We just are trying to do what we can with what we have.
And that is challenging, but I think we need to move forward with a
reasonable budget. We need to sell this to the taxpayers and
voters,
and I'm just not comfortable with pushing all this forward.
And I think we're punting the can or kicking the can down the road, and
I really hope that we can make some reasonable
decisions and difficult decisions, and that's where I
am this evening. So thank you.
Councilor Scott, thank you so much.
What isn't clear to me is whether you are guiding
the school board to stay at six, go to seven, or...
I am currently trying to stay at six.
Okay.
Without the
transfer or SRO-
Okay
... additional funding. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Councilor Coleman and Councilor Walker, you want to flip a coin?
Who's going next?
Okay. I
really agree with
Carter,
because my recommendation to the school board was three to five.
And I
also
think you need to look at recommendation that
Councilor Matthews in that looking at
positions that are at the top and at a higher rate of
pay need to be looked at.
My background, I come
from a medical background, and
I keep saying so few did so much for
so many with so little.
And
freezing on wages, I've
experienced that more than once.
And definitely the school
needs to
their budget needs to reflect all of the services they
receive.
And
I'm not certain even 8% is going to pass
this year.
Because even though gas prices, you talked about buses, it's just the
bus drivers. It's also the wear and tear on a bus that's
running all day long or doing more routes,
maybe fuller.
But the cost of fuel in most of the buses, I'm assuming use diesel.
And we have such uncertain times right now with this
current government.
We can't expect anybody to rescue us except for us, so we have to
really, really tighten our belt. Some of
us...
I can tell you, I grew up with you pay your bills, and then you pay
yourself and really work toward having if you're
not going to have a job for a year.
S-live so lean in between
wants and needs, and I totally agree with
Counselor Carter. It is a good
but not the best. It's the best we can within a budget.
And when I've always budgeted, this is how much it's going to, and I
make it fit. That meant for years I cut my own hair,
and I didn't
ever have a coffee outside. I made it at home.
This
is maybe New England, I have no idea
where this says, but if I owed
somebody a quarter, I
would go without until I paid it, because I just can't have
an unpaid bill.
So Counselor-
So I am saying try to stick to
seven or under, and you must absorb
all of the services. So even though
it would only raise our budget by
0.75%,
$360,000 is
$360,000. So it's yours.
Well, thank you. Thank you. So seven and keep the cost.
Yeah.
All right.
You can add, as they say, up to eight, but I'm not certain that that
budget will pass.
Okay. Thank you. Thank you very
much, Counselor Coleman. Counselor Walker.
Mr. Morille, I have a question for you.
Okay.
In the spirit of cooperation and trying
to partner,
is there precedent for
other
types of solutions
in terms of things like maybe we start looking
at capital costs for school repairs for the Skillen boiler,
for the roof at Dyer, for things like that.
Is there a precedent in other communities that you know of where we could move
those costs
for a one-time basis over towards
the city side?
I haven't really looked into that, so I'm not sure
if other communities have done that.
But is it possible here? Probably, yeah.
Do we have an idea of how much the Skillen boiler and the
Dyer roof are?
$3 million.
$3 million for which?
The boiler.
The boiler, and then the Dyer roof. Anybody?
$600,000.
How much?
$600,000. Okay. So, that is something that I would like to explore.
I'd like to explore moving those big capital costs over into our budget,
maybe put that as a parking lot
item. I understand that that's something that no one has thought about so far, but
I do feel like this is a budget crisis, and we do need to think
about creative ways that we can partner outside of the
areas that have been identified so far.
So I just-
I'll just say, we'd probably have to decide that tonight because the parking lot
takes place on May 12th. The school budget has to go to voters on
May...
You have to vote to send that on May 5th, so we'd need to know then if
they're responsible for that or if that's in the city's
budget, and we have to allocate that towards the budget then.
But can I just... Okay, so just for clarification, I don't
think that either of those costs are part of your FY27
budget. Is that true?
Correct.
It is
true that they are not.
Correct.
Okay.
Yeah. I know that they are upcoming costs, though, and-
Right. So what I'm trying to think about is,
obviously, we've heard from one of the counselors and from
other folks that the idea of exploring how does the
city and the school in the future perhaps work together, particularly on capital
expenses, sounds like that might become a workshop of the
future.
Okay.
And I'm comfortable with that.
As we're talking about this, I want to talk about what is our appetite for
all possible creative solutions, and I think beyond the SROs and
the plowing, I think those are other areas that we could
explore how do you either share those costs, cover those costs, things like that.
Because I know that that was a big concern from a facilities perspective.
But Counselor Walker, I'm just clarifying.
I still have way more to say.
Yes. And I'm not cutting you off, but I'm clarifying.
Your intention is to discuss those kinds of
costs in future budget setting because
how we discuss that now in time for their meeting on the
29th, in time to get something back to us on the 5th, seems
challenging.
Okay. And if that's-
But you don't have to fold. I'm just trying to clarify.
Oh, I'm not. I'd like to talk about that as a
council. Is that something that we would be willing to do?
I understand that that might make sacrifices for other capital
projects
that are pending, but I think it is something that we
should talk about as a community or as a council because that does impact the
entire community. And it is those costs, either if they are bonded
or go into the school budget, do eventually come back to the taxpayers.
Mm-hmm.
So it is a shell game, and I just want to talk about basically where to put the
shells.
Okay.
Do you want to hear my other stuff first?
Yes, please.
Okay.
Other stuff welcome.
So I
respect the opinions of my fellow counselors greatly.
But I categorically disagree with several things.
First and foremost, I think that we should strive for the best possible education
that we can give our students. I think that public education is a fundamental
right of our community,
and I think that from an equity perspective, that good enough is
not acceptable for any community. We really should be striving for our best.
And if that comes with a cost, then we are responsible as a community to bear it
because those children that we are educating now grow up to be
the future business owners and leaders in our community, and we owe it to
ourselves to set them upFor the best path of success
possible.
I also believe that tightening of
belts and buckling down on budgets should not come on the backs
of our children. I really don't.
Abby, I really appreciate your
analogy to Artemis with the interplanetary employees and the
field of administrators, because I think that's a really interesting way to look at
it. I
will admit that listening to the school budget meetings, I have also
shared a lot of people's questions about why there wasn't more cut at an
administrator level, and I think that offers a really good perspective.
So it's not our role to advise. I'm not doing that.
I thought that was really good, and I wanted to highlight that.
I absolutely support 8%. I think you all know that I came into this asking
for nine. So I think 8% is great. I think that I
would really like to see some of that money go towards restoring some of the
positions, especially in special education.
I think that that is just paramount to ensuring the
success of both our teachers and our students in the
next year. And I'd also really like to see the related arts positions at
the middle school come back. I think that as many people have pointed out, I
remember my own middle school years, I watched my daughter's middle school years,
and those are just brutal years. And I think that the
most important thing we can do is lift up our students, and the
related arts positions are a place that a lot of people find a lot of joy and
future paths
for careers in life. So I think that I'd like to see that.
That's just my wish list. I know that we don't have a say in that.
In terms of the SROs and the
snow plowing, I am definitely open to that,
especially the SROs. I'm concerned about snow plowing, just because I
know that our public works department runs pretty darn lean,
and so I don't know what kind of hidden
costs or consequences there could be from a staffing perspective on that.
But again-
We have Melissa. We have our public works director here, if you want
any...
I do have a-- Could I get a clarification on what you're asking?
They're asking for us just to pay, not for us to do the
work.
Oh, okay.
Is that correct?
We talk to you.
Oh. That's apples and oranges.
I mean, we-
Melissa, you can help answer-
I'll let Melissa answer this, but I already know the answer to it.
But I just want clarification.
Thank you for asking, because I misunderstood that.
I thought they were asking for us to take that
on.
Hi, Melissa.
Hi. I'm back.
Yes.
Just for the night, though.
Just the night.
Melissa Hutchins, public works director.
So for us to take on snow plow, unfortunately, that would not be feasible at this
time. We actually hire outside contractors to help us.
So we have nine outside contractors that do Mill Creek, The
Cove, the mall area, and Red Bank. We don't have enough staff
to even maintain those roads.
Also, we don't have the extra fleet.
If you have a three-inch storm or more, you're going to have
someone dedicated with a loader and an employee at the school.
So each school would require someone there to constantly plow.
And then right now, we run just enough to get the schools
sanded and salted just before school opens.
So the school has hired help. Nelson plows the
schools. We come in, we sand and salt the schools.
But we don't have the capacity or the equipment to be able to
maintain schools.
Okay. That's what I thought going into this, and that's what I thought you were
asking for. So thank you for the clarification.
Thank you.
Thank you, Melissa.
Anything else?
No.
So where have you landed?
So 8%, yes.
I
would be willing to do it for one year.
But I do agree with the city manager that I would like to
see the school dollars accurately reflect the school spending.
But again, in the interest of as a community pulling together and
assessing the crisis,
I'd be willing to do it for one year.
Okay. Thank you.
You're welcome.
Okay. Councillor West?
Is it all right if I talk again?
Yes, you may.
Look, guys, this is what we have to face up to.
They are going to end this year $2 million to $3
million in the red.
The issue of the 8% wasn't so they could get more people.
It was so that they, because the way it's been explained to me is the city
was going to
use two to three million of our fund balance and then ask them
to come in with a repayment plan. Here's where I am.
I think we ought to just clean the slate.
If they come in this year with a $2 to $3 million
deficit, we just take our fund balance and we pay it, and
that's it. We start fresh, and we hold them
to some higher level of accountability.
Because otherwise it is too mixed up.
I had a reasonable approach, I thought, of saying, "Let's go to
8%, give them. That'll bring in about a million that they could
use to pay back some of it."
Because they wouldn't hire any more teachers or do any of that good stuff that one
of my colleagues thinks they could use it for.
But I can see we are all over the map.
I don't see how we can pull four councilors together with
one approach. But we can't get away from the
fact that they're in the red $2 to $3 million.
And what are we going to do about it?
Right. Well,
good news for us is we could give all kinds of different guidance, and then the
school board has to figure it out. But that might not be particularly
helpful or responsible. May I ask you-
Because it's our money. That's the reason why we have to figure it out.
May I ask you for a clarification? When you say clean the slate, that
means
the deficit is met, but there is not
a requirement to pay it back?
That's correct.
Okay.
I think that's the only-
Okay... feasible way to do it, givenAnd I'm not happy with it
because, as everybody knows, I've been trying to have a capital
building, take some of our excess funds and have a capital building
fund so that we wouldn't be in the big mess we're in with all our buildings.
But I just don't see any way around it this year.
Are you still going to allow them the 8% or keep it at 6%?
No. Okay, forget it. 10.
No, she's going to-
If I do that, then you have to go back to your 601, and that makes
one of my colleagues happy,
and hopefully it would make all the other ones happy because they don't have to
repay the two to three million. I'm really trying to pull four councilors
together here.
What am I, chopped liver? I didn't get to say anything yet.
Can I ask-
Yes
... a clarifying question?
The pattern continues. Yes. Thank you.
And I do very much-
No, thank you
... appreciate what you're-
I am sorry, I'm not going to be Solomon on this one anyway, so...
I just want to clarify. What you're saying is
that the two to $3
million fund balance is not a loan, but is
just using our fund balance to fund the deficit,
and that is not
an additional percentage or two percentage beyond the
6%. So you're saying-
Correct
... keep
6%, eat the deficit with our fund
balance, and move forward?
Yeah. 601.
Okay.
601.
So it would be-
Thank you. No, I just want to clarify-
Yes
... where the percentages versus the fund balance was falling.
So to just try to say it in a more articulate way, they are anticipating
an FY26 deficit of $2 to $3
million. When the books are closed, and they're ready to close the books
on this fiscal year, we sit down, we see how much that is,
we pay it out of our fund balance from our FY27.
For them, they have
developed a responsible budget for FY27.
It's a 6.01% increase. They go forward with that,
and next year we really hold their feet to the fire.
We will never, never do this again.
Thank you for the clarification.
Now I wonder if I could get a
majority vote for our consensus, because it's a workshop,
from my colleagues on that approach.
I don't know if you can.
But can I say my thing now?
You're the mayor, go ahead.
I know. I know, but I wait until you finish.
Did we hear from Councilor Matthews? I must have missed it.
True. He asked questions and never really gave a position.
No, I thought he landed it.
No.
You stuck your landing, didn't you?
You can go ahead.
No. Well, go ahead. Go ahead, Councilor Matthews.
I
personally do not feel 8% will pass.
Last year there was a movement with the school vote. Okay?
We normally had 5 or 600, 700, 800 tops vote.
Last year we had over
2,000.
Yeah.
2,000, and it was
a significant amount of people voted against the school budget, correct?
Yes.
The only thing I can say is, should the city council
decide to...
I would
move forward with 8%.
You guys better get out there and preach to the choir, because I'll tell you right
now, you better get all those school parents out there voting.
You better get everybody out there, because the other half is coming full force, I
guarantee it. And they came full force last year and almost
took you. And it's going to be a long summer for the school board,
a very long summer, because you guys are going to keep going back and back
and back to workshops. Now, I have to say
that
I don't like increasing taxes on people, but I
would rather do what Councilor...
West.
What's your name? Thank
you. I'm on a lot of meds.
So listen,
I'm not a fan of that, just so you know.
Oh, I know.
But it doesn't raise taxes, but it doesn't allow us...
It cuts us $2 million short of projects, and I just-
I know
... I just got a nasty letter from
residents on the golf course whose houses were being pelted
by golf balls because we haven't put up a net yet.
Mm-hmm. Yep.
So I'm
really undecided at this point. I really am.
It's okay.
And we don't have to make a decision tonight, but I got your guidance so far.
I hear you guys, so.
All right. I think maybe-
Go ahead. Your turn.
Maybe I haven't allowed enough quick
opportunity for other councilors to respond to the idea that
the F26 deficit would be paid by the city
in its entirety with no expectation of paying
back. Does anyone want to react to that fairly quickly?
I know finance director might have something to say too, if you'd like.
The finance director wants to react to that.
Just in general.
It's generally in here. I'm not clear about the money.
It's just we have going to pay our bills.
Right.
Ellen Samboin, finance director for the city.
If we choose to draw $2 to 3 million from our fund balance with
no restoration plan or no documentation of
action of either how not to do that again, even for
our own use, without any plan to restore it,
we are going to get questioned by rating agencies when we issue our next bonds
as to, "Okay, you drew $2, $3 million.
What are you going to do about that?" So whether it's a payback from the schools,
whether it's another plan that we have in place,
if you draw fund balance with no plan to restore it
and the reason behind it is for budget deficit, they're going
to question that pretty heavily, and they're going to wonder what we're doing
to make sure
that it doesn't happen again, and if it does, what are your action
plansTo take care of it or to restore
it over some fairly short time period of years.
So not 10 years, but two, three, four, five years.
So I just caution you, if you're going to do that, we are going to have to document
something that says we're just not going to write them a check and forget about it
and draw fund balance for a deficit budget situation without
any recognition that that's not a
good thing to do on a regular basis.
Okay. Can I ask you a quick question?
Yeah.
Would that be true of any department in the city?
Say, the fire department-
I don't know
... or the police department said, "Whoops, we need $3 million that we overspent."
It works for any department?
Only if we're taking it out of fund balance.
Yeah, that's what I mean.
So if we had a deficit in one department and not in another, and our overall fund
balance didn't take a hit, then that wouldn't be the issue.
The issue is the available funds to the city. We have a fund balance policy.
Are you adhering to it? If you're drawing from it, why are you doing that,
and how are you restoring it? So I don't know what'll
happen in the next couple of years. I don't think any of us really do.
If we take $2 to $3 million out and we take money out to
use for CIP or we don't, if we happen to drop below the
9%, then they're going to really get concerned.
Yeah.
And we all hope that doesn't happen.
I'll also mention that there's two ways that the school can also restore
fund balance. One, obviously, we've been talking about, is raising taxes and
dedicating it to a restoration. The other one is, hopefully,
with some restructuring, if you generate surpluses, obviously that goes
into fund balance. So that could happen over the next few years as
they restructure their budget, and they may actually have a little surplus now and
then that can funnel into fund balance.
So-
And that is what happened in prior years, prior to the past two.
Correct.
They were generating surpluses.
Yeah, that's how they built up fund balance to over $5 million a few years ago.
Okay. Ms. Scott.
Yes. Would you mind staying there for one second?
Sure.
Yes, Councilor Scott.
Just to clarify,
I don't think the school department has used city fund
balance in the past. They've depleted some of their fund
balance, but they have not used city to cover deficits. Is that correct?
Not in my tenure. I don't know what's happened a long time ago, but right.
They had over $5 million. I think you guys have seen the-
Yeah
... the slide that shows what the use has been over the past few years. Correct.
But the city does have an obligation to fund
the school deficit if there is one and there's not fund balance to cover that.
I'm just trying to think about our obligation to do that and
how that is managed by a repayment or
bond considerations-
Right... in the future.
So that's a great point that probably we should clarify.
So because it's a municipal school district,
financially, they're a part of our general fund.
Right.
And even though state statute and everything else isolates school fund balance and
school activities and all of that stuff, it's actually restricted in our
financials for schools because it can only be used for education.
The financial impact is if they don't have fund balance and they have a deficit,
it's coming out of our fund balance because we're all in the same fund.
Right.
Yeah.
So it's not just an obligation, it financially has to happen that way.
Right.
Yeah.
Okay. Thank you.
Yep.
Councilor West.
I'd just point out that we have lots of money in our fund balance to do this,
and that in fact, the budget on page nine, the bottom paragraph,
when it talks about the use of the fund balance, and then it goes on that we
have currently
18.7%, and then that we would go down, we'd do this
and that, and then we'd end up with 12.8%.
And when I pointed out that the numbers didn't make sense in that paragraph, what I
was told by the city manager is that's because kind of
quietly on the side, we had set aside $3 million of our fund
balance for the schools.
Mm-hmm.
So we have already set aside $3 million, and we still
end up with 12.8% fund balance. So we have plenty
of fund balance to do it.
And I have one more quick question.
12%, it sticks in my mind as it means
something. Am I completely imagining this?
Is there some guideline for not going under 12?
Something-
So to begin with, it's your policy.
So 9% is the minimum, 12% is the maximum.
Right.
So you want to be in between there.
Oh, okay. All right.
And the policy says anything over 12% can be used-
Thank you
... for one-time purchases. So it's typically that amount that we
look to, to use for CIP. And yes, if we're at 12.8%, you would
have .8%, which is maybe about $1 million,
to carry into next year for CIP, barring any other, however this year
ends up, if we generate a surplus or fund balance goes up or down
more.
Got it.
That make sense?
Okay. Councilor Scott.
Can I clarify? I understood the 12% to be a goal,
not a maximum, and that if we are above the goal, we can use that
for
CIP money, but not that it's a maximum, but a goal.
That 9% was the minimum and 12% was the goal, and as you get above
and below 12.
We're kind of saying the same thing, yes.
Okay.
Fine.
The goal is 12. Until you get over 12, you don't want to spend any-
Yes
... I think is the intent of the policy.
Okay. Thank you.
Yeah.
Thank you, Mayor.
Just real quick.
Yes, thank you.
So
by us paying that, wiping that debt away, I know it
doesn't help your budget this year,
right?
Abigail?
Correct?
Yes, that does not change our FY-
Okay. Can she go to the podium?
Yeah, go to the podium.
Yes. So, having a clean slate doesn't change our FY27 budget,
but it would mean we wouldn't have to budget for that in FY28
and moving forward. So if we were on a payment plan in FY28 and moving
forward, that would obviously come at the cost of personnel.
So it-
Or a tax increase.
Or a tax increase. But it would be enormously helpful.
And we would accept, I think, any action plan, improvement plan
Yes
... that we would need to show
that we're not going to do this again.
Thank you.
Okay. Any-
Yes.
Oh my goodness. Yes.
I will be brief.
Yeah. No.
Go for it. Thank you.
I can? Oh, okay.
So,
the mayor asked for responses to Councilor West's plan.
This is really hard for me to say.
I think at this point, given the dire straits we truly are in,
I'm going to yes, and to this one. I would support
the
cleaning up of the debt. We have the fund balance.
We're over the 12% goal,
and we still will be even if we
pay
as long as it's not more than three million.
I can
live with 8%. I agree with Councilor Matthews that you guys got to go campaign the
heck out of it.
And in the end, it's not so much. I will support 8%, but if you come
back to me with 6%, I will support that too.
It's really up to you guys to decide what the percentage you're coming back with.
But obviously, we're giving the guidance as to the total that we would
support.
If you guys can make it work, if you guys can fund more
teachers and maybe change that, that'd be great in my
personal opinion, but that's not up to me.
So my guidance is that if you come back with eight or less,
I will vote
to pass that on to the voters.
Any... Okay.
No, I think that's Councilor West.
Dangerously, I think what I heard is coming close to some sort of consensus.
And maybe I can be persuaded. Actually, where I was going to go
is, in these times, I think it is appropriate for the
city to make what essentially would be a grant
toward the FY26 deficit. Does it have to
be two million? I was going to recommend it be one million.
That would be helpful.
And if that one million was coming, I was going to say
I would support the 7% budget. That's what has come back
to us.
I don't support that the city would take on
operational costs of the schools.
I think I've heard more than one school board member say throughout this
process, we need to show people what the real costs
of running our schools are.
Snow plowing is one of them. SROs. I was on the school
board at a time when the decision to have an
SRO, I think there are... Are there two of them right now, one at the middle
school, one at the high school? That was controversial,
actually. That it was argued that for some students,
a uniformed officer does not represent safety.
It
reminds them of things that they have learned to fear, and it
was a controversial decision. In Portland, they decided not to
have SROs.
So that is something that is a school board
decision.
So I guess that's what I was going to take my magic
wand and say, "Let's make a grant of one million for
FY26. Let's do the 7% increase that
was asked for, but let's not take on operational costs."
Madam.
If we keep working it, I think we've got a consensus to not take on the operational
costs.
Yep.
We can go there. I think we've got a majority to give them some
kind of a grant, so maybe we can talk about how much of a grant, and then maybe we
could get a majority to go with the 7%, because that's what they asked us.
And I do think that we shouldn't substitute our judgment for the school board,
except in very unusual cases.
So they came in with seven, let's go with seven, but say, "No,
we won't take on these expenses," but let's now talk about the amount of the grant
that we're willing to give them for-
Okay. Thank you.
Back to Councilor-
But what if we're giving them a grant without increasing taxes?
Well,
excuse me, can I have a private conversation?
Wait a second, I've got to move this way.
This is a committee-
Ron, would you support seven that was their request?
The school board requested seven.
The school board, that was... Yes.
Would you go with that?
I said that I would approve
sending it to the voters. It doesn't mean that I approve it or I would vote for it.
Yeah. Would you send it to the vote?
But I'm just saying that they're going to have to sell it, because I don't
believe-
Yeah
... that the voters of South Portland can really support any more tax
increases.
I agree that they're going to have to sell seven.
But they came to us wanting seven, so then I would hope that they could sell
seven.
All right.
And if anybody asks me individually outside of this, and not as a...
I would express my opinion about seven too.
Okay. If I
happened to be a school board member sitting in the audience, I think I would've
heard us say things and
We heard them say things.
And maybe would say we have the authority to go back and
discuss what we heard. That's what I would say about the
percentage increase. And I think we are now going to have a
brief but meaningful discussion about the
idea of helping with the FY26 deficit,
perhaps without strings
attachedAre we having
that discussion?
I think we should.
Yeah.
Okay.
Did you want to say something?
Sure. I fully support the idea. I do think that we should just wipe the slate
clean. I do think that we should have very
clear documentation out there for our
auditors and for the public to understand what we're doing and
what steps can be taken to prevent this from happening again.
In the spirit of this is a community problem,
I think that this is a community solution.
Okay. So I hear a full, whatever the deficit is-
Yep
... it is paid off and it does not have to be paid back.
Anyone
next? Is there anyone- Yes.
I agree, but I would hope that the school would be
instrumental in helping us with the documentation that we would provide
to auditors and to those people who are setting
our bond rating.
Yeah.
Because it's
clear there's a good reason, right?
I think that our finance director said we have to explain that there's a good
reason that we're doing this, and it won't be as bad.
Yeah.
And I think it's clear there's a good reason.
Let's clarify that we are actually now talking to our
city manager and our finance director, and that what the
school board members are hearing may have impact on some decisions they
might make about their FY27 budget.
Yes, Counselor West.
Well, I think
they've made their decision on their budget, and they came in with 7%,
and we say whether we like that or not.
And then the second part is, we are willing to either wipe the slate
clean or do a million. Well, I was going to ask one more
clarification from the school-
Please
... about how much this deficit is likely to be. I'm sorry.
Were you saying that the food deficit is
something from even before this year?
Yes. So the nutrition fund is its own fund.
They also used to have their fund balance, which is now depleted,
kind of at the same time as ours is. But there is about
408 or so deficit in
the nutrition fund from FY25. And I've built that
into our
current deficit as a holistic look of
everything.
So yes, I think $2 million at the tops is more likely.
That includes nutrition last year and nutrition this year, and our school this
year.
Okay. Thank you. That's helpful.
Yeah.
Can I just ask a clarifying question on that?
Please.
If you don't mind.
Yeah, sure.
If our enrollment's down-
Mm-hmm
... over the last couple of years, why are we in such a deficit with the
nutrition
back to back years?
Mm-hmm.
And when we were at a deficit of 408,000 in
'25-
Mm-hmm
... how did we get... I'm trying to figure that out.
Mm-hmm.
It's a great question.
We also have a very brand-new nutrition director who has inherited
this.
The nutrition fund has run at a deficit for several years, drawing
on their fund balance.
It's a combination. There are two things, food and labor,
and that
is higher than what we get back from the state of Maine.
So every year you're going to run at a deficit.
Mm-hmm. Well, I think our nutrition director is very focused on getting this
into a more financially sustainable position.
In our current budget this year, I've budgeted for a more realistic, but I
think they really will have a deficit this year.
But the conversations are very much geared towards how can we
reduce that
moving forward.
We have to go back to junk food because it's cheaper than healthy food.
Well, we're trying to find that magical balance of serving-
Yes
... good food-
All right
... at a lower cost.
I got you. All right. Thank you.
Mm-hmm. Yes.
All right.
Okay. So the $2 million includes the food
deficits?
Yes. It does.
Okay. So we could choose a number,
like 2,200,000,
so it's not so open-ended, if people wanted to.
The mayor was saying one million. I think that's too low, but choose
some specific number and say up to
2,200,000.
And...
Okay. Yeah.
Which would help us do our own budget.
Yes.
Just going to make a small suggestion.
Because we won't know for sure how much it is until the end of the year is closed
out completely-
Right
... which might be August or September.
Yeah.
I would encourage you to put a up to amount and not a specific
$2 million. Because if it's less than that, then we might do less than that.
So I
would do an up to amount that you're comfortable with, and then we'll see what it
is.
And also, I will just say,
this discussion is
obviously related to the school's budget,
which has been noticed and publicized.
But this particular decision that relates to the city's
budget has not really been noticed, publicized,
and it just feels
potentially not the decision we should be making tonight.
Well, do we have to bring that up on agenda or not?
Yeah, I was going to say, can I just have input?
Yes, please.
So-
Me
... tonight we're giving guidance.
Right.
And I think the city manager has to bring that forward to an agenda or as part of
our discussion-
Thank you
... of the budget in the future, and that will be noticed.
Thank you.
Okay.
The guidance is good.
You got the guidance. I
don't think I'm required to summarize it,
but
you got it. Good luck, everybody.
We have to tell them whether it's six or seven.
We want to hear from the city manager.
Yeah.
They don't know now. They do not know right now-
I think, well-
... whether we're at six or seven.
And we need to give them guidance on that specific.
We really do.
Counselor Scott.
I just wanted to clarify that if we are going to an up to $2
million grant to fund a deficit, I am-
I would prefer six. So that's where I am.
I don't think I've changed. That's my guidance.
Okay.
Thank you.
We've got a six. Do you want me just to do it one more time?
I am up to eight, and with the... But I will do
seven. I will do 7%.
Well, are you, at this point... Okay.
7%.
Six.
Seven.
Six. You're a seven out of seven.
But what I heard Ellen Sanborn say, so that
we do have enough-
Can't say that's a classroom
... so up to 3 million.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Hey.
So up to 3 million, and with an expectation and
a hope that it is less. But what Ellen had said was,
"Don't put..."
Yeah, so that's why-
Okay
... up to doesn't mean that
3 million is there, but it's...
Okay. I-
So 7%.
Seven on the guidance.
No operational costs, and up to 3 million.
All right. And I was a seven. And Councilor Pride?
I would support up to eight, but that includes seven, obviously, and
Okay.
And I'm up to three, which includes two, obviously, so.
Yeah.
Okay.
I mean, that's how it's supposed to work.
They're supposed to make their budget based on our guidance.
Yeah.
If they choose to go to eight, then the people who aren't going to vote for eight
aren't going to vote for it.
I think we are doing what we're put up here to do.
Councilor West.
Seven, I would go up to seven.
Thank you very much. Councilor Matthews.
Do whatever you gotta do.
Do-
I'm at the point of, it's up to the voters.
God bless the voters, because they're gonna hold you guys accountable, and
I just...
Yeah. Well, we're part of the accountability, so.
Can I make one final request?
Yes, ma'am.
As you consider this, and you go forward, and I think I asked at
our school board council meeting, I
would love to support a budget that you think best serves our
students. Here's the dollar per student, here's the staff
ratio. This is what we think we need based on the needs of
our students, based on the staff that we have.
And, I feel like we are talking about a budget in
sort of an inertia category, and not necessarily like what
we need to serve a student in South Portland.
So, as we think about this going forward, as we need to sell this to
voters, I
really would like to understand what that sort of story is, and I think
anyone can sell that story of what do we need to serve a student in
South Portland? Maybe not the absolute best gold
standard, but I just would like to know that.
So I am happy to sell that story. I'm happy to consider that, but I
really would like to understand what those figures are,
anyway, going forward. Thank you.
Okay. Thank you.
Mr. City Manager, did you want to say anything?
No, I think we have the guidance. I do think it's important to
reiterate whether it's one million, two, or three.
Yes, it's over the 12%, but that is money that next year we would've used
for capital purchases.
Yeah.
And now city departments will suffer and not be able to get
certain capital purchases, plow trucks-
It's awful
... whatever it is, ambulances, those things are going to impact the departments
heads here, because that's not going to be repaid.
We just have to go into that clear-eyed.
All right.
I think we're going to...
I
hear whispering. I'm not sure why exactly.
I think we've done our job
of giving guidance, and I think it's going to
not change.
All right.
Just one very quick question, because I really think we have an
entire rest of the workshop.
No, I think we're still not clear, or Rosemary DiAngelis,
school board.
Well, I'm still not clear. Are we talking one million, two million, or three
million? We have to know that number, what your guidance is.
You're all over the place. I mean, you've been everything from,
"I don't care what you ask for," to-
We're just doing our best imitation of the school board.
Yeah. All right.
So I've got the-
All right. So-
I've got the guidance of 7%, but I-
... Rosemary, Madam Chair.
Yeah.
So I'm understanding your que-
You feel mystified by that-
That concept
... but clear on the other. Councilor West.
I'm sorry, but I disagree. This has to do with what we will
do with this year's deficit, which is going to be this year's deficit.
And that's part of our budget discussion, as part of our fund balance.
We're not really discussing that tonight. It sort of came up in the context.
So I think we've agreed as a council-
Yes
... what we're going to do, and we're going to move on.
We'll discuss the extent of the fund balance that we'll deal with the school board
in the future. But I think we have made it clear that we will make a
significant
grant to offset this year's
deficit, and before, it had always been that it was going to be requiring
repayment, which would've meant higher tax increases in the following
fiscal year.
Mm-hmm.
I think we're trying to avoid that the best we can.
There seems to be a little bit of difference of opinion on the council, but I'm
sure we'll work it out in the coming weeks.
That is a good summary, Councilor West.
We're going to nominate you to be a
summary committee of one.
All right. So, folks, I'd like to say
that this ends the school budget workshop part
of our discussion. I'd like to recess the council for
exactly five minutes, and then let's come back.
We're going to try to get this party started again.
Oh.
You're not getting it back.
Councilor Matthews,
return to the fold. Thank you. All right.
We are re-adjourned. No, we're
out of recess.
There we go.
And words.
We're moving on. So I think that you are
going to lead us, Mr. City Manager, and I think the first department we're talking
about is the City Clerk's department.
Yep, and before we get to those, just an overview, especially for newer councilors,
but you only do this once a year, so just as a refresher.
So we've split up the departments.
Some will be going tonight, some will be going in two weeks.
Each small department has about five to 10 minutes to do an overview.
Larger get about 10 to 15 to provide you with a brief overview of their budget.
If councilors wish to add, delete, increase, or decrease
funding for any sort of budget item,
we're going to keep track of these and add them to the parking lot.
So they're not decided on tonight like, "Yes, we're going to fund this new thing,"
or, "No, we're going to cut this." They're just added to the parking lot, and that
parking lot workshop is held on May 12th.
So everything from tonight and everything from two weeks from now that you put in
the parking lot, that's when you'll determine whether or not those items are
cut or included or increased or decreased from your final budget
that you'll vote on in June.
If you are looking to increase the budget, if there's an item that
didn't get funded or hadn't even been contemplated and you want to add it, the
charter does say that if you do make an increase after
the budget's been presented, if you do make an increase, the total proposed
expenditures, you also need to increase the total anticipated
revenue to at least that amount. You can also,
by inference, cut something else.
And so what we ask for is when we go through this
process, something to the effect of, "I would like to
add, remove, delete X amount in funding for this budget item in
the clerk department budget."
And that way, we know specifically what you're asking for and where the funding's
going to come from, in particular, if you're adding funding.
Sometimes we've seen councils just add like, "Hey, I don't know if I want to
fund this or not. I've just got questions." So sometimes there's questions
that get put in the parking lot like, "I'd like more information about this
topic, so that's why I'm going to put it there.
It's not that I want to necessarily cut it." So I guess that's an option as well.
So with all that said, we're starting off with the city clerk's budget.
The clerk's budget is up $25,000. That's a
6.9% increase.
Additional election costs and replacement voting booths are driving
much of the increase here. The impact to the median residential
taxpayer is $9.96 to fund this
department for the year, and they have no capital budget requests.
And I will turn it over to our city clerk, Jessica Hughes, to provide
additional information and answer questions.
Great.
Thank you.
So our additional cost comes predominantly through elections.
Fees and pricing for that has steadily increased.
And the additional part of that increase that is not listed
there is our record management portion.
We have not preserved or maintained some of our records for over a decade, so I
am trying to build in a small portion of that
to get us caught up and then to maintain those records.
Part of that is the records that we maintain for council,
but also our vital records that we do produce birth, marriage, and death
certificates from. So it is not specifically all elections, but majority of that
cost does come from elections. The piece that we are
looking to offset some of this is I have budgeted
for all of our election workers, our wardens, our ward clerks, who administer our
elections. However, we've given the option to those
individuals to volunteer their time as a part of their civic duty, and most of
our election workers want to do that anyway.
So we did put that in as part of our election clerk application this year that'll
be coming before council on the 21st,
and I'll be able to provide a little bit more adjustment to my budget at that
point. But currently, that's what the increase is for, is to make sure that we are
paying everyone the minimum wage that is required.
The replacement of our voting booths is specifically to our community center.
We have a set, I call them the accordion-style booths.
Those are our older booths, and every year we have a couple that are damaged, so
it's reducing the number that we have available.
By statute, we are required to have so many booths based on our population.
I am hoping with the savings that I am having in fiscal '26,
that I might be able to purchase them this year.
So we do have increases, but again, I'm trying to be very streamlined in how we can
conserve those funds for our budget.
The last piece that I will add that came up in conversation during our
recess is just being mindful of our election process with the school
budget. It is not built into the budget that we have a school budget that
is voted down by our voters, and then we have to go back
to have another school budget validation referendum.
That is not something that we have seen in our history of South Portland, so it is
not part of our budget. If we are concerned that that might be a topic
this year that we want to be mindful of,
that buffer will allow me to have those funds available to do a secondary
election. So even though I might be able to purchase the voting booths this fiscal
year, those funds might be able to be needed if we have to go back for a second
school budget validation referendum.
Just as some perspective, because we have not seen that in South Portland, so I do
want to be transparent with everyone.
That's all I have for you.
Thank you.
Can I ask a question?
So yeah, we do questions and then public comment and...
Yes. Sorry, I'm studying your budget.
Questions from the council. Councilor Walker.
I had a quick one. And I don't know if this belongs with you or it belongs with a
different department-
Sure
... so feel free to direct me, but who sets parking ticket rates?
Is that part of the clerk or did you just administer?
I didn't know with licenses and fees where that landed, so I wanted to ask that
question.
Sure. So that actually comes from the department for the fee.
Okay.
So we recently had them from the police department.
That came forward as part of the master fee schedule-
Okay
... for two parking fees that were adjusted.
Okay. So I will save my questions for that for the clerk.
Please.
Thank you.
Other councilors questions for our clerk?
All right. Do we have public comment on this item, the clerk's office
budget?
Anyone? All right. Well, we'll close public
comment on that topic.
Counselors, do you want to make any
recommendations for changes or parking lot items?
I don't see any.
Geez.
Wow, they're all going to be this easy, right?
You just jinxed us.
All right. Well, then I guess we move to our next topic.
Thank you so much, and thank you in advance to any election workers
who would like to volunteer.
Next up is our human resources budget.
This budget is up $6,415. That's an increase of
1.2%. This budget's annual cost to the median residential
taxpayer is $40.48.
Very few highlights here. Really the biggest thing is moving the Civil Service
Commission budget out of this department,
as they are now... We've changed the process, as council know.
You've changed the process for how committees request funding, and those requests
now show up in the council budget. There are no capital requests here,
and I'll turn it over to our HR director, Rob Meadow, to talk about any
other highlights that he wants to.
Thank you very much, and thank you for giving me a chance to speak tonight.
Let me just make two very quick points.
That $20,000 that was typically traditionally part of the
HR budget for Civil Service Commission, that's now moved over to Civil
Service Commission. It's no longer part of the HR budget, as the city
manager is explaining. I did not zero out that line.
I kept that line at 10,000. The reason I did that is if you look
at expenditures for civil service-related costs this
year, there's about 14,000
this year that was expended on
promotional
assessments for police and fire. About 14,000.
Last year, we spent 17,000 on
pre-hire psychological evaluations for police and fire.
If you combine those two costs, we're over $30,000.
So that's why, to be cautious, I kept some
money in that line in case we have
a year where we have significant numbers of new hires in police and
fire, and we have to do a lot of testing or
other costs related to that. So if you're wondering why I didn't just zero it
out, that was my thinking there.
The only other issue I wanted to mention is, as I mentioned before,
we're doing really well with the community college refunding
of training costs for us through the ALFON Grant program.
Mm-hmm.
And
as you know, the ALFON Grant will pay 50%
of tuition for trainings that our employees
undertake, provided we comply with their requirements, which
are quite light.
Sometimes the payment for these that we get back from the community college is
rather late. It's hard to predict when we're going to get that.
But in calendar year '25,
we brought in a little over $25,000.
That's money that we would be spending otherwise for this
training, and we're getting reimbursement for it, thanks in large part to
my colleague, Lou Cavalero, who handles this program for us.
So those are the only two items I wanted to mention. Thank you.
Thank you very much, Rob. All right, questions from
councilors?
Councilor Walker?
I just have a quick question about the office supplies.
I noticed it was up 160%. Can you talk about...
We
had to purchase a photocopier.
Okay.
That would do it.
Yeah.
Thank you.
All right. Any other questions?
What kind of photo...
Never mind.
All right.
Do we have members of the public who'd like to make a comment on this budget,
the HR budget? Doesn't look like we do, so that
is closed.
Counselors, anyone want to recommend any changes or parking lot
items?
It doesn't look like there are going to be. No?
Nope.
All right.
I think that we're going to move on then to the next department.
Thank you again, Rob. Thank you. Happy copying.
All righty.
Our next budget is social services general assistance.
This budget's down
over $360,000. That's a 19.3% decrease.
The annual cost of the median residential taxpayer of this department is
$21.94. And just so folks know, how we obtain that
number is we take the costs
for the department, we subtract non-property tax revenue.
So in this case, the state reimbursed 70% of most of the GA
costs, and then whatever is left over is what we need to raise from taxes.
And so we figure out what that impact is on the average tax
bill.This budget, there's big changes
because demand is down. Now, it's down significantly over the
past few years because there's
less applications, there's less use, because we did have that spike during the
pandemic, primarily due to the influx of folks being placed
into the hotels, which were being used as de facto shelters.
But before that happened, we were still seeing an increase
in need. And so despite that spike, we're still on an upward
trend. Even though we're down from the past few years, we're still on an upward
trend over what we saw in the late '19s.
But in reflection, or in reaction to the fact that
we are seeing a decrease in
requests, we have proposed eliminating a position
mid-year. And that position is now actually vacant, so we're going
to recommend this item be placed in the parking lot, and council can
realize a full year's worth of savings versus the half-year that
we've proposed.
And
again, we added two positions over the course of the past several years in this
department, so we're still going to be up one position over where
we were pre-COVID. And so that's still to deal with the increase in demand.
But again, over the past few years, we've seen a decrease in needs for our food and
rental assistance.
And so those budgets are decreasing significantly as well.
No capital requests here. And I'm going to turn it over to our Social Services
Director, Chris Pupke, to talk more about this and his budget.
Good evening. I'm Chris Pupke, Social Services Director.
I don't have much to add. Scott just gave me a great intro.
But effectively,
numbers are down from the 2023 peak, but still
above the historic numbers. We started to see an increase
in 2021, '22, really.
So we're still above those numbers.
But our projections are based on actual usage, which is why we did
a decrease for rent and food assistance, which those budget lines
had been inflated to deal with that large
increase in 2023. Those two specific types of assistance are things that
folks at the hotels would be accessing, versus something like, say,
electric assistance, which is for
renters.
So that's why we're kind of just getting those numbers down to more in line with
what we're using at the moment.
And
I do just want to add that
despite a decrease in the applications,
this is how I get those numbers. Those are the numbers that we report to Department
of Health and Human Services for reimbursement on a monthly basis.
Those are unduplicated, so
we will sometimes have to meet with somebody more than once a month.
So just because the application numbers might be down, doesn't necessarily
mean that it's just an equal decrease in actual
workload. If somebody comes in and applies for assistance at the start of the month
for their rent, and then comes back a few weeks later for their electric bill
because they didn't have the bill at the time of the first appointment, that's two
appointments, that's two meetings, takes about the same amount of time.
But still, our applications are definitely looking like
going in a good place. So I'm happy to answer any questions.
Just want to make sure people understand, too.
Thank you.
We're not denying anyone.
No.
If they qualify for assistance, this budget doesn't say, "Sorry, we've run out of
money," or, "We've cut that." Anyone who qualifies still gets assistance.
What we're saying is that because the demand is not there, we don't need to budget
as large of an amount. But this isn't reducing benefits we give to
anyone, either if they qualify, they're getting less, or they qualify,
but they're getting nothing. That's not the case.
And if there's a-
Just want to make sure that's clear
... a huge unanticipated increase in demand, something catastrophic
happens like global pandemic,
we can't deny assistance if we exhaust our budget.
So if I overspend on my food, the state says we
still have to provide that assistance.
Okay. Counselors, questions?
I have one, and I apologize if it should be clear to me from this, but I always
think it's a good idea to
understand how much of the GA
money in comes from the state and how much from South
Portland.
So the state reimburses 70% for the actual assistance side of it
and doesn't provide any reimbursement for the administrative side.
But the actual assistance we grant is reimbursed at a rate of 70%.
Okay. And there's
nothing that's going on, and that has been going on in Augusta that makes us think
that's going to change?
So there has been some talk of...
There's always requests to increase. We're always pushing for that.
Mm-hmm.
There has been some talk or some proposed legislation, I guess,
to potentially increase that amount.
But the last I heard, the
way to do that would be a tiered approach for the
bottom. It wouldn't include the top, I think, six communities, and
we're four. So it wouldn't change for us.
So in other words, they were going to-
Top six by size or by-
Spending. By GA spending.
Okay.
Yeah. So they were going to do an increase, I think
90%. I think it was 75% for the first year, and then 80.
Then it was going to go up every couple of years.
Mm-hmm.And it was going to be for,
again, the smaller communities that use less.
Okay. So our slice of the pie is considered kind of larger.
Got it.
Yeah.
Other counselors, questions?
Public comment on this budget.
Does anyone have public comment on this budget?
All right, doesn't look like we do.
Any council discussion of moving things? Counselor West.
I just want to thank the manager for noticing
that with a lesser demand, we could eliminate a staff position.
I do think as we go through the years, and it's very difficult for us
financially, we need to be aware of where demands are in
flux, and when we can reduce staff without reducing services to
the public, we need to do that. So thank you.
Councilor Pride
Can we put that mid-year reduction into the parking lot?
And it's a decrease. I'd like to eliminate the position
altogether.
Okay. You got that?
You got it? We already put it in there.
Right.
So this is formality.
As requested by the city manager. I'm just making... It's a formality.
All right. Yes. No, I approve.
Process.
I just want to make sure that we have our parking lot attendant.
Attendant Two.
Thank you.
All right. Any other councilors? No. Thank you, Chris.
And I wanted to say thank you to Rob, and I hope I thanked the city clerk before
she left. Thanks to all of you for preparing these budgets,
answering questions, the work you do,
it's much appreciated.
Okay. Moving next to the police.
Okay. Police.
Wasn't that public? Did you do public comment earlier?
Yes.
Yeah.
I missed that.
Hey. Wake up, D**k.
No, it's good to question me.
Police department budget is up to just under
$7.9 million. That's a $482,000 increase, up
6.5%. Annual cost to the median residential
taxpayer is about $445.
Some of the highlights, this is another department where even though the
position didn't live here before, it was in the parks department,
even though it was a school grant, but there's a whole background to that.
They had asked for the position through the Drug
Free SoPo Unite program, the one full-time position and one half-time
position be included in their budget.
In part due to living within the
guidance from council and also a directive, no new positions unless they could pay
for themselves, this amount was not included.
So that's $106,000 cost for,
I think it was three quarters of the year because the grant runs through October
1st,
the end of the federal cycle.
Because the wage increases for the new union contract, that's a
$382,000 increase.
There's some other highlights here, which I won't go through.
I will note, because I suspect there are folks here tonight for this, there
is funding for one additional
license plate reader, ALPR. Our contract is with FLOC, so some people
refer to them as FLOC cameras. This would be a complement to
our existing fleet that the chief has requested.
There are four capital item requests.
Three of them we were able to afford funding for.
So there's a negotiator van replacement, a street closure, portable
barriers that are put up when streets are closed,
a motorcycle replacement that the chief's been asking for a while.
We were unable to
fund the UTV replacement vehicle,
as shown here. So I'm going to turn it over.
I know chief has some things he wants to talk about.
And then also we're going to hear from folks from SoPo Unite
as well about that position. So I'll turn it over to Chief Ahearn.
Thank you, Mr. City Manager, Dan Ahearn, your police chief.
Thank you, Mayor, for the opportunity. Thank you, city councilors.
As Scott mentioned, we are up 5.7%.
The cost drivers are always going to be our wages and our vehicles.
Those are the big money items at the police department.
Wages are up due to two
contracts being negotiated with help from you, with help
from Rob Netto.
We were able to
negotiate those two contracts, both patrol and command.
And that's done
in time for our budget to be completed. That was great work.
The reason why they're up so much is because we were working through comps in
our local areas like Westbrook,
which they had a really big contract, so we
were playing catch up with them, trying to get our folks
comparably paid. We lost an
officer recently to Westbrook, and when I had my exit interview with her, it was
due partially to
their wage agreement.
Vehicle purchases are up
with upfit costs rising as well. We had to add
$11,000 to the budget, which was not previously budgeted
for. Small claims deductibles. When
our vehicles are involved in accidents, we weren't
budgeting for those deductibles through MMA.
Software subscriptions, contracted services continue to show increases.
The automatic license plate readers cameras, we have seven of
those.
Those are at a cost of about... What you see now
is about $3,000 for a licensing fee, is how it kind of works
out right now. So I have that cost at $21,500.
Again, seven
stationary ALPRs. ALPRs in the vehicles we've had for
15 or so years.
The addition that we're going to talk about a little bit tonight with the city
manager,
being fiscally responsible, cut that, but the SoPo
Unite program at the high school that our school
resource officers work very closely with.
I'm still a little bit unsure on where we are with school resource officers,
because
I don't know if they're going to fund that.
So if they're going to fund that, that's great, but if they're going to cut
it, then we're responsible for
$130,000 in lost revenue,
I believe.
Well, yeah. So the benefits shows up in the HR budget, so it's 220
with benefits.
So, there now. You put that cost back on them,
and if they cut them, we still have them. We still have police officers.
I just want to point that out. I was a little unclear as to whether they were
supporting that program or not going forward.
So,
would like to know that. Recruitment and retention continues to be a
primary focus for us.
Union wages will keep us in step with comparable departments as I said, allowing us
to better recruit and retain quality individuals.
Our CIP budget, as the manager stated, vehicles continue to be a main
driver.With this year's request for negotiator van replacement,
our second motorcycle, which adds to our traffic unit.
We have a second traffic officer. Traffic
continues to be our number one complaint, as you all know.
You get the same emails that I receive.
So we were able to add a second traffic officer, and we need to upgrade that
motorcycle. He just recently went and completed his motor officer
school, very difficult school to complete, so we're up on board there,
but we need to upgrade that motorcycle.
Portable traffic barriers will help us immensely when we're closing down our roads
for things like our parades, the Bug Light
Park festivities that we have, 4th of July road races.
Anywhere we might have an emergency, accident, or
something of that nature where we have to close down a road, these are portable and
easily deployed.
A 2026 update. As you know, we have our
annual report online, so you can review that online, but I'd like to highlight a
few things. We continue to see... I'm kind of rushing. I'm sorry.
Continue to see an increase in calls for service.
Individuals suffering from mental health and substance use disorders driving those
increases. Our behavioral health liaisons,
help officers handle these calls, providing invaluable resources to our community
members. The police department currently has three vacancies in our sworn officers
complement and one behavioral health liaison vacancy.
We have one officer in the academy graduating in June and one officer who
recently joined our department from Philadelphia.
If you agree to shift the burden to...
Well, I'm not going to talk about the SROs because we talked about that.
Our patrol division continues to struggle with forces.
This is due in part to four officers being placed on light duty for a
variety of medical reasons, including injuries suffered while at work.
Filling these vacancies add to our use of overtime funds. If the S...
Yeah.
In March, I traveled to Tucson, Arizona, with our CALEA
team,
accreditation team. We received our CALEA Accreditation Award.
There are only four agencies in Maine that have achieved this award.
This is a long four-year process where we must prove
and demonstrate our commitment to professional excellence in policy and practice.
This is our third award, and we begin the quest for our fifth
as we return to Maine. We continue to increase our community engagement
with more Coffee With the Cops events and recently coordinated our Senior Walk
program, where we meet with seniors every Monday morning in our community
and walk and talk for an hour. Next week's talk is at Bug Light, and
encourage you to join us.
Almost
done.
Each year, we have an annual report.
You can see more of the highlights and our stats on the website on our
annual report. Your support of this budget request will enable us to continue to
upgrade our fleet, help us attract and retain quality individuals for our team,
and provide the necessary equipment and training needed to carry out our public
safety mission. With this requested budget, we'll be able to continue to provide
professional police services expected and deserves for every member of our
community.
I would love to ask you to allow me to have Leanne Dodge come up.
She is the director of the SoPo Unite program.
She would be far better
able to give you the information that you need to make an informed decision
on this program. Okay?
Yes. Thanks. Please bring Leanne up.
And then I'll be available for questions over here.
I'll-
I'm Leanne Dodge, program director of SoPo Unite: All Ages,
All In. I know it sounds cheesy, but superintendent at the
time chose that little tagline, so anyone can be part of it.
And our mission is to create and sustain a safe, just, and healthy community
to prevent youth substance use. And we focus on six to
18-year-olds. I work for the whole city,
but my office this whole time has been in the high school, which has been awesome.
In fact, when I first started, my colleague said, "Don't even bother working with
the youth. They're too busy. They're not here long."
So I was like, "Yeah, but I'm right here in the high school.
Seems like
access to them." So we started a youth subcommittee with about
five students in 2016. So we're in year 10 of
federally funded grant.
And in these last nine and a half years, we've now had close to
500 students involved in SoPo Unite.
And I'm going to share some of the successes that they've done, and hopefully, you
all received this packet of
information. I don't know if you had time to look through it.
And I have our youth consultant here, Sarah
Jorgensen, who in a moment is going to hand out a couple more things that
just came out.
But I'll just share a couple of quick things.
The part of the brain that's best, that is ready to take risks, if
anyone wants to guess, when do you think that's fully developed? When it's...
Yeah, I'll do it.
25.
Like 22. So it's way younger. This is the risk-taking
part of the brain.
Oh, risk-taking.
Yeah, I'll do it. If your friend jumped off a bridge-
Bridge.
... how old were you then? So it's 13.
Oh.
And it's not till 12 years later that your brain says, "Hey, that wasn't a good
idea."
And so I've had the great opportunity
to work with this age brain. Your brain's best for learning from
13 to 20 without much effort. So we
have students that play six instruments, some that speak
five languages fluently. I kind of know English.
But the bummer is 90% of addiction starts
before 18.
Yep.
So we have a very short window of opportunity to work with these young people.
And in your packet, you'll see the main integrated youth health survey
data has seen a decrease in South Portland substance use
with young people. So it's working.
So that's the quantitative piece.
So a few qualitative pieces,
just some successes, ripple effects.
Our big thing we passed, and D**k, I don't know if you were on school board
then2018, we were the second school in the
country that didn't suspend students out of school for substance use
violations. We used restorative practice.
When I first started, if you got caught using-
Wow.
I know. It was.
You were kicked out of school for seven to 10 days.
That's also known as two weeks of not being in school.
What do you think you were doing for two weeks?
Homework? Yeah.
Volunteering? Yeah.
So we changed that to restorative practice, where a student
is held accountable. It's actually a very adult process, and they get assessed by a
social worker in the school, have to take accountability for their
actions, and have interventions if need be.
So what was cool is we were the second school in the country, then it turned
into us being in a national guidebook, for many other
states have now adopted our policy.
And also Ken Kunen, who's in Santiago, Chile,
they have it there too, so it's an international policy that South
Portland adopted. We also changed our athletic code.
If you as an athlete got caught,
we would kick you off the team for 14 days.
Don't show up, don't come to the game, don't come to practice, you're dead to us.
"It's a privilege to be a Red Riot," that's what I first heard.
I was like, "All right, it's a game." But anyway.
So now we use restorative practice in athletic code.
Some schools nearby recently adopted our code because they
had, if you got in trouble at least one time, second
time, you're banned from sports all four years.
Oh.
Never to play again. Raise your hand if you were an athlete in high school, and
that was maybe your only fun thing. Yeah, I see some hands up.
I taught for 20 years the class for folks who were arrested for operating under the
influence, the kids that were under 21.
Many of them had been suspended from school or kicked off of
athletic teams. So that's always been in my mind, if we could work on this
now while we had access to young people.
So I just shared that piece. And two other quick fun,
great things that have evolved is, and I gave you all a
problem gambling graphic novel, which I always thought sounded
inappropriate, but it's like a cartoon book.
Four of our students are the characters in this.
Did you know that problem gambling sometimes starts at age 10?
And it's connected to substance use and suicide.
And the teacher across the hall from me, her husband worked at Oxford
Casinos, and someone hung themselves while he was working.
He was a security guard.
So it's serious. It starts at a young age.
Four of our students are the characters in this book.
It's now in 27 states and comes with a health class
curriculum. Again, this is not what we had planned.
We were just like, "Yeah, let's do this book.
That'll be cool."
And then two last things. I lied, there's two more.
The other thing is we have a lot of athletes that are part of SoPo Unite.
And years ago we asked them, "Hey, Josh, you're a captain.
What kind of training do you get?"
And he looked at us like he's looking at us now.
"What are you talking about?" Like,
"No training?" So Officer Gray, who was our school resource
officer at the time,
and a couple of other colleagues, we created a captain's training that was for
every season, and it was an hour long, and we had alumni
captains come back and talk about their experiences,
and we did that for three years.
And one of our students who-- Sometimes captains are a captain more than once.
And this one guy told me, "I almost fell asleep that
last time." Because he'd been through it a couple times.
So now Sarah Jorgensen, who's here, is our youth consultant.
She and others, with Officer Gray and others, created a
nine-session leadership academy for athletes this year.
We've already completed eight of the sessions, and we have college and
university coaches come and speak to them.
They learn about mental health, nutrition, all those great things.
So,
I'll leave you with this, and Sarah's going to pass it out to you, is another
testimony from a statewide agency.
And some of you
came to a meeting two years ago with our students who wanted to
improve transportation in South Portland.
And you might wonder, well, what does transportation have to do with substance use
prevention? Well, if you can't get to all the great places in South
Portland,
thank you, sorry, it's not that great if you can't get there.
So our students created
a map of South Portland, and we had an art contest,
and it's going to be made into huge posters into the middle school, Red
Bank Community Center, so that students know how to take the bus
or how long it might take you to ride your bike over to Wainwright,
which has a cool picture.
So I'll just leave you with that this work has a
ripple effect, and unfortunately, with substance use, the
work is never done. I wish I could say, like, by Friday, there will be
no more youth substance use. I can retire.
There will always be a need to do prevention.
And the more prevention you do, the less treatment and
recovery resources you need to provide.
So thank you, guys.
I'll shut up.
Thank you. No, that was fascinating. Thank you so much.
So an invaluable program, fully supported.
90%
of all addiction start at 18. 90%.
Hm. Big number.
She told me that, and I almost fell on the floor.
Wow.
Everybody loves her. We love her. This program is invaluable.
This is about prevention and proactivity,
and it's far easier and cheaper to
treat people and try to keep them from becoming addicted
to treating them in addiction protocols
Thank you for coming and sitting and spending the time, and thank you to
Detective Gray for being probably the best SRO in Maine.
I'm ready.
Okay.
I'm ready for all of you.
All right.
We're going to have councilor questions, then we'll have public comment.
It seems to be a bit of a pattern. Councilors. Councilor Walker.
Okay.
I have several questions, but I want to ask my SoPo Unite one before I
get distracted.
Ms. Morrelli, what is South Portland's percentage that we get of
the Opioid Fund settlement or settlement fund money?
I don't know the percentage, but every dollar we receive is taken up by funding
behavioral health liaisons.
So
when I looked at the... There was a thing in the paper, it was timely, and so I
went out, and I looked, and it looked like we have the money
budgeted for two positions right now.
Mm-hmm.
And then it looks like there's still a significant amount of money available that
we're not using there. Did I read that wrong?
Yeah, no. The amount we get each year covers the costs for that.
We do have some funds that were built up initially
that we received before we ended up spending on them, but
at some point, we're tapering off receiving what we get for
the opioid funds over the years. So every few years, that amount gets
less, so eventually those two positions will fully be on the tax rate because
we'll have exhausted our opioid settlement funds.
And you said you have an open behavioral
specialist position right now-
Yes... correct?
Yes, correct.
And you fully need all three?
The department... The reason I'm asking is I wonder if we could shift some of that
money towards funding the SoPo Unite position.
So we have two, not three.
Okay.
Yeah, two behavioral liaisons.
And one is open.
And one is open, correct.
Okay.
And you need both. I assume.
Yes. As I said, the-
I know. It's a silly question. I know.
Well, I'll tell you. So our calls for service are up, but our calls
for service are different as well.
So we're going to these mental health crisis calls.
We're going with our behavioral health liaisons.
The great model was this co-response model where they would
co-respond with us. We make the scene safe, and then we
allow them to come in and do their professional work that they do.
They're
licensed social workers.
Yeah.
They have the skills and the training that we don't have.
We have very minimal training. Although we have good training,
it's minimal. And so we're actually transitioning,
and the plan now is to transition to
them taking on the onus of those calls.
They develop those relationships with the
people in our community that we recognize that need these helps.
They come up with safety plans. They provide the resources. They do the follow-up.
You'll hear it oftentimes if you have a scanner on, you're like, "Hey, can you go
to 123 Main Street?" I hope that's... Yeah.
Probably a bad example. And because so and so is upset, and he's throwing things
around again, and he's off. "I'll go." And you'll hear one of our behavior,
"I got that. I'm going to go. I'll let you know if I need any help." So that's the
model where we want to get to because that frees up our officers to do all the
work.
Because I really want to find a way to fund that position. I agree with you.
I think it is instrumental.
Is there a possibility, and I don't know who to direct this question to, but is
there a possibility that there is future grant money to fund that position in the
future, and we are just in this kind of in-between period right now?
So
Leanne did a really good job. She has
a second,
and that position is going to be funded through a grant.
I'm sure that she is looking at other grants. This is a 10-year grant.
We've been
on the dole here for 10 years with this program, so we're way, way ahead.
I know it comes from somewhere, but
yeah. If there's
a program that should be funded through federal grant funding, it
should be this program, right? So I have to assume there is.
We'll continue to look for those grant funds to do that, but I'd
hate to see this work, this really good work,
fall off the wayside because we can't find
the money to fund it.
I have the information, too, on the opioid, just to clarify for everybody.
So the wages and the benefits of the BHLs, this is a little bit
dated information, but is around $205,000 a year.
In FY27,
we expect to get about 69,000 in opioid settlement funds.
In FY28, we expect to get 98,000. '29,
98,000. '30, 91. 2031, we get
84. And then over the next couple of years, it's in the 70s, 60s, 50s.
So it's still peaking, and then it will go down, and there is
some money initially built up, and like I said, in part because I think there
was a little bit of a financial issue where we weren't charging the
positions the opioid funds at first, even though that was the direction of council.
But they are now. So I just wanted to provide that information about what we're
receiving versus what we're spending is not...
They're definitely out of whack. They're not covering the full amounts annually.
All right.
Okay.
I'd like to put that item in the parking lot if I could to be paid for
with property tax.
I do have a couple other questions.
I thought I saw something going on over here in the way of a question. No.
Okay.
No.
Yes. No.
I don't think we put things in the parking lot till council discussion after public
comment.
Oh, sorry. I apologize.
Yeah, okay.
Just a procedural thing, but-
So-
Sorry.
It's okay.
Okay. You have more questions, but you guys didn't have any questions. Go for it.
Parking fees
Can we-
Parking fines
... parking fines. Yes.
How do we discuss increasing parking fines?
We have, I understand, some of the lowest parking fines in the greater
Portland area.
So we just addressed that. So we just created...
We went from 20 to 50, so we are comparable,
and we went to $150 for
people that are parked in violation of the
overnight parking and storms. So
it was-
And I think, Ellen, how much did you estimate in additional revenue from that?
25.
20. Huh?
25,000 or hundred?
Thousand.
Thousand. Okay.
So I just met today with
Milan Nevidor, and there's an issue
down at Romney Road, the
Hannaford staging area. So we're dealing with that.
And Melissa-
Yeah.
So,
Melissa and I, and Milan, and the assistant city manager
trying to figure out a way to keep these trucks from ruining our road down there
from parking in no parking spaces.
So it was suggested to me that through these conversations we've
had, and we've tried to play nice in the sandbox and continue our
professional relationship with this great business partner.
But they keep pointing the finger at subcontractors, not Hannaford
employees, and there's not a lot we can do about it.
They were going to build up the parking yard that they used to have, and that was
going to
let these trucks queue in that yard and not deteriorate
our road there. As you can see, the soft shoulders eroded away.
It's creating all kinds of problems.
So he was suggesting that we come up with a $1,000 fine for parking
there. I'm all for it. I'll suggest it. I'll write up the memo. I'll present it.
All for it.
Great.
Because that's the only way that we're going to get their attention down there.
I think we're at the right
place for our fines right now, 50 and 150.
I think those are in line with area places.
Okay. Thank you.
Okay.
Other councilors with questions? No.
I just want one clarifying. Did you say that we have three
liaison positions or two?
No, two.
Okay, thanks.
And one is currently vacant.
Oh, one's currently vacant. Oh, I thought you said two.
Yeah.
That's where I got confused. Okay, thanks.
All right, Carter. I mean, Councilor Scott.
It's fine. Councilor Carter, I like that.
This is sort of a broad question across several departments, but I just noticed
the
sort of salary and overtime and hourly expenses seem
very different, and I wonder if there's sort of an analysis
of savings in terms of bringing hourly
employees into a salary position, if that saves time in terms of hourly and
overtime. And again, I'm the new kid on the block.
Sure.
But for now, I can only claim that for a little bit longer.
But just trying to understand that-
I used to be the new person, too. I loved that one.
So we only have two salary positions, the deputy chief and myself, and everything
else is by union contract. So it's all hourly.
Okay.
Thank you.
Thank you. Anyone else, questions? All right.
We're going to open public comment on the police
department budget.
Come on down. We'd like to hear your name.
You can state the street that you live on if you'd like to.
Awesome. Sounds good.
Good evening, members of city council.
My name is Alex Potter, and I am a new South Portland resident
on Sandy Hill Road.
I became a resident of South Portland just October of last year.
Listening to the difficult discussions tonight regarding the school budget, I want
to start by saying that I moved here with my wife, we're expecting our first child
in a couple of weeks, specifically to start a family
because we heard that the schools here
are so good, that the community is so good for raising a
family in. So thank you guys for the hard work that this community has put together
to make that happen.
I'm also a former Army infantry officer, West Point graduate,
a former Army Ranger, and a veteran of deployments to Afghanistan, Iraq, and Syria.
This is relevant because I know what it takes to secure a nation.
I know what it takes to deal with bad actors.
I have a profound respect for the law enforcement officers here tonight
who work hard to protect this community and who might see this
technology, which is AOPR, which is, I'm sure, what everyone's expecting to
discuss tonight. They see that as a benefit.
And I also understand that we have had that in vehicles for 15 years, and we have
seven cameras already.
Excuse me. You have to talk to the mic.
Oh, got it. Sorry.
Okay, thanks.
Yep, we've had the
ones in the vehicles for 15
years, and we have seven already.
I still think that the world has changed with artificial intelligence and
the ability to
actually use all of this data.
Back when I was deployed, we could get hundreds of thousands of terabytes of
data. But if you can't process it, then it doesn't really matter. Now we can.
So this is a fundamental shift.
Benjamin Franklin famously warned that those who would give up essential liberty to
purchase a little temporary safety deserve neither liberty nor safety.
We are a nation built on that exact principle, codified in our Constitution and our
Fourth Amendment.
These cameras flip bedrock presumption of innocent until proven guilty
entirely. They subject every single citizen to a digital dragnet,
tracking our vehicles and our movements using artificial intelligence to establish
our daily baselines just in case we commit a crime.
Technology like this will inevitably be abused.
I saw firsthand in Syria what happens when authorities gain access to unchecked
surveillance. There are always people who enjoy having that kind of power over
others, and corruption naturally followsYou can write all
the local checks and balances you want-
30 seconds
... this data enters a
network accessible across a massive variety of agencies.
We may trust our local police, but this is going to the federal level if there's a
flock camera.
Once we feed local data into the federal system, we lose control here in South
Portland, where local governance actually matters.
We also have to think beyond the immediate moment.
The political pendulum of the United States always swings.
If you're a supporter of the current administration, think if the other side has
this power. If you're not a supporter of this current administration-
Time
... I don't think I have to say anything else.
Good timing, I guess.
Thank you. Well done. Thank you very
much.
I'd like to talk about...
Let's see. The-
Could you please say your name?
Yeah. My name is Wayne Broderick, live on Union Street.
And in
about October 31, Sanford last year was going through quite an ordeal on these
flock cameras. You guys must be aware of it, that the city council was kind of
flip-flopping and eventually went with what the citizens said because they were
very concerned. At the same time,
about a week later, November 10th, there was a flock camera installed in South
Portland down at Cash Corner. I had messaged Jessica, and she didn't really know
much about it, and I
did get to find out a little bit about it.
It turns out that instead of messaging, like putting something on the
council website or announcing this awesome new technology that we're going to get,
it was just
nothing. I mean, why wasn't there something on the
page? I had to email. It should've been announced.
There should've been some kind of transparency rather than this kind of silent
rollout. So from the very beginning of this implementation, it's been
kind of covert, maybe hoping people didn't understand.
I remember one of the councilors mentioned to me about the budget and that it
was funded through a grant. Well, that's what they're doing, is they're giving
these grants to get these cameras so that it doesn't go through any budget.
It doesn't get approval from the councilors.
You guys may not have even known that it went up.
And this flock company, those cameras can do a lot more
than just license plate readers. They take photos of the people in the vehicle.
They take photos of what the vehicle's got in the pickup truck bed or whatever.
One person in another city was tracked 525
times in a month on these cameras.
And you have to remember, Edward Snowden in 2013 had told
us about some of these violations that the NSA was doing, and this
is
bound to be abused. It's already been abused if you look up the lawsuits.
Other cities have taken these cameras right out because they're just not...
Some of them because they were deemed to be accessible to the public.
They didn't want them to have it anymore.
And
it's borderline unconstitutional because it does create a digital
dragnet of everybody, whether or not you've done anything wrong.
The
information isn't held locally. It's held in these national servers, and these
companies aren't really... They're into profit, so they're going to try to
sell your data to other companies. They're going to cooperate with ICE.
So by allowing these cameras, you're essentially feeding that information to ICE.
30 seconds.
And
it's just
to not have transparency at the beginning, I think, is what bothers me the most
because you can say, "Well, we're going to be whatever." But the rollout,
especially considering everything that was going on in Sanford, to just do it
silently seems to be in poor taste.
And I don't think you guys had all the information about it or maybe didn't share
that you knew because
it just was not a very transparent rollout like we'd expect to see with law
enforcement.
Time.
Thank you very much.
Keep them coming, folks, if you're here for commenting.
Hi, everybody. Alex Redfield on Cooper Street.
Thank you to the council, Mr. Morelli, Mayor Tipton,
and all of the city staff and leaders who put a lot of
work into this meeting, this budget, and making the city a place I'm
happy to live in and raise my kids in.
I have been to more city council meetings than usual recently, and I've tried a few
different approaches to help my comments land.
Tonight, I'm going to try authenticity.
I took a second to check in with my six-year-old about what I've been doing for the
last two Tuesdays. I told her the city is coming together to figure out what
to spend money on next year, that there's not quite enough to do everything for
everyone right now, and everyone's trying to figure out what's most important.
She told me the answer to that question.
She said the most important thing is that there is a new swimming pool with open
swim after 3:00 that I can go to after school.
So if you can make that happen, that would be really helpful.
I chose not to bring up with her the issue that I'm here to speak about tonight,
the police department's contract with Flock Safety, because I don't really know
how to do it in a way that I feel good about.
I can't quite figure out how to say that there are cameras out there that know
when we go to the trampoline gym, and that the police use those cameras to
find bad guys, but that other police outside of South Portland have
used those same cameras to do awful things to good people who have done nothing
wrong. I'm not ready to take on that conversation about how
and why we would prioritize this over any number of essential projects
and costs that truly build a better, safer community, let alone a new
swimming pool.
So I'm asking for your help in making sure that we can all talk about this and feel
good as we do so. If you, as stewards of the city and the
institutions within it, can confidently say that our relationship with
Flock is fundamentally different than the relationship between the Mountain View,
California, Police Department, where Flock recently was
revealed to have enabled a nationwide sharing setting without local authorization,
that would help me feel better. If you can learn why the hits on South
Portland cameras come up 1,200 times in the haveibeenflocked.com public
database of audit logs released from police departments in Texas and Georgia
that have signed 287G agreements with federal immigration
agencies, that would help me, too.
And until you have that certainty and confidence and can help communicate that to
the growing number of citizens who are concerned about this decision and its
impact, I'd urge you to heed the guidance offered by Pedro Vazquez on
behalf of the Human Rights Commission last week.
And to paraphrase, that guidance was to recognize that this continuing partnership
with this company creates risk at best and harm at worst to the segments
of our community that are most in need of rebuilding trust at this moment.In
summary, please park this. Help everyone dig into issues at play
here. Bust out the fine-tooth comb, or I guess, yeah, as
Councilor Matthew said earlier, let's take the time to dive deep to ensure
that our spending commitments across all departments-
30 seconds
... are getting the same level of scrutiny that our school budget did, and to
ensure that all of our investments are actually building public safety, trust,
and well-being, and in alignment with our city's values. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Additional public comment on the police budget.
Hi, I'm James Laplante. I live on Broadway.
I'm a small business owner and a resident of South Portland, and I'm here to
ask you to reject the additional funding requested for the
Flock camera systems that the city police currently
utilize.
I'd also like to request that the city end its contract with Flock in
no undue terms, and remove these cameras from our neighborhood
as soon as possible. While I appreciate the
public safety services of our police department, I do not think the benefits of
these camera systems outweigh their risks.
Flock cameras are operated by private corporations that collect
local data from these cameras to be used in a nationwide database.
That database collects license plates and other
information like facial recognition.
Some cameras can even collect audio.
These cameras have been proven to have security issues
in the data that they collect and how they are shared.
The data that is collect is being used in AI
analytic systems that are controlled by a company called Palantir.
Yeah.
Palantir is funded by Peter Thiel, a tech billionaire who has
been quoted as saying he no longer believes that freedom and democracy
are compatible.
Think about who is in charge of our data, our data that is going to these
companies. We've been told not to worry about these cameras.
They're only being used to track criminals. I'm a law-abiding citizen.
I've never broken the law. I've barely gotten a speeding ticket.
I take pride in being a contributing citizen to the city.
I take pride in using my First Amendment rights.
I attend peaceful protests in South Portland to raise my voice about
matters exactly like this, and I am
unapologetically anti-fascist.
Last September, the White House issued a presidential memo expanding the
definition of domestic terrorism to include
anti-fascism.
The Joint Task Force of Terrorism has been directed to investigate individuals or
groups that hold these ideologies or participate in anti-fascist
activities like peaceful protests.
The data that is being collected by these cameras can be
used to investigate peaceful protesters, and it will come from these
Flock cameras in our neighborhood.
It might not happen today, but it will happen.
I do not trust that a corporation is in control of our private data
or how-
30 seconds
... it will be used. I think that the risks of having these cameras in our
neighborhoods outweighs the risks of our freedom, our privacy, and
far outweigh the benefits of these police tools.
South Portland did a fine job before they had these cameras were installed, and
I'm confident they will continue to do a good job without them.
Our crime rates are dropping. These cameras have nothing to do with it.
Again, I ask this council to stop this contract, to reject
it, and to get these cameras out of our city. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Others?
Carlton Parsons, South Portland.
Good evening, Council.
I was tasked,
and at requested by a group of concerned citizens
not to measure Flock by
their human rights abuses, but simply by the quality of
their company.
So I did my research and used my analytics and research and academic
tools to the test. Looking at the Flock research website,
all of its research papers and case studies are paying customers,
saying exactly what worked with no real methodology or
statistical model.
What started as a critique of Flock and their promises of
improvements quickly became a larger analysis,
covering a wide variety of white papers over
the past five years.
On the landmark Flock white paper itself, the study was
authored and funded by Flock employees themselves.
Only 74% of the total respondents made it to the final
data. The self-reported attribution from
those agencies,
the authors themselves even concede that they cannot establish a
causation
in doing so, unlikely that their
research will show that
Flock has contributed.
Including other research papers as well, an Atlantic
City study, the most recent and rigorous form,
found no reduction in overall violent crime rates, despite
scanning every single vehicle entering the city.
99% of scans by captured vehicles
are connected with people with no crimes.
Not only that, but there's documented real-world positive incidents that
are plenty, including armed detentions in Aurora,
California with a $1.9 million
settlement, and CBS News verifying that more than a
dozen such incidents have happened in a six-month investigation.
I am more than happy to provide the City Council with a more
thorough and provided research if you would allow me to do so.
I am here to serve you and the citizens, and to provide a measured
response in the effectiveness of Flock.It is up to us
to decide whether these small improvements to
crime are worth the risk to our community, and
also to those relationships. The relationships
between the community and the police ourselves
all rely on those relationships. They
provide those trusts to solve those more violent crimes.
Those, and even within those studies, said that
traditional policing every time outperforms Flock.
So for us, it's important to look at the data and
measure what is the most effective.
And I'm happy to share those results with you by email. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Hi. Kaylee Moore, Delbert Street.
I'd like to just reflect on kind of two recent experiences.
Um, the ICE surge in January, which many of us were
stepping up to help our neighbors, and we now know many of our neighbors were not
criminals even though they were detained.
In talking with other cities that have gone through similar experiences,
we were told when we were driving into these communities we should be covering our
license plates with snow, we should be turning our phones off.
I don't think I personally thought that moving to South Berlin, those would be
things that I would be considering, and it is really deeply upsetting.
I'm sure we also all saw the video of the Portland
resident who was told she's now in a database when she was just
existing in her town.
As we discussed, and as our police chief discussed, behavioral health is actually
what will stop crime. I used to be a social worker. I deeply believe that.
It was really cool to hear about your program.
Those to me seem
like much better things to be supporting and funding than something that will
be tracking us, not because we have a police department that is
behaving inappropriately, but because we live in a country that I think we really
can't trust other people with our data right now.
So I just would like to ask that you stop the contract,
that you move that funding to something more productive.
We just sat and listened to what is happening within our town,
and that we focus on the things that we know will keep us safe, like proactive and
preventative mental health services and other things.
So I think just to reiterate, everyone else here spoke so well.
It is so important to me that I can feel safe and that everybody feels
safe, and the cameras are in certain locations, and they are targeting certain
people, and that is just not, I think, what we all want for our
town and our community. So thank you very much.
Thank you.
And I don't know if I'm allowed to give my extra time to somebody else, but
Thank you for being generous.
Anyone else? Yes. So it looks like we have at least two people.
Come on.
I think we have two after me, if I saw correctly.
Willis Duvall, Ocean View Avenue.
I'd like to echo everything that everyone else said.
I didn't go to ranger school. I'm not a data analyst.
But I do have two kids that I'm raising here.
And there were two flanks that kind of stuck out to me in this conversation.
Before I came in, I was watching the video feed, which I think we're very fortunate
to have.
And the cost of an ed tech came up.
It's roughly double the cost of this Flock program.
So the idea that we would cut half an FTE from an already cash-strapped school
department to fund clearly extra-constitutional data surveillance,
it's inexplicable to me, and I mean this in the most civil way
possible, it will have severe electoral consequences for anyone who supports it.
Probably legal too.
But this is an issue that everyone I've talked to, as soon as they hear about it,
is outraged.
They don't believe that this council, that I think is generally fairly well viewed,
would support it.
And after a hellish experience with federal law
enforcement in this community less than three months ago,
our police department is asking for more money for the exact tools that
enabled that kind of encroachment on our rights.
I think we have very good reason to be skeptical of exactly how cozy
local enforcement actually is with those authorities,
as the Press Herald discovered.
And we can talk about procedure all we wish,
but this is something that has
very, very, very little public support, and for good reason, legally,
morally,
and financially. And if we're talking about a cash-strapped community, this is
absolutely not something we should be spending money on.
And frankly, if it were free, we couldn't get paid enough to accept it.
I too have a small daughter who lives in this community.
She lives in my house.
And she's very curious, she's very talkative, and she asked a lot of
questions when ICE was here. She asked why people were standing on corners
protesting. She asked why there were very,
very interesting people walking around her school in orange vests to make
sure the kids were safe. She asked why they're still walking around her
school to make sure the kids are safe.
I can't really tell them it's that
we want our kids to stay safe, and I can't tell them it's because there is a
federal government that has very little interest in enforcing its own rules to
protect us as citizens, and the fact that this,
I would like to think, enclave of moral and-
30 seconds
... legal virtue,
would even consider something like this,
again, I mean this civilly and peacefully, there will be severe, severe electoral
consequences.
And it is morally unforgivable.
And this is to say nothing of the clear racial disparities that clearly
disadvantage the people who are not represented in this room.
Certainly not on the council, and that's no fault of your own, but it ought to be
considered. Thank you for your time, thank you for this marathon meeting, and thank
you for hearing me.
Thank you very much. Next.
Thank you.
Hi, I'm Shelby Leighton. I live on Stanley Street.
We have gone through a lot of pain in the last
few weeks about raising the school budget
by 6 or 7%. And
it has
involved 80 people losing their jobs,
a school closing,
all sorts of really, really, really hard decisions.
And so I really want us to take that same
energy that we
looked at the school budget with and look at the police budget
request to increase by 6.5% with that same energy.
And I want us to think about why each of the line
items in this police budget is more necessary to the
safety of our community and more important to us and
all of our neighbors than the people who are teaching our children,
and who are feeding our children, and who are doing all the important work in our
schools. And I think that I heard
some really great things that are going on in the police department budget,
like the SoPo Unite program, like the behavioral health liaisons,
that should be funded and that do meet that criteria, but there are other things in
the budget that do not meet that criteria, and sort of the lowest hanging fruit
of all is this Flock contract. And
Flock's business model is to create a nationwide network of
cameras that surveils all of us anywhere we go and can be
searched by any police department anywhere.
I have not heard from anyone, from the police chief,
from the city manager, from the council, what safeguards we have in
place to stop that from happening when that is the entire
reason that Flock exists.
It's not clear that anyone here
knows what Flock is doing with our data.
And no matter what safeguards we put in place,
Flock will always find loopholes to exploit to
ensure that it can do what it was created to do, which is
create a nationwide surveillance network that it can sell
for profit.
I think other folks have already mentioned that there's examples,
for example, in California, which has a strong law against sharing
ALPR data outside of the state or with federal officials.
There's been numerous examples-
30 seconds
... of Flock nonetheless doing that without the permission of police departments
and in violation of state law.
And I just have no confidence that they're not going to do that here
no matter what we do.
So I think we should not spend any more money on Flock
until we know that it is keeping us safe and not putting us at
risk. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Councilor Steph Steinbrink, Cottage Road.
I commend and admire and will try not simply to
echo the speakers who come before me.
Someone referred to this as a marathon meeting.
I do not want to do more than my three minutes to contribute to that.
And I think we would be happy either to have you just deny the
54 grand that's to be designated to
Flock or to say, "Well, we'll table that, and we'll have a community-wide
discussion about this where everybody can talk," and we can really
air the concerns here.
Fine either way with that, just so you know what I think we're after.
We didn't get together, so I'm not sure what my colleagues are about
here.
So these ALPR cameras,
especially these Flock cameras, they're in about 5,000
communities. There are about 80,000 of them in the United States
alone.
They scan 20 billion license plates
in a month.
So we're talking about a big enterprise here, and we
have, as you've heard, kind of flimsy
guarantees about how all that data is going to be used.
But we do know this, so they call their present cameras Sparrow and
Falcon, but they've got one called Condor that's on the way.
And Condor will be able to read people's faces as they pass.
The technology now already has a thing
called vehicle
fingerprint capability, and that means that it isn't just
capturing your license plate, it's also capturing the things that make
your car unique among all the automobiles on the American
highways. That means any dent in your car, any stickers on your
car, any kinds of
racks or canoes or whatever you have on your car, all that gets recorded, too.
So this isn't just happenstancial.
I want to say, I come from a generation where my relationship with the police
was at best, and I think
my friends' relationship, troubled.
And it's taken me a long time, and it's taken me living in this
community to have some sense about the kind of
coordination and collaboration and even admiration that I can feel
for the police department. So this is nothing about
them that I particularly question, but I do think
the wisdom of undertaking this kind of program,
especially-
30 seconds
... with its inherent dangers,
especially in the political
atmosphere that we live in now, all of this just seems to me
to be
... clearly mistaken, and I would urge you not to support this
part of what the police department is asking
for. Thank you.
Thank you. Sorry.
Hey, everybody. Sam Anderson. I live on Dawson Street over by Cash
Corner.
I don't have anything prepared. I have a three-month-year-old baby at home, and I
work a lot, so time is precious. And echoing that,
won't echo many of the other things that my colleagues here have said, all of
which I agree with regarding this program.
Like I said, I live on Dawson Street.
I work
between Darling Ave near the mall, and then on
Bradley Drive in Westbrook. So on an average weekday, I'm
clocked by these cameras 10 times plus.
And the thing I want to highlight,
outside of all the moral concerns with the company and
surveillance state...
is device security.
These cameras have been proven to have serious security
exploits that Flock has repeatedly lied about and denied.
And basically, anybody with some pretty basic computer
skills and readily accessible equipment can access
these cameras
without passwords, without security.
And some of these cameras can capture full motion video,
audio. I could borrow the stuff at work to do it tomorrow.
I won't, because that's illegal. But- ...
I think that that's a serious concern on top of all this other stuff.
And I think that in addition to ending this
program and removing all of the cameras, I think we should have legal protection
against things like this being set up in our community in the future. Thank you.
Thank you very much. Is there anyone else with a comment about the
police budget?
Thank you. Oh, you got two folks.
Well,
Jeff spoke, so I have to speak also.
No, you don't.
Council.
Good one, Richie.
Don Pine, Beach Street. I do not have prepared
remarks. I've just been listening to people.
I'm an old software guy, and I thought I retired, but a lot of
the software work has followed me.
And so a part of me just says, "Look, this is a technology
that
we'll be contending with from now on." The artificial
intelligence capabilities of camera
recognition, computer recognition are here to stay.
That's part of me.
I think one of the things that really upset me
in hearing people's opinions here,
was that even when laws are passed,
this company, Flock, violates the law anyway.
That even when communities speak and states speak and say,
"Here's the boundary. You cannot use this technology
to go over this line. Stay on this side of the line, okay.
But go over the line, that's illegal." Apparently,
Flock has been violating those laws.
That's deeply troubling. So what I would like to say
to the city when I take all these
different
thoughts and dimensions that run through this and think of them
together,
this is an issue that this city must understand.
We need to understand this. We
take issues like sea level rise. I don't know, is Julie
Rosenbach still here? There she is.
She knows about sea level rise because
she's had to. We take issues like the extreme storms that have
come. Do you guys know what direction they come from when they wipe out
Willard Beach? They come from the southeast. We know that now.
That's an issue that we as a community have had to
come to understand.
My neighbors have convinced me there's a serious problem here and a
serious issue with this new technology that, again,
based on my background as a software guy,
we know this technology's coming.
There are obvious legal problems, illegal search-
30 seconds
... and seizure,
the need for warrants. There are obvious national,
state legal issues here. So,
the only thing I really want to say here
is just like the sea level rise, just like the storms,
just like the budget shortfalls,
this is an issue that this city is going to have to come to
understand. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
I thought there was one more person. Yes. Thank you.
Hi, everyone. My name is Julia.
If I sound out of breath, it's because I am four months pregnant, and I am.
I moved to South Portland two years ago, and I actually am an
employee of Flock. They did not ask me to come here. I came here on my own accord.
I'm here because I'm local, and I care about this community being safe,
and I also once had a lot of questions and
misinformation.
I want to start with the fact that Flock has helped solve over one million crimes,
and that the cost of crime per household in South Portland, according to
crimegrade.org, is over $700 a
year per household. This was from 2025.
I understand that you want facts, and I would like them, too, so I'm
going to address some common myths that circulate around Flock.
Flock license plate readers do not track people.
They do not know your name, they do not know where you live, and they do not follow
you aroundFloc software has built-in safety guards
that work to enable proper usage. For example, all
searches in Floc must be tied to an offense type.
There are no
random searches.
We are not owned by Palantir, nor does he have access to our
data. All of our searches in the system are
audited and tracked. Certain searches are blocked in states where bans and
policies ban sensitive material like abortion and immigration.
We have tools in place to check to see if atypical usage is
happening,
like our audit assistance tool that flags behavior that we think warrants a
closer look. This enables your police chief or Floc
admin to monitor the usage more often.
I also want to call out that Floc does not have a contract with ICE or DHS.
They do not have backdoor access to Floc.
Your police team, and I'm going to work with them personally on
this, can have a transparency portal that is available to the
public.
This portal will show how Floc is used, its usage
metrics,
and access details like who your police are sharing data with, if
anyone.
I would also like to call out that there is no auto-sharing in Floc.
There is no national or federal auto-sharing.
If your police department chooses to share data with another
department or would like to have another department's data shared with them, it
has to be a two-way agreement.
This is also something that could be shown on the transparency portal.
30 seconds.
I would also like to say that South Portland Police own 100% of the data collected
here. Floc does not own any data, does not have access to data unless you
grant it to it,
and we have never sold or shared your data with anyone.
The agencies have complete control.
Finally, I'd like to say that Floc products actually reduce bias in
policing with objective evidence.
I think it's fair to ask questions, and I continue to.
Time.
I continue to encourage you to. I'm here, and your police chief are here to answer
questions you have. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, who are you? You don't work for the government.
No, I don't work for the government.
Yeah. What's your name?
Sorry, my name's-
Wait. Guys.
Whoa.
She said-
We all have to do that, right? We all have to.
She didn't say what her name was.
Julia, did you say your last name?
No, my last name is Ferreri.
Well, you can talk to me.
Sorry.
So I'm sorry, I thought I didn't hear your last name.
I did hear your first name, Julia.
Julia Ferreri.
Ferreri. Nobody else had spelled their name, so we'll take it just like we hear it.
And-
I'll spell my last name.
Fine.
You're Sam Anders? No, you're not.
So, I-
We're all good.
Julia, I think you're finished your comment. Thank you very much.
You're Willis.
DeLatt. D-L-A-T.
All right, everybody, now we know who everybody's name is, and if there is
any doubt, we can watch it on our video, but I think we've been
keeping track. I have anyway.
Thank you everyone. Is there anyone else who has a comment about the police
budget? And remember, they did talk more than just about the Floc
cameras, so if there is anything related to the police budget.
Okay, it doesn't look like that. So we're going to close public comment,
and truly appreciate all of the comments. Thank you.
And we now have a little council discussion.
Oh, we do have questions that the city manager has answers to, and I have a
feeling that we also will have questions that might require a little
bit more time to try to get some answers to, but maybe not.
Well, I only have two questions that I had, so I don't know.
But the first one was why did the council know about this?
Why wasn't there any announcement?
So this, in October of 2024, on October 8th,
the city council, during a publicly noticed meeting with agenda materials publicly
available, accepted a JAG grant to purchase specifically Floc
cameras. So it was very clear in the agenda materials. It wasn't a secret.
It wasn't hidden. This isn't a grant the PD got without anyone's
knowledge. It was public, transparent.
The Sanford decision was made a year later, so it doesn't quite line up with when
the council accepted the grant versus September of 2025, when
Sanford had their debate and discussion. So there's a year gap there.
So those times don't really add up.
I don't know if other communities announce when they're putting cameras up.
If we didn't and others did, then maybe that's something we fell
short on. But anyway, there was a public process.
The safeguards that are in place, it sounds like maybe the council will put this
into the workshop
for further discussion on the 12th.
I think that would be great, and I hope everyone shows up for that that did
tonight, maybe even more so that we can have a fuller conversation because it's
important to understand all the risks
with Floc. I've looked into it quite a bit because a lot of concern has been
brought up.
There's some things that I think are worth talking about, worth the public
understanding, and making sure the council
understands it as well and makes decisions based on the facts
of the matter and can that way determine whether or not the money should
be included in the budget or not. So I think we're at that
time. We can talk more, but generally, the safeguards include state law, city
policy, access logs, the fact that we haven't
enabled sharing with ICE, and our policy
says that we won't, for example,
as well are some of the safeguards.
But they're good questions, and I think it does warrant a fuller discussion.
Okay, and I have, I think, one more question.
Mr. Parsons asked if he could send research that he's done to the
council. Anyone can email the council at any time.
So that is a
yesUm,
okay.
Misha.
I mean, Councilor Pride. Sorry.
No, it's all right. It's getting late.
One thing I didn't say before is I do want to point out all the staff who
are still here, and I thank you, and I hope that the residents
understand. It's 10:25.
Do any of you go into work at 10:25, after working a full
day of work?
Probably not many,
so thank you, staff, for still being here.
I'm sure some people do, but it's not very common.
Anyway, thank you, staff, for still being here.
I will just make two requests for the parking lot.
One would be the Flock cameras.
And I ask that along with whatever
information
you and the chief can provide, Mr. City Manager, that we
also get an analysis of the contract with Flock from our corporation
counsel to give us a better idea of,
legally, what they can and can't
do with our data. So that, and then the
second thing I'd like to put on the
parking lot is the SoCo United position-
Here's the mic
... for funding.
Where'd funding come from?
It would be taxes.
Okay.
Unless we find something else in the meantime. But for now, it's taxes.
Madam Mayor?
Yes.
I'd also request that if Julia is available that night,
because she is working with the police department, if you wouldn't mind coming back
for the follow-up discussion.
Sure. When is that?
Do we have a date?
May 12th.
I would like to request that if that is part...
We heard from
this person named Julia as a
making public comment, but if this is actually
someone who is a consultant with the police department, shouldn't we get that
information?
I'm not aware.
Is this a consultant for the department?
I'm not-
Can I speak a little more on what my position is, just to clarify?
Well, actually, Chief, I'd like to hear from you, thank you.
Is Julia working with you?
She will be.
Dan Hearn, police chief.
I met Julia as I walked in the door. She said, "Hi, Chief.
I'm Julia." I said, "Julia, how are you?" "I work with Flock." Great.
Great to see you. She took it upon herself to be here.
She's a resident,
and I applaud her for that. She is working with us,
as I learned when we had our conversation downstairs.
We've had a bunch of different people.
I'm going to stop there, because I could talk for-
All right. So just-
... four hours
... all I'm asking is-
I will have people-
Julia is not known to you as the person who sells you Flock.
You've already established that.
She's-
Correct
... a resident who sells for them.
We worked with someone else when we purchased these cameras.
Okay.
A different representative from Flock, but she represents Flock.
All right. So I think we've got that, see.
Yeah, I mean, she wouldn't be part of our presentation.
She'd be here if council has questions, but we'd let her know.
Right. I think the fact that she had said, "Well, I'll be working with the police
department"-
And she will be
... sort of brought that question into the room. In what capacity? Thank you.
I just want to say that
it's a bipartisan contentious
topic. And because
I did get a copy of the contract, and
this is going to be brought up in Congress on April
20th, because there is a data broker
loophole which allows access to data without a warrant.
And that our contract has retention period of 30 days when
the state of Maine has just 21. But I found a
very disturbing
paragraph that said, "Flock,
subject to and during the retention period, Flock may
access, use, preserve, and/or disclose the
footage to law enforcement authorities, government
officials, and/or third parties if legally
required to do so, if Flock has a
good faith belief that such access, use,
preservation, or disclosure is reasonably
necessary to comply with legal process, enforce the
agreement, or detect or prevent, otherwise
address security, privacy fraud, or
technical issues or emergency
situations." And this present government
has used emergency situations to take away rights.
And right now, the way this operates
without access to data and a warrant-
My point of order
... is a violation of the 14th Amendment.
So that's why it's going to Congress-
So-
... on April 20th.
All right. So I think-
Don't worry about it.
You'll have more information.
You'll have your chance to respond during the parking lot.Thank you.
Because that-
No, no.
That's okay
... I'm sorry, but that 5.3 in the contract, there's
two attorneys here. This is about legal process.
Yes, and I trust both of you.
All right. Hey, everybody. Stop speaking.
April 20th, there'll be more information.
Councilor Colvin, please stop speaking. Here's the deal.
We have put this into the parking lot.
When we come back to that, we'll have more information.
We'll have a council discussion. I would welcome anyone who made
public comment now who wants to come back, to come back and
do so.
And that's how we're going to do it, okay? Because that's the process.
So now, if we have closed the
workshop on our police department, we're going to move to fire.
It's 10:30. We're going to get this thing to wherever
we can get it by 11:00, and then we might have to decide to move some
stuff around
Library's next. Thank you, everybody.
All right. So for fire budget...
Next, we're going to see Chief Solberg.
Right there.
He's right there.
Right in front of me.
Perfect.
How are you right here?
So the fire budget is up
$507,000, a 6.8% increase.
Annual cost to the median residential taxpayer is
$334.26.
There was a request, as there has been in previous years, for four new firefighter
positions in order to live within the budget guidance.
That was not funded. This does include the
estimated wage increases and overtime impact for the new collective
bargaining agreement, the two of them we have in the department, at a cost of just
under $520,000. There's some other things that
I'm going to skip for time's sake, but there is one item in the parking lot here,
a savings of $13,817. So we're heading in the right
direction twice now with some things.
There's a duplicate carryover that we can eliminate from this budget.
So we would ask that that be put into the parking lot.
There are four capital budget requests that we were able to fund this year, all
four, a new fire engine, an outfitting of ambulance number
42, a new command vehicle, and a remount of ambulance number
44. I'll turn it over to the chief for further
discussion.
Yeah.
And I'm sorry, Chief, that I tried to throw you off and said we were on the
library. We are not.
No worries. Bill Solberg, I'm your fire chief.
I'm not going to present, Scott. I'm just going to wing it.
Okay.
Yeah.
It's late enough. Yeah, as Scott mentioned, our biggest cost driver is of course
our most important one, which is our people.
I'm very proud to say that we're in the final stages of negotiating successive
agreements with both of those unions prior to their expiration.
And so that should be finalized very quickly.
Other than that, as you go through our budget, you'll see fluctuations up and down
like you normally do with us. We try to look at every account every year and
make realistic projections as to what we're going to spend.
Some of the bigger ones you'll see is a really substantial reduction
in the public safety supplies. That was the foam project that we
funded this year. That's complete now, so that's back to sort of
normal. You'll see some increases in maintenance costs for our fire trucks.
We know we have two projects that we have to do this year to open it up a little
bit. Our capital is really just our plan going forward.
We're trying to fund a new fire engine this year for purchase.
We don't expect it for a couple of years.
And to put some context, we're about to take delivery of a truck this month that we
ordered basically three years ago.
And so we're just trying to get ahead of the purchasing curve on that.
Again, we've been remounting ambulances at a significant reduction in
cost versus new. We would like to do another one of those this year, and then the
other items are really just sort of housekeeping things that we would do
typically in any other year.
And other than that, like I said, it's pretty much a maintenance budget.
We have been asking for additional people over the past few years.
We do expect the need to add an additional ambulance.
I've said this before in other budget sessions.
Two years ago I said three to five years. I'm sticking by that.
So at some point,
we really do have to discuss this in perhaps a workshop so that you guys fully
understand what staff is doing day in and day out and what staff
is not able to do day in and day out, just due to our backlog.
But generally speaking, FY27 is pretty straightforward,
and I'll take questions.
Councilors, do you have questions for the chief?
I have a question.
Councilor Walker, thank you.
Can you speak a little bit about what is represented in contracted services?
A number of things in contracted services.
One of the bigger ones for us is our medical billing.
So for all of our ambulance calls, we bill for service for
those, and we use a contractor for that.
They get a portion of what we
collect, and so their fee goes up as
we collect more money. The other thing that's really important in contracted
services are maintenance agreements for all of our cardiac
monitors and stretchers. And so,
a cardiac monitor nowadays is between $60,000 and
$70,000. And so to have them under a maintenance contract,
if something goes bad with them, we're not eating the cost of a
new monitor because it
falls on the floor or whatever might happen to it.
That's another big one in contracted services.
Thank you. And can I ask one more question?
Yes, please.
Why the decrease in protective gear?
To make budget.
Oh, okay. Is
there more you want to say about that?
So we're pretty proud of the fact
that we give everybody two sets of turnout gear here.
And most departments strive for that. We've been able to do it.
The reduction there is in call company gear, so we have fewer call company
members. We do replace their gear on the same 10-year cycle that we do everybody
else. But to shave a little bit off this year to get to our
number, we reduced that.
Thank you.
Any other questions, councilors?
All right. Do we have public comment on the fire
department budget?
Charlie Teenie, Pleasantdale. Earlier this evening, the
petroleum handling came up. They're not paying their fair share.
I was just curious if they have special requirements for the
fire department and if they have ever made any
contributions to our fire budget. Thank you.
Thank you for that question.
Anyone else, public comment on the fire budget?
I don't see any. That is closed. Can you please answer that question?
Chief,
I'm not aware of any contributions that the tank companies make to
the fire budget. I know in the past maybe they've done some training or-
Years ago, they funded a foam fire truck in
1990... I'm going to date myself. '91,
probably, '92.
I'm sorry. In '91 or '92, I think they funded a fire truck.
They have done training in the past, so they've
sponsored us to go to tank firefighting school.
It's not consistent every year, but once in a while, they do fund that.
Citgo is one of the companies that has a
grant program that's pretty easy to get, so they've funded some
equipment for us the last couple of years.
But that will come to you during the regular
action items, as typical. I think we've got it three years in a row.
It's maybe a couple of thousand dollars each time.
Mm-hmm.
Not much.
Okay. I don't think there are any other questions.
Councilors, did you have more to say?
Add, subtract, any changes on the fire budget?
All right. Well, then I think that part of the workshop is done.
Councilor Matthews, I had said that we would go to 11 and then,
or just before 11, and call it done and figure out what we want to do with the
remaining items.
I apologize. I need to-
Yeah.
All right. Now we have the library.
Well, before that, we still have the dispatch budget.
Just want to make sure so-
Oh, I'm sorry. You're right
Yeah.
There's two different parts. Okay.
So, the dispatch is... It's kind of a shared,
obviously, service for police and fire.
But we're part of the Portland Regional
Dispatch, and so we pay into that. This is going up, based on our
agreement with them, the costs are going up $62,000, a
3.6% increase. It's just our contractual share.
Average impact is $88. And
both chiefs can speak to this, but Chief Selberg-
Yeah. I'll do it. Phil Selberg, fire chief again.
So PRCC, which handles our 911 dispatch, the
telecommunicators, the dispatchers, and PD and fire for a number of communities,
including us,
we pay into that collectively as part of an interlocal agreement.
One important thing that I will point out as well, because I think this gets lost a
little bit, is not only does it fund
those people in there, but it also funds infrastructures for the radio system.
We use it, Melissa uses it,
water resources going on, and the school department uses it.
So, the money that goes into this budget actually funds more than just those
people. It also funds that infrastructure that we all share as well.
I know there's some capital increases this year over there for
fiber optic stuff, and then obviously wages over there.
So that's what those increases are.
Okay. Questions?
I have a question.
Yes, two of our councilors have questions. Councilor Walker.
No, go ahead.
I saw your hand first.
Okay.
So what are the overall savings by using this model?
Would there be an instance where we actually find it cheaper to take this in-house?
My initial answer would be no.
Okay.
Rough numbers we looked at a couple of years ago, we would expect to
have to staff probably 12 full-time positions plus a
supervisor-
Okay
... to handle our call volume. So we'd be looking at,
I would guess, $5 to $6 million,
plus facilities and-
So it's considerable.
Yeah.
Considerable savings.
Yeah. This is rough numbers, so
we could do a deep dive if you guys really wanted us to, but the other
factor there is the radio infrastructure.
It's very
technical. And it's shared, and it was grant funded, and it's
pretty important for us to stay on it, so-
Okay... as it stands right now, it's probably a decent value how we're doing it.
Okay. Thank you.
Sorry, can I?
Yes, please.
Did you say it was just Portland and South Portland that were on this
collaboration, or what were the communities?
So they do 911 service for Cape Elizabeth,
South Portland, and Portland, and then the radio infrastructure
covers pretty much every municipal service for both
cities and school departments.
South Portland and Portland-
Mm-hmm
... when you say both cities?
Mm-hmm.
Okay. And then my other question
was
do you think that there is an opportunity, and I know this is not your
department, but for greater regional collaboration across
Cumberland County and continuing to add
communities to this to increase sort of
efficiencies?
There could be. It's difficult to get players
to come to a table like that. And so I'll just give you
an example. Right now, Scarborough is about to invest millions
of dollars in a radio system.
Yeah.
Okay. Thank you. And I feel like I'm going to get struck
down by something, but you said the school department uses
this as well?
They do.
Okay.
I yield my time.
All right.
Any other questions, councilors, on dispatch?
Any public comment on dispatch?
I don't see any public comment. It's closed.
Councilors, are there any changes you were looking for to the
dispatch budget?
Nope.
No? Okay.
All right.
Let's do the library
and figure out how to make it earlier.
Library is up 57,000, a 6.2% increase.
Average cost to the median residential taxpayer, $70.34.
The couple of highlights here is there's increase in the books budget line due to
increased demand for both physical and digital collections,
and there's also an increase in the minor equipment line to replace public
work tables.
Hand out here. Here's yours.
Turn it over to our director, Kevin Davis.
Thank you, Scott. Kevin Davis, library director.
I just handed out a memo that I had shared with Scott earlier in the week.
Just a little example of return on investment for public libraries.
It doesn't really pertain to tonight, but just thought it would be good information
for you guys to have.
There are only two significant requests
from the department in this year's budget, and that's the $5,000 increase to
our materials budget,
and then $6,000 in the minor equipment, which would be for replacing
furniture. A lot of the public-facing furniture in
the building is original to
1966,
and it's showing it.
So, happy to answer any questions you might have about our services,
or these requests, or anything.
Councilors, questions? Councilor Scott.
I just noticed, unless I missed it, I don't think there's
a CIP library request, or is it in
a different portion?
Yeah. The bridge is under a facilities budget.
Okay.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Yeah, we have very few things within the library that raise to the
level of the CIP budget.
Oh.
So Don's the lucky one.
Any other questions?
Sorry, I'm distracted by your memo.
Any other questions on this side? All right.
Public comment on our library budget.
Anyone?
All right. We will shut public comment on our library budget.
Councilors, are there any changes you'd like to see?
Any movement?
Councilor Scott.
I did just want to comment that $70 per person average
across the city for the services that the library provide is an
incredibly affordable and wonderful service, and I
thank Kevin and all the people who support our library.
So,
thank you.
Okay. Most excellent.
That was a nice thing to say.
All right. Well, then we will call the library part of the
workshop finished. All right, councilors,
it's 10:45. We have staff that has
valiantly stayed here for a very long time
tonight. Julie's just right about to go, and
she's holding up that she's going to take five minutes.
I just feel badly-
It's three minutes
... three minutes even. Sustainability, public works,
facilities, parks, rec, these are important departments.
They all are important departments, and yet it is what it is.
So Julie, I guess if you're ready to come on up and dazzle us, please
do.
I'll skip the intro and just let people read the screen. How about that?
Thank you.
You want me to pass them along?
Yes. I don't know how to-
I can do that.
Okay.
I can do it all.
Thank you, guys, so much. This is...
Okay. Julie Rosenbach, sustainability director.
I just have a couple of points to make.
The first one is that implementing One Climate Future is one of the
eight city council goals, so it's fairly
important in terms of the work that we're trying to get done.
I'm not going to go through my programming, because in
January or so I emailed the council
our One Climate Future five-year progress report, and that had a tremendous
amount of detail in it. Every year, I usually beforehand
give the council, for what it's worth,
what we're planning on working on in FY27 for the
budget that I'm asking for.
But I forgot to put it earlier, so I'm just giving it
to you. For what it's worth, these are things we're going to be working on.
I want to highlight that everything that we're working on, we do our best
to minimize our operating costs year over year.
And so far in 2026, we've been awarded over
$250,000 in grants, and we have several
more grants out there that are pending that we're waiting to hear back from.
However, there are some parts of our programming that are not eligible for grant
funds. So I'm asking for, in particular,
$9,000 to fill the gaps in our grant funding
for the programming for our home energy program.
So, last point, given the stresses people are feeling
and the rising cost of energy,
and almost everything else, this program builds on our previous Electrify
Everything program. And the purpose is that it's going to help low
and moderate income folks,
fixed income folks who want to age in place,
help them weatherize their homes and understand their energy
systems and their costs, and how they can make energy-efficient upgrades
and finance those upgrades. And so, that is my budget
presentation.
Well done.
Thank you very much. Councilors, questions? Councilor West.
There's a CIP request submitted with your budget.
That would be a total of $120,000 for a bike
share program. Is that for real? You're going to bring the bike share program back
again?
No, it's across the tab.
Oh.
It's across the tab.
Oh, sorry.
Yeah.
I had to submit that before the council workshop.
Okay.
So,
further questions, councilors?
No, I don't see any. Public comment on the
sustainability budget?
This page.
Do we have public comment on the sustainability budget?
All right, does not look like we do. That is closed.
Councilors, is there anything you'd like to shift around in the sustainability
budget?
There's nothing I want to shift around, but I just want to highlight, because I
know that in tight budget years, this department is often kind of
seen in the community as low-hanging fruit of why we need it.
But I'm not a math person, so if someone is a math person and wants to give me the
percentage, that would be great. But looks like the budget for last
year was $273,942, and you said you brought in
$250,000 in grants?
That's amazing. So, you funded almost your entire department through grants.
So, I just wanted to highlight that.
Yes. Good highlight there.
I know everything.
Councilor Scott.
I don't have anything to add or subtract, but I will say that in
terms of the return on investment, which was the title of the library's memo
and not the sustainability's memo,
I think that if there was an analysis done on the return on this investment, not to
mention the grant funding, this would have a
massive return across our community in terms of savings, and
it goes back to Amory Lovins'
megawatts. So, thank you, Julie, and all your work, and I very much
support this budget and all the work that we're doing here. So, thank you.
It is not a low-hanging fruit for me.
Nope.
I know that's not what you were saying.
Yeah. Good to hear. Thank you. Any other councilors?
All right. Well, I think we are finished with the sustainability part of
the workshop. Public works.
So, we brought our public works director back from maternity
leave. I think she said she'd prefer to be here.
I don't know if that's still the case or-
I don't know. Yes.
Yeah?
A toddler and a three-week-old at home. Yeah.
Yeah.
You can be sleepless anywhere, and-
I know. My other half isn't liking tonight, but it's okay.
I can figure it out.
Melissa Hutchins, public works director.
Scott, are you going over or you just want me to be quick?
Go right ahead.
Quick?
I'm cutting on the time, so.
I'm just going to do really quick because I know Carl really wants to go tonight.
Our biggest
increase is overtime, but that's because of union wages that have
been negotiated. Equipment rental's up quite a
bit, but that's our winter plowing contractors.
Can you explain that real quick, the on-call?
I think that's important for the council understanding.
So, every time that we put this out to bid, every three years,
we get pretty much one vendor. It's really tough to get contractors
out there,
because they're tied up at other municipalities.
For example, Scarborough has Dearborn.
We had Keenan and Gorham Sand,
and then other municipalities have other contractors.
So there's not much out there for plow
contractors. Basically, how it works is if we have a smaller
storm, we do that in-house. That's why you'll see some times where people say it
takes a little bit longer
or we haven't been around to plow their road.
It's because we're trying to fill up those nine spots with our drivers.
So we're struggling, so there's routes that don't get touched until the guys
finish their dedicated route, then they work into the other
routes. And we do that to cut costs, because we obviously couldn't
fund contractors every single storm.
So we try to use what we have wisely and use it for
larger storms.
And what we do is we have to give them a two-hour call, so two-hour heads up.
So we call them in advance, they come in within two hours, and then they start
plowing.
So there's a rate per hour for the loaders, which is pretty much about
$200 an hour, $215 an hour, and then the grader
is $300 an hour. So you pay them per hour, and that includes their
equipment, the fuel, the labor, everything.
And then we also pay winter storage.
So for every piece of equipment that we retain by them, we have to pay a monthly
storage to make sure that we're guaranteed the equipment.
If not, then the equipment then moves, and then they have to haul the equipment
back in.
So during the storm, we wouldn't have the equipment readily available.
So we're not getting much bidders on it.
It is out there right now for bid, so
hopefully we'll get more people interested, but we'll see.
So that's the increase there.
Construction supplies increase is just because the salt per ton is
very expensive. We do use salt on all our main roads, and then we
also mix in 30% salt with our sand.
Our largest
increase is solid waste and recycling.
That is the EcoMain fees have gone up, Casella curbside collection has gone
up. A lot more interest in our household hazardous waste event,
so that has quite a bit more participants and higher volume, which is
great. The Garbage to Garden increased,
and then also contamination fees, tipping fees through EcoMain has
increased.
And then that is it for our operating.
And as for capital, we are requesting two
single-axle trucks, and those are plow trucks.
Those are replacing a 2002 and a 2009,
and that still leaves us with old fleet.
We still have other 2002s, 2007s,
four 2008s, 2011.
So we have a lot of aging fleet.
We asked for a compact excavator, and that's just we don't have one now, and that
saves on us renting the equipment.
It's also more efficient to remove sidewalks.
A skid steer, that is for pretty much everything in the summer, and
that is a 2005 we're replacing.
We're looking at replacing the sign shop truck. That's currently a 2012.
And because we are in the urban compact, we oversee all of the
state roads. So all of the overhead wires, the span
wires-Signage, all of that is us, and we do not have
a truck capable of being able to do that.
Parks does have a bucket truck, but they use it quite often during
the season to maintain trees. So this would be outfitted with a
bucket, and that would allow us to replace spin wires, back plates
on traffic signals, clean the
video detection cameras for the actual signals.
It'll be outfitted with a puller to actually replace larger signs.
And then we also have on there a street opening truck.
That is funded by street opening permits.
That's currently replacing a 2014
car.
And then we have a local match for our Crockett's Corner design.
That is something that came out of the Safe Streets for All assessment.
Crockett's Corner is a high-crash location. It has a history of safety concerns.
It's a $30,000 match,
and then we get a federal grant for $270,000, and that is the complete
design. This also opens us up for the potential
grant for construction, which should be about a 10% local match.
And then the other item is our Broadway Pedestrian Improvements
project, and that is just for these
community development block grants, the $288,000 we're getting from
them. That project, we also have a million dollars worth of state grant
money, and then the local match that we have from the
2018 or 2019 bond, and that's it.
Do you want to talk quickly about street opening budget too, so we don't have two
different-
Yes. So street opening, this is just all of the
contractors out there, they have to take street opening permits from
us as well as excavator licenses, and all that money is put into its own fund and
there's one employee for that position
inside the public works department.
So all of those fees, we calculate every year on how many permits we've taken
the previous three years, and then we set the fee during the budget
process and that pays for it. So there is funding from
previous years that are only used for street openings because it's
its own program.
So that will fund the truck
solely out of the previous funding that we have.
Yeah, that should've been listed here. That's my fault.
Question?
Oh, sorry, Scott. I thought you were still saying something.
We're good.
Okay. Melissa, thank you. I think
you're getting really reckless when you start replacing
24-year-old vehicles.
Mm-hmm.
Counselors, questions?
Councilor Walker.
I'm trying to keep my questions kind of short.
So the increases in traffic lights and streetlights and sidewalk
maintenance,
what are the drivers in those increases?
And then also, do we own the streetlights or does CMP own the streetlights?
So we own the streetlights. We purchased them during the LED conversion
process-
Okay
... so now we manage it. This is just for the cost of the electricity.
Oh.
Those have increased. Ellen can touch more because I get the prices from her on
those.
Okay.
As far as sidewalk, there is no increase.
Our budget is still the same from last year.
Oh, okay. Sorry.
It's fine.
Thank you.
Welcome.
Other counselors with questions?
Just one quick one.
Yes.
Do we lose, just hypothetically, if we weren't to do the Broadway
corridor, if we weren't to approve that or whatever,
you said there's a matching grant to that one?
The Broadway ped one or the Crockett's Corner?
Both.
So Broadway ped is already funded by the bond.
Okay.
So the local match is money that the voters already approved-
Okay. That's what I thought
... back in 2019.
Okay.
So that money's allocated.
Yep.
We just didn't have enough to complete the project because it's been-
Got it... what, seven years now, the project's skyrocket.
Right.
So I got a grant from the state, which is a million dollars, so they're going to
cover that, and then Community Block Grant is 288,000
grant. That's going to cover the difference from our recent cost estimate, and that
is going to bid this year. So-
Okay. Yeah, that's fine.
Yeah.
I just missed the part where you said that
we had got the extra money.
Correct. We have all the money, as of right now, if the budget passes and
we get the Community Block Grant.
Right. All right.
Other counselors, questions?
Public comment on the public works budget?
I don't see anyone. We'll close that.
Counselors, any ideas for pushing things around,
moving things, parking lot items? Nope.
Nope, nope, nope. Thank you, Melissa.
Then we're going to close this part of the workshop.
Please go home.
All right. You guys-
Is she talking to us?
As we-
No.
Yeah, unfortunately not.
Counselors, I think
we should try to get the last two done.
So we're going to start the facilities part of the workshop. Thank you.
Come on down.
Good evening, counselors,
Mayor Scott. Thank you.
So I'm
just looking at the
line item summary.
Don Hop, Skip Hopkins, facilities director.
Thank you.
Apologize. Almost forgot my name there for a minute.
Oh.
You don't have to do every line, just give-
Yeah
... the highlights.
Yeah.
Yes. Yeah, highlights. So,
hourly
wages have gone up about 23,600.
It's about a 3.8% increase. That's due to COLAs primarily,
pretty much everything else. You'll see our overtime
has gone up about $10,000 for this new
budget. Overtime's kind of weird.
Anybody that works 37 and a half hours
in our department, there's 12 of us or
soIf somebody works up to the 40
hours, that gets coded as an overtime expense, even though it's not time and a
half. It's a single hour,
but it gets pushed down into OT. I'm not really sure why
finance is like that, but that's primarily what
a lot of the OT is. We don't get a lot of overtime.
Although we did just this year bring on
someone to take on-call duties when Ron, our
supervisor, is on vacation, holidays, away for the week.
We have somebody else that's on call to be able to come in and support the city
24/7.
So that's some overtime for that person.
We give them a little stipend for that week as well.
So that's why that overtime budget has gone up.
If you go down through, the major increases would be
equipment maintenance. So equipment maintenance is predominantly preventative
maintenance. That's what we use that line for.
So we added some preventative maintenance to some
different areas this year.
There's about $10,000 to flush heat loops.
So a lot of these buildings have a closed loop in them where they run the heat.
In that loop, the water in it gets stagnant after
years. So basically, the city has never flushed any of these loops in
the buildings that we own. We've got new buildings like MSF and Cash
Corner that have these loops, and so I want to make sure that we're doing this now,
and it should be done every five years or so.
So we put that in as a five-year
preventative maintenance. There's also some other things that were never in here in
the preventive maintenance. There's a five-year sprinkler inspection.
Every five years, an internal inspection needs to be done with sprinkler systems,
so they drain the system. They run cameras down it to look at the
interior of the pipe, so on and so forth.
That's never been done in the city before either.
I want to make sure we're getting that into our new buildings, Cash Corner,
Municipal Service Facilities, and this building here needs it as
well. It's never been done here, but I'm sure the water in this
loop here looks pretty stagnant. So that's a
$10,000 increase there. You'll see there's a
$6,200 increase in the five-year sprinkler
inspections. That one's just from the Mahoney school.
So,
we also have some other five-years coming up.
So we're trying to get those on our preventative maintenance schedule
now so that we can get those things done and take care of business.
So that would be the,
excuse me, did I say 16? 18,700.
You'll see the biggest increase is in
contracted services. Contracted services is what I like
to call, and some people disagree with me, but what I call the emergency
line. So basically, if a boiler goes down in a building, an air handler,
an electrical issue, major electrical issue, basically these funds
in this line, we try to put it out to all those repairs in the
city.
This year, if you look,
we had budgeted 144. The reason I did that
was because we started putting so much stuff in the preventive maintenance.
In
a newer building, typically you start doing preventative maintenance, it cuts
back on your reactive maintenance.
So those emergencies don't happen because you're doing preventative work.
So I, over the last couple of years, have increased that preventative maintenance
line, such as we're doing a little bit this year as well.
And my theory was that the reactive maintenance would drop.
Well, I didn't take into consideration police station, fire station,
and some of these older buildings, City Hall.
The beginning of this fiscal year, I had six or seven
$10,000 jobs. I lost a boiler over at PD.
I lost a rooftop unit. We had a condensing coil go.
All those jobs were like $10,000. So it started eating up our
emergency budget line real quick.
So we went through
a lot of the money, so as you can see, my projection for this year,
we had budgeted 144. My projection was
173. That's closer to where we're going to be.
And then for this year, I bumped it up
to 185,000
due to, I expect the same thing to happen in some of these older buildings.
They're getting older. Things are starting to happen with the library, at the
branch library, the golf course buildings,
so on and so forth. Community center's doing pretty good.
You've given us a lot of capital to put back in that building.
So we're looking pretty good there, but that's a $41,000 increase in the
contracted services.
Another 10,000 in heating fuel.
Excuse me. All the buildings used to have
their own heating fuel line, and as we've been working year to year, we've been
bringing those into Facilities. So same with electricity.
Electricity's all in Facilities now.
We're trying to get all the heating gas and oil from other
buildings into the Facilities budget. So we added...
I don't remember what we added this year.
Got it written down here somewhere.
I think it was the planning building, the Hamlin building, and
the increase over at Mahoney as well.
Plus we did a 5% increase across the board for heating fuel
in the budget. So that's where you're seeing that number increase.
What else we got?
Down at the bottom, building improvements,
31,500. That building improvements, that's a line in
Facilities that we hadn't really used in the past,
but we're using it now to
try to plan ahead for some of those emergency things that happened,
such as heat pumps. You look at this building, we've got these split systems
all through the building. Same thing over at the Hamlin building.
One of these systems go down, they're getting old, they're getting over 10 years
old, 15 years old. So I put 30 grand in there for
those. They're about 15,000 a piece to replace a good size
heat pump unit.We've also put...
If I find my right page here, sorry.
I got a new compressor. There's actually a
facilities trailer in there as well.
Right now, we have three vehicles in the fleet.
We have a pickup truck, a small van, and an EV
vehicle.
When we go to do a job, such as city hall renovation, or we got a big job going
somewhere, we're doing an office or any type of work, we're trying to
go get supplies with a pickup truck that's only got a six-foot bed in it.
All the tools we have spread around the city, so we don't have a place just to
keep everything that we need in one place.
So we end up carting stuff back and forth, the buildings.
Wet vac, saws, all that stuff. So that trailer would kind of
house all the maintenance gear, ladders, saws, all the
equipment that we needed, so when we pulled up to a building, we wouldn't have to
chase around the rest of the city to go find that stuff.
As we take on more and more projects in-house, then we like to
have something like that. So that's
in the building improvements. Fluid pumps for
MSF. Fluid pumps are over at the municipal service facility.
Out in the garages, they have
all the fluids, all the oil, the lubricants, the grease,
the antifreeze, is all pumped through this big system
throughout the building. We have huge tanks that are out in this one room.
They have pumps on them. They pump that pressure up to anywhere from 1,000
to 4,000 PSI and push that fluid all through the building.
We lost one of those this year, one of the pumps.
I've got five pumps in there. So I've just planned on potentially
losing another one if they're all about the same vintage.
So, I've got some money in there for that.
That's pretty much it. Chipped paint at West End Fire.
I've been telling Chief I was going to fix that floor over there.
The red paint on the floor has been chipping up for years now.
And his crew tries to chip up as much as they can, but I'd
like to
try to get them some support over there and make that floor look pretty for them.
So once again.
And that's it on the budget. If you want me to jump right into capital or if you
want to ask questions on the budget first.
Councilors, do you have questions?
Okay. Thank you.
Councilor Casal.
Yes, Councilor Scott. Thank you.
Only because this is my area of expertise, not mowing specifically, but
what is the actual budget for mowing the solar field?
That
wouldn't be in my forte.
That's Parks and Rec.
That's the next department.
Parks and Rec.
Sorry. That's...
Okay.
It has increased mowing solar farm.
That's the next-
Finance office says that's 20,000.
20,000.
Where are you seeing that now?
It's on the bottom of the operating budgets.
Oh, yeah.
Oh. There's energy too that Skip does.
Oh, I apologize.
That didn't get-
I apologize.
Yeah.
Julie can speak to that. That's in the electricity budget.
I apologize. I didn't go through that.
Okay.
If that's what it costs-
Come on
... to mow...
Did
I answer the question? That's what it costs-
Yes
... to mow the landfill. The reason why it was
less last year is because we had a problem with contracting with
people, and so we couldn't get them to mow it.
And I'm sure you guys saw as you went by and heard from people that there was
stuff growing up through the panels.
This is the appropriate amount of how much it costs to mow
in between all of the panels and take care of the landfill.
And I just want to say that even though it seems like it's a lot, every
year we pay $500,000 to
$800,000 less in our electricity
costs. We don't have budget for that because we do have the solar.
It's 10,000 for next year based on the cost that we
paid this year.
Can I just ask a question?
So it's plus 10,000.
So-
I apologize.
Can I add? So you need to do this because these
things growing up affects the functioning of the panel?
Yeah.
Yes.
The weeds grow up in front of the panels, and then-
They're there in front of the panels
... we got to take care of some.
All right. It's not just an aesthetic. Got it.
And Councilors, on CIP you see all the items here recommended.
There's a lot that aren't, but the
things that I didn't recommend are things that we'd have to do if bonds don't pass
or we don't move forward with things.
So I just want to be clear, that's why-
Good
... those aren't funded.
And yeah, you want me to speak on that or you good?
Do-
If they have questions, maybe, yeah.
Questions?
Okay. Apparently not.
I have multiple CIP questions.
Oh, on the capital?
Well, yeah.
Capital, yeah.
So-
Yeah. Oh, yeah.
All right.
But he didn't talk about it yet.
I haven't talked about capital yet.
Okay.
I was asking if you'd like me to, or I'll take questions if you'd like.
Yeah, however you want.
However you want to do it.
It sounds like you better roll while you can.
Okay. I'm going to roll with it. So, if you look at the capital for the new
central fire police station, city hall facility, and Moore
library. So I put those numbers in there due to the fact that we
need to look at it. These buildings need to be done.
So these numbers represent what it would cost to renovate these
buildings where they are right now.
It would not accommodate our current programming needs.
It also would notInclude some of the parking needs, such as if we
renovated this building, City Hall, for instance, I've got $40
million in there. If we renovated this building, brought it up to
current building codes and standards, fire
NFPA standards, all the stretch codes, and everything that we wanted to
do, it would cost $40 million to redo this building.
This building would not accommodate all the city buildings, such
as Hamlin and some of the other programming and assessor's office.
It would be built to accommodate what it houses right now.
This is the numbers we got from
doing our studies on all the buildings around the city, and the
same with all of them. New central fire station, police station, city
hall, and a new library. Those are the prices that it would
cost if we renovate those buildings.
If the bonds don't pass and we don't do anything, if we're going
to renovate these buildings in place, that's what it would cost us
at today's price. There's no escalation on here.
There's also parking. Library would not accommodate parking over there
if we
built out the square footage that they need for the programming needs.
So it does not include any parking, such as parking garages or where
we might park these people. Same here at City Hall.
It would not accommodate the parking that we needed here because we'd have to take
some of the parking lot, and so basically,
these prices don't really look at the big picture.
And then you get a building that
doesn't meet our programming needs for today.
It would just meet them. So that's kind of a down and
dirty bottom line. So I put them in there just to give us a look at,
well, if we don't pass these bonds or don't do anything, these are the kind of
costs we're going to be looking at at today's dollars, not
5 years from now or 10 years from now. So they're just in there as placeholders.
I didn't expect that they were going to get funded this year, so I just wanted
everybody to know that.
We tried to explain it during the budget presentation last week.
That they're in here to show the cost. They're not in here as funded.
There's no associated debt service payment with these, so it's a little
bit of a misnomer to say that they're funded.
It's just a showing of, hey, if city bonds
don't pass, this is what new facilities would cost,
or new facilities, really renovating the facilities,
is probably a better term.
And then there's the associated, these costs here, which are all the things that
we'd have to also do as well if we don't get new
buildings. But there were some specifics broken out.
So-
So you're not really going with this list.
The top list here, the new city facilities, this top
line.
Right.
The council's not allocating 165 million
dollars
in the CIP.
But we probably shouldn't have listed it this way, but it's just-
Yeah. I think we just wanted to put it out there.
Kevin was concerned that we were pulling the library out of the
City Center project, and it was like, well,
this is what it would cost to renovate the library.
And then I said, "Well, if I'm going to do it for the library, I might as well do
it for all the buildings." So if these buildings don't get
rebuilt elsewhere or in a bond, then at some point we'd have to take
a look at thinking about these. So it really shouldn't be in this year.
Those could float out. We did a seven-year capital, so they should actually
be out in
past
years here.
So none of this list we-
None of those four right there. The rest of it is all capital outlay.
Not the 165.
The 165.
Not this top one right here. Whoops. Jesus, this won't let me do it.
The top one that says new city facilities, that's not really
something we're funding.
But the rest of the list is.
Everything else is funded.
Okay.
Those are not related to-
So I just-
Facilities truck, door access system.
Yeah.
Those are all things we need to fund.
Thank you, Scott. I just wanted to put them in there so that we can open some eyes.
So facilities truck right now, I do not have a vehicle for the city.
I drive my own personal truck all around to all the buildings, so on and so
forth. I used to have a EV, but then we
hired more staff, and now the staff uses the EV to get to buildings, since
we clean multiple buildings. A staff member may clean three or four
buildings, so our three fleet vehicles are being used all
during the day. So that leaves me without a vehicle.
I'd like not to keep using my personal vehicle for
city functions, so that's what that's all about.
The door access system.
Right now, all of our door locks in the city are housed
over in Portland, and
they haven't really been charging us for it for
a considerable amount of years, I believe.
And we've been told that as of July 1st, that
they will no longer support it or take care of it.
A Linux system that does all of our door locks.
It's the brains for the system. This 40 grand represents that, bringing that
system over to us, putting it in our IT, and putting all of
our door locks on the system. The good thing about this price
is it's a server, basically, and so all of our
existing door locks will work on this.
At some point, we'll probably bring the cameras over to the system as well.
That's an IT thing that we're talking about as well, since that's housed
elsewhere also. So,
that's the 40,000 for that. We really need to do it or we won't have any door locks
as of July 1st.
NOCO detectors, these are at the fire station
predominantly. Municipal service facility.
NO, nitric oxide, CO,
carbon monoxide
detectors in all the bays for the fire stations and municipal service
facilityThose detectors that check
for either a gas-fired engine or a diesel engine,
looking for the gas,
all of those detectors have a three-year
lifespan on them.
Municipal service is going on seven years now, so they're supposed to have been
replaced at three years. Also, over at Cash Corner, which is going
on five years now,
we've got some that are actually out of order over there right now.
So basically, I put this money in to be able to
replace all the filters and devices
in Cash Corner, West End, and municipal service
facilities where we have these vehicles.
So,
electric vehicle, that's
the least vehicle that we have. That's a buyout for it.
Car's only got a few thousand miles on it because we use it to just go around the
city. So 27,360 would actually
buy that lease out, and then we could continue to run that vehicle.
If not, we trade it back in sometime in July or
August, I believe.
South Portland Community Center entry roofs.
The roofs we've done, we redid the pool roof over there.
We redid all the roofs on top of the gymnasium and over the
administration areas. There's some smaller roofs going down a
corridor towards the pool from the lobby.
That roof was just a small section.
We never replaced that when we did the big roofs.
So those are leaking now. There's one section that actually has concrete on it, and
that's leaking, so that's money to replace those two sections of
roof, which would pretty much give us all completely new roofs over at
the community center at this point.
The Willard Beach shack is 30 grand.
That's
to building improvements, as well as the boardwalk that goes around it.
If you guys go down there, you'll notice there's a lot of rotten wood on there.
There's a lot of it stick up. It's a tripping hazard.
People have cut their feet on it. We have to go down and replace quite a
few boards every year. But it's time that it probably should be done
and done right.
The bridge rehab at the branch
library. So, Kevin had put in
$50,000 for a capital for that bridge.
And so facilities thought that we could go over and
we were going to paint it.
Basically, we were going to sandblast it and paint it and make it all look good
again. Well, we went over and started looking at it, and a lot of the
steel where it connects to the building has actually started to rot away.
It's thick steel, and it's starting to delaminate.
It almost looks like a piece of wood.
The rust on it is just coming off in layers where it mounts onto the building.
And then up underneath, where the
concrete and the decking is, it's corrugated deck,
galvanized. All that is starting to rot down through, and the
steel is rotting all the way along.
So both of those spans are in pretty sad shape.
So I've taken some of the $50,000 that
we had already approved with CIP to use to do structural
analysis on it. So I've got some
structural engineers looking at it to find out just what we need to do with that.
And I put $200,000 in there that I'm thinking it would
cover if we need to replace the steel on that building.
The South Portland Community,
SPCC pool air handling unit number two.
You guys have been generous, and I have two new rooftop units
going on the main building,
this month actually.
Coming right up, and so that's going to help.
We've also put a couple of new boilers in over there.
I've actually put three new boilers in with CIP funds
and some... I know I'm going long way, aren't I, guys?
All right, take us home.
So I see people looking at their watch.
We're going through the elevator next.
Maybe not every item.
All right, sorry.
Every known building item.
Then there's the elevator project. That would completely rebuild that elevator.
As Scott has said in the past, that elevator is way past its
life expectancy. We can't get parts for it now.
Basically, we need to rehab it. So that would redo the entire elevator, the cab,
the piston, all the rails, everything all the way down through.
So we'd have a brand-new elevator.
That's all I have.
Oh, come on. You got to have more.
No, I've got more, but Scott didn't approve.
Come on.
Scott didn't...
Said I can't talk about it.
Give me, give me haha.
Scott said I can't talk about any more stuff.
Ha ha ha. Funny.
Any counselors, questions on any of the projects or
the costs or
anything?
I have some questions on the un-
Councilor Walker.
And please, nobody, I'm not looking to make eye contact with anybody.
On some of the unfunded items, is it okay to ask
those questions now? I'd potentially like to move them to parking lot.
I guess you better.
All right.
Yeah.
Well, are you going to put them in the parking lot, or are you going to talk about
them?
I'd like to put them in the parking lot.
Ah.
There you go.
If
I was to be able to request one item that's not funded, would be the
replace sewer service main at the police station.
Okay, that's on my list. Police and fire are basically my questions that I
had-
Yeah, sure
... for that.
Go. Shoot away.
I can table my questions for our parking lot discussion.
Yes. That's what you should do.
Okay.
That's what I would do, yeah.
Just know when we get to asking to move things, I have a number of things I'm going
to move into the parking lot.
Facilities.
Yes.
Okay. Do we have any members of the public who want to talk about these
things? Oh, we have someone. Thank you.
And then-
I am Jack. I live on Everett Avenue.
Yeah.
I was here for the school board meeting.
Yes, you were.
But I stayed, and my six-year-old's going to ask, so I have to ask.
Is there any plan to redo the playground at Willard Beach?
Yes.
Thanks so much.
Next topic.
Coming up. Coming right up.
Can I just make a quick comment? Haley Moore at Delbert Street.
I have a small business that takes care of properties, so nothing like what you do.
The one thing that stuck out to me is an employee should not drive their own
vehicle for work, and I feel like that's something really small that makes a big
difference, and it seems like you do so much.
So I just wanted to comment on that. Thank you.
Thank you.
Anyone else would like to comment?
Oh, are you...
Oh.
All right, public comments closed on that one. Where are we?
Who are we? What has happened?
Okay. Can I move my things to the front now?
Yes. Quickly. Thank you.
All right.
So this is the list. I'll just go through it real quick.
Bathroom at Central Fire,
heat pumps for fire,
and replace the
sewer main at PD.
And
again, I'm not necessarily looking to do all of these, but I think that we should
have a conversation about them. And also, renovate bathrooms at
PD.
How would you fund that?
And funding source?
Property taxes and fund balance, because again, I don't
know if I necessarily want these, I want to have a larger discussion about them.
Yes.
And 11:30 is not the time.
Appreciated.
Okay.
You are a wise woman and councilor. Thank you.
All right.
There he is.
Was someone saying something here? All right.
Good video.
We finished Facilities. Come on up, Carl.
I think we should adjourn.
Oh.
Are you going to answer the question-
Carl was so worried, he was saying, "Should I even show up tonight?
Are they going to adjourn?"
Are you going to answer the questions from public comment or the questions-
I'm sorry, yeah. Questions from public comment.
So,
to answer your question, the Willard Beach playground, that's included in the Parks
and Rec budget.
Did you hear that?
So it's in this one, and it is recommended for funding.
I appreciate that.
Thank you.
All right, Carl, we remember you. Please say things.
Hi. Carl Coughlin, Director of Parks, Recreation, Waterfront, and Cemetery.
So originally, I had a presentation that was 17
slides.
I think it was three.
It is going to be three. I'm going to hit on three points.
I know one, Councilor Matthews sent an email about earlier today.
Another one, this nice young gentleman has waited the last five hours to
hear about the Willard Beach playground.
But really,
me and my deputy director, Anthony Johnson, are just here to answer your guys'
questions. I know because I'm going last, that means I'm Scott's favorite, and you
guys are likely to fund all my projects and not have any questions, so.
Is there a way that I can-
There should be a dongle there, unless the school took it with them.
Does it work?
Oh.
We didn't discuss that.
Okay, forget it. It's fine.
Yeah.
You can use anything you want. You can have-
Oh, man. Oh.
Now he's panicked.
I'm just going to read off my screen, and you guys are going to have to trust that
what I'm saying is truthful.
Don't help him.
Oh, no, it's okay.
It's okay. It's 11:30. I'm not messing with this.
All right. Thank you.
Absolutely. Anything for you folks.
So, the golf course, I know last week somebody brought up the golf course and
whether or not it was profitable and you know the...
It's all right now. We're good.
No, I'm fine.
So I just wanted to give you guys some information on the golf course.
The golf course is an enterprise fund, which means it is completely funded by user
fees rather than taxes.
It has generated over one million dollars in revenue the last four years.
2023 was about 270,000, and this year, year to date, we
brought in 186,000, but we're going to be tracking to bring in about
340,000 this fiscal year. So the golf course
has really, really, really
turned the corner from where it was 10 years ago.
The golf course does have a very healthy fund balance, and it has been funding its
own projects the last few years. The golf course parking
lot renovation, we've purchased a few mowers, we have a few items in
this year's CIP, and potentially a netting project this year or next year in
CIP that we can fund using the fund balance from the golf course.
And the golf course has hosted over 25,000
rounds of golf in 2025, and that's just only going
to increase.
One thing that you're going to see in my budget is that our hourly account is
increased by about $80,000, and that's due to us creating a full-time golf
course foreperson position. This position would work at the course
year-round and play an integral role in winter operations when they're
not working at the course.
Currently, we have two full-time employees at the course.
One has a split allocation that is 40% paid for
by Parks and 60% paid for by the golf course, and the other is completely
paid by the Parks budget. Since the golf course is in a position to be
self-sustaining, funding 100% of the foreperson
position utilizing user fees and still having the
40/60 split employee would allow us to maintain the current staffing
levels at the course and continue to provide a high level of service to the
community. And by shifting the financial burden from Parks
to the golf course for that position, the savings to the Parks operating budget
would allow us to add an additional full-time position to our budget at no
added expense. We're just taking that person and we're shifting it over to
our revenue-generating machine.
And the last thing I just really want to touch on is the
Willard Beach playground. As you folks can see, I have quite a
few CIP items that are recommended for funding, but this one
has a little bit of nuance to it.
So we're asking for $165,000 to replace the existing playground
that has far exceeded its useful life, needs to be removed this
spring or summer just due to safety concerns.The new playground would be
moved closer to the beach house and it'd be constructed with materials that are far
better suited for the environment than that playground that was installed 25 years
ago.
Maine DEP, in recent conversations, notified us that if a new playground were to
be installed, that we would need to build a dune system between the playground and
the water and manage it in perpetuity.
We estimate that cost to be about $30,000 to build the dunes, and
then we'd have to budget for $30,000 every year in
our operating budget just in case that dune would get washed out.
And then,
evaluating upgrading the playground was identified as a high priority in the
Willard Beach master plan.
That is
all I have for you folks. I could talk for another hour, but I
don't think anybody is in the mood.
So this is for parks, rec, waterfront, and golf course, all in one?
Yes.
Yeah.
All right.
My question is about the net for the golf balls that-
Right
... the neighborhood
or whatever, because the trees were cut and people are getting
cars dinged and windows broken.
So
it's my understanding, I'm following with you, okay?
Yeah.
So we get the emails with the condos are being pelted and a lot of
house damage. I know that the netting is in the '28
budget.
Yes.
What is the cost of that? So if I wanted to make a suggestion,
I knew what that cost was.
Just give me a guesstimate.
We think it's going to be about 90 to $100,000 just for,
Anthony, was that hole number five?
Yeah, hole number five along the Broadway would... It already has a net along it.
Right. I know that, yeah.
The house behind that, where we're looking to net that and-
The condos
... further woods are, we've got some trees down there, so that house would get
pelted by golf balls.
Yeah.
No, I know where the condos are.
Hole number five on Broadway, at the intersection.
That's what's in the '28?
No, that's where we got the quote from a year ago.
To have an additional net on that hole put
sort of midway on the fairway so that house wouldn't get hit.
Okay. Just tell me this, because it is late.
How much?
Is to protect those condos in the '28 budget?
Yes.
Thank you.
Okay.
That's all.
Okay. I'm good with that.
I have three questions real quick, and I promise they're quick.
Just because it will lead to the parking lot thing.
Is the current Polaris ranger still working?
Yes.
Nearing the end of its useful life.
Okay. And then the wood chipper, how much does it cost to contract that out?
I'm sorry, what?
The wood... Sorry, I'm going really fast. I apologize.
Wood.
The wood chipper, how much does it cost to contract that stuff out?
So, it's not inexpensive. We have a tree contract with Asplundh.
I don't know what their hourly rate is offhand.
Okay.
But having a chipper would make it easier for us to
just manage it in-house, do it in-house.
We would then keep the wood chips that we could use on trails or use it in our
parks.
Mm-hmm.
Carl, did you save some money on something this year and you may be looking to
repurpose-
Yeah, so-
... those funds with the council in this meeting?
Well, so-
... yes.
So
we are potentially saving about $100,000 on the purchase of our
bucket truck, which is funded this fiscal year, and I was planning, once
that's under contract, to come back to council and ask if I could use those
savings to fund the chipper and potentially other things that
are tree related. So, there is an opportunity to fund that
chipper with funds that have already been allocated for our
tree truck.
Okay. And then how do we increase the revenue at the golf course?
Because I want to use that money for everything.
I see this happening.
Charge non-South Portland residents a lot more.
Just remember, every cent that
the golf course generates stays at the golf course, so-
Oh, yeah
... for as much as I'd like to spread that wealth,
I'm going to be a little selfish on that one.
Councilor West, I think Councilor Mathews has a question.
Actually, I'll wait then, because I want to put something in the parking lot.
I'll wait.
Me too.
All right. I thought Councilor West had a question. Anyone else? Question.
Does not look like that.
Public comment on parks, rec, waterfront, and
golf course.
I don't see any public comment. We will close her down.
Counselors. Counselor Matthews, you may begin.
I would like to take and put in the parking
lot the
net to protect the condos that's in the '28 budget,
and move it to this budget this year.
Okay? Funding source?
CIP.
Oh, that's-
Or the golf course fund, right?
Yeah, the golf course fund. I mean, excuse me. When I say CIP...
Yeah, it's late.
Yeah.
You didn't chime in. You didn't say CIP is not a funding source.
I didn't mean that.
I heard it from over here.
I actually didn't mean that.
Yeah?
I meant-
Ellen yells at us all the time.
I meant fund balance.
All right.
CIP is not a funding source.
Golf course.
All right. So-
Golf course fund balance.
Keep it together, folks.
Yes, you have noted that in your-
Netting for condos-
Our parking lot attendant will note it
... funded by golf course.
Golf course fund balance.
All right.
Yep.
Natalie West. Oops.
If I understood this right, I want to take the netting for hole
five, that's still unprotected. Is that
correct? For the part that you said where they cut the trees?
That's still unprotected, yes.
Yeah. So I want to take that and put that in the parking lot for this year.
Yeah.
And the source would be the golf course fund.
Well, we'll get all this back on the golf course.
We'll get it. No, we'll get a cheaper rate if we get a whole bunch of netting.
Wait.
Economy's of scale.
We're going to buy a whole roll.
All right. Counselor Walker.
I want to talk about the ranger, the Polaris thingy.
Polaris.
Yeah.
With fund balance
Fund balance.
All right. Anyone else want to switcheroo,
recommend, change, push, do anything?
All right. Well, Carl.
Oh my God. I think we're finished.
Carl the merciful.
Thank you to all of the staff and all of the people
Anthony, aren't you glad you came?
Thank you.
Yes, very glad.
And I really thank all the staff members, most of whom are
gone. Thank heavens for them.
I'm sorry. You saw what happened.
There is no shortage of stuff to talk about in South Portland.
So all right. We still have a tiny little bit of this meeting to
finish.
Barely.
And where is it? A
review of our workshop schedule.
We're just looking at it. Do we have any decisions to make there?
The only thing, I just want to confirm we're okay to take off the Wainwright
Festival discussion since we talked to the family.
Oh, yeah, you did.
Because council put that on, we can just take it off.
We did. I mean, counselors.
Julie.
Yes.
Okay.
All right. So we're taking off-
Yep, and there's no workshop requests, so no action
All right. That is all good. We love that.
Do we have to do anything else? Oh, my goodness. I think we can just adjourn.
Yes?
Yep.
Thank you, everybody. The budget workshop is adjourned. Woo-hoo!